<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>quant-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/quant-ph</link>
    <description>quant-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/quant-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 05:00:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>GroverGPT: A Large Language Model with 8 Billion Parameters for Quantum Searching</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00135</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00135v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum computing is an exciting non-Von Neumann paradigm, offering provable speedups over classical computing for specific problems. However, the practical limits of classical simulatability for quantum circuits remain unclear, especially with current noisy quantum devices. In this work, we explore the potential of leveraging Large Language Models (LLMs) to simulate the output of a quantum Turing machine using Grover's quantum circuits, known to provide quadratic speedups over classical counterparts. To this end, we developed GroverGPT, a specialized model based on LLaMA's 8-billion-parameter architecture, trained on over 15 trillion tokens. Unlike brute-force state-vector simulations, which demand substantial computational resources, GroverGPT employs pattern recognition to approximate quantum search algorithms without explicitly representing quantum states. Analyzing 97K quantum search instances, GroverGPT consistently outperformed OpenAI's GPT-4o (45\% accuracy), achieving nearly 100\% accuracy on 6- and 10-qubit datasets when trained on 4-qubit or larger datasets. It also demonstrated strong generalization, surpassing 95\% accuracy for systems with over 20 qubits when trained on 3- to 6-qubit data. Analysis indicates GroverGPT captures quantum features of Grover's search rather than classical patterns, supported by novel prompting strategies to enhance performance. Although accuracy declines with increasing system size, these findings offer insights into the practical boundaries of classical simulatability. This work suggests task-specific LLMs can surpass general-purpose models like GPT-4o in quantum algorithm learning and serve as powerful tools for advancing quantum research.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00135v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haoran Wang, Pingzhi Li, Min Chen, Jinglei Cheng, Junyu Liu, Tianlong Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Coherence-Protection Scheme for Quantum Sensors Based on Ultra-Shallow Single Nitrogen-Vacancy Centers in Diamond</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00180</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00180v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent advances in the engineering of diamond surface make it possible to stabilize the charge state of 7-30 nanometers deep nitrogen-vacancy (NV) quantum sensors in diamond and to principally remove the charge noise at the surface. However, it is still a challenge to simultaneously increase the action volume of the quantum sensor by placing NV centers 0.5-2 nanometers deep and maintain their favorable spin coherence properties which will be definitely limited by the magnetic noise from the fluctuating nuclear spins of the terminating surface species of diamond. Here we show that leveraging the interplay of the surface induced strain and small constant magnetic fields, the spin coherence times of the ultra-shallow 1-nanometer deep NV center can be significantly enhanced up to the spin-phonon limited regime at room temperature in $^{12}$C enriched diamonds. We demonstrate that our measurement protocol is beneficial to $\sim$10-nanometers deep NV centers too in diamonds with naturally abundant carbon isotopes where the variable response of the spin bath to the direction of the small constant magnetic fields establishes vector magnetometry at the nanoscale.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00180v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anton Pershin, Andr\'as T\'ark\'anyi, Vladimir Verkhovlyuk, Viktor Iv\'ady, Adam Gali</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal asymptotic precision bounds for nonlinear quantum metrology under collective dephasing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00189</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00189v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Interactions among sensors can provide, in addition to entanglement, an important resource for boosting the precision in quantum estimation protocols. Dephasing noise, however, remains a leading source of decoherence in state-of-the-art quantum sensing platforms. We analyze the impact of classical {\em collective dephasing with arbitrary temporal correlations} on the performance of generalized Ramsey interferometry protocols with \emph{quadratic} encoding of a target frequency parameter. The optimal asymptotic precision bounds are derived for both product coherent spin states and for a class of experimentally relevant entangled spin-squeezed states of $N$ qubit sensors. While, as in linear metrology, entanglement offers no advantage if the noise is Markovian, a precision scaling of $N^{-1}$ is reachable with classical input states in the quadratic setting, which is improved to $N^{-5/4}$ when temporal correlations are present and the Zeno regime is accessible. The use of nonclassical spin-squeezed states and a nonlinear readout further allows for an $N^{-3/2}$ precision scaling, which we prove is asymptotically optimal. We also show how to counter {\em noise-induced bias} by introducing a simple ratio estimator which relies on detecting two suitable system observables, and show that it remains asymptotically unbiased in the presence of dephasing, without detriment to the achievable precision.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00189v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francisco Riberi, Lorenza Viola</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unraveling the switching dynamics in a quantum double-well potential</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00209</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00209v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The spontaneous switching of a quantum particle between the wells of a double-well potential is a phenomenon of general interest to physics and chemistry. It was broadly believed that the switching rate decreases steadily with the size of the energy barrier. This view was challenged by a recent experiment on a driven superconducting Kerr nonlinear oscillator (often called the Kerr-cat qubit or the Kerr parametric oscillator), whose energy barrier can be increased by ramping up the drive. Remarkably, as the drive amplitude increases, the switching rate exhibits a step-like decrease termed the "staircase". The view challenged by the experiment demands a deep review of our understanding of quantum effects in double wells. In this work, we derive a semi-analytical formula for the switching rate that resolves a continuous transition between tunneling- and dissipation-dominated dynamics. These two dynamics are observed respectively in the flat and the steep parts of each step in the staircase. Our formula exposes two distinct dissipative processes that limit tunneling: dephasing and decay. This allows us to predict the critical drive amplitudes where steps occur. In addition, we show that in the regime of a few states in the well and under moderate to low temperatures, highly excited states are populated predominantly via cascaded and direct thermal heating rather than quantum heating. At very low temperatures, however, the perturbation induced by the nonhermitian Hamiltonian becomes important and facilitates a new form of quantum heating. We numerically map the activation mechanism as a function of drive amplitude, damping rate, and temperature. Our theory deepens the understanding of switching dynamics between metastable quantum states, highlights the importance of a general interplay between tunneling and dissipation, and identifies a novel quantum regime in activated transitions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00209v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qile Su, Rodrigo G. Corti\~nas, Jayameenakshi Venkatraman, Shruti Puri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal Control in Nearly-Adiabatic Two-Level Quantum Systems via Time-Dependent Resonance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00293</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00293v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this study, we theoretically analyzed a control protocol based on ``time-dependent resonance" in nearly adiabatic two-level quantum systems, demonstrating that it exhibits properties equivalent to adiabatic control. This protocol is based on ``time-dependent resonance", where the frequency corresponds to the time-dependent energy gap. Through numerical calculations, we showed that this protocol serves as an optimal control protocol. This approach enables efficient and high-precision transitions to the target state. Our findings provide a new perspective on quantum optimal control theory and suggest potential applications in qubit controls and quantum information processing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00293v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takayuki Suzuki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Investigating Pure State Uniqueness in Tomography via Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00327</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00327v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum state tomography (QST) is crucial for understanding and characterizing quantum systems through measurement data. Traditional QST methods face scalability challenges, requiring $\mathcal{O}(d^2)$ measurements for a general $d$-dimensional state. This complexity can be substantially reduced to $\mathcal{O}(d)$ in pure state tomography, indicating that full measurements are unnecessary for pure states. In this paper, we investigate the conditions under which a given pure state can be uniquely determined by a subset of full measurements, focusing on the concepts of uniquely determined among pure states (UDP) and uniquely determined among all states (UDA). The UDP determination inherently involves non-convexity challenges, while the UDA determination, though convex, becomes computationally intensive for high-dimensional systems. To address these issues, we develop a unified framework based on the Augmented Lagrangian Method (ALM). Specifically, our theorem on the existence of low-rank solutions in QST allows us to reformulate the UDA problem with low-rank constraints, thereby reducing the number of variables involved. Our approach entails parameterizing quantum states and employing ALM to handle the constrained non-convex optimization tasks associated with UDP and low-rank UDA determinations. Numerical experiments conducted on qutrit systems and four-qubit symmetric states not only validate theoretical findings but also reveal the complete distribution of quantum states across three uniqueness categories: (A) UDA, (B) UDP but not UDA, and (C) neither UDP nor UDA. This work provides a practical approach for determining state uniqueness, advancing our understanding of quantum state reconstruction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00327v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiahui Wu, Zheng An, Chao Zhang, Xuanran Zhu, Shilin Huang, Bei Zeng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Supersinglets can be self-tested with perfect quantum strategies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00409</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00409v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Supersinglets are states of spin zero of $d \ge 3$ particles of $d$ levels. They are invariant under unitary transformations of the form $U^{\otimes d}$ and have applications in metrology, error protection, and communication. They also violate some specific Bell inequalities. However, neither any of these applications {\em require} supersinglets nor any of these of these Bell inequality violations capture the unique properties of the supersinglets. This leads to two questions. Question 1 is whether there exists a task that can only be solved with supersinglets. Question 2 is whether supersinglets can produce a unique $d$-partite, $d$-dimensional nonlocal signature. Here, we answer both questions affirmatively by presenting a protocol that self-test all supersinglets by producing $d$-partite, $d$-dimensional {\em perfect} quantum strategies for any $d \ge 3$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00409v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Debashis Saha, Ad\'an Cabello</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Violation of the Thermodynamic Uncertainty Relation in Quantum Collisional Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00627</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00627v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The thermodynamic uncertainty relation (TUR) is a fundamental principle in non-equilibrium thermodynamics that relates entropy production to fluctuations in a system, establishing a trade-off between the precision of an observable and the thermodynamic cost. Investigating TUR violations challenges classical thermodynamic limits, offering the potential for improved precision-entropy trade-offs, which is crucial for enhancing performance and optimization in quantum technologies. In this work, we investigate the thermodynamic uncertainty relation within a quantum collisional model, which offers the advantage of discretizing interactions into successive collisions with auxiliaries, allowing for precise tracking of dynamics and the incorporation of memory effects and non-Markovian behavior. We consider three types of dynamics in the collisional model: one is Markovian evolution, achieved by taking the continuous time limit and imposing the stability condition, while the other two are non-Markovian dynamics - one arising from increasing the collision time between the system and the auxiliaries, and the other from incorporating interactions between the auxiliaries. For the Markovian dynamics, we examine the classical and quantum TUR bounds in the non-equilibrium steady-state regime, and also the finite-time TUR bound. We demonstrate that the classical TUR bound is violated once a certain threshold of collisions with the auxiliaries is exceeded, with the maximum violation observed at the steady state. For the two non-Markovian approaches, we find that the violation of the finite-time TUR bound is highly dependent on the type of non-Markovianity, warranting a detailed comparison.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00627v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arghya Maity, Ahana Ghoshal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized Probability Theory: notes for a short course</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00718</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00718v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A slightly revised version of notes distributed during a short course on GPTs, given at the Perimeter Institute for Theoretical Physics in March and April of 2024.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00718v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alex Wilce</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Role of long-range interaction in critical quantum metrology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00771</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00771v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Long-range interacting quantum systems are useful for improving the performance of various applications of quantum technologies. In this work, we carry out a detailed analysis of how the long-range interaction affects the measurement precision in critical quantum metrology. By employing the paradigmatic model of a Kiteav chain with power-law decaying interaction, we focus on the impacts of long-range interaction on the critical sensing for the scenarios with and without uncertainty in system parameters.We show that the long-range interaction can be used as a valuable resource for enhancing the sensitivity of critical parameter estimation in both scenarios. Our findings not only provide more insights into the features of the long-range interacting systems, but also verify the usefulness of long-range interacting systems in quantum metrology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00771v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhen-Xia Niu, Qian Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermodynamic work and heat for a quantum process: Approach by Hamiltonian decomposition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00832</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00832v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The separation of internal energy into heat and work in quantum thermodynamics is a controversial issue for a long time, and we revisit and solve this problem in this work. It is shown that the Hamiltonian plays dual roles for a quantum system, and by decomposing the interaction Hamiltonian between system and environment accordingly, an ``effective Hamiltonian" for an open quantum system can be proposed. The explicit expression of the effective Hamiltonian is obtained systematically, and as a consequence, the internal energy of an open quantum system can be well defined, leading to the reasonable definitions of work and heat for a general quantum process.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00832v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tao Zhou, Jiangyang Pu, Xiaohua Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pseudorandom quantum authentication</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00951</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00951v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce the pseudorandom quantum authentication scheme (PQAS), an efficient method for encrypting quantum states that relies solely on the existence of pseudorandom unitaries (PRUs). The scheme guarantees that for any eavesdropper with quantum polynomial-time (QPT) computational power, the encrypted states are indistinguishable from the maximally mixed state. Furthermore, the receiver can verify that the state has not been tampered with and recover the original state with asymptotically unit fidelity. Our scheme is cost-effective, requiring only polylogarithmic circuit depth and a single shared key to encrypt a polynomial number of states. Notably, the PQAS can potentially exist even without quantum-secure one-way functions, requiring fundamentally weaker computational assumptions than semantic classical cryptography. Additionally, PQAS is secure against attacks that plague protocols based on QPT indistinguishability from Haar random states, such as chosen-plaintext attacks (CPAs) and attacks that reveal meta-information such as quantum resources. We relate the amount of meta-information that is leaked to quantum pseudoresources, giving the concept a practical meaning. As an application, we construct important cryptographic primitives, such as verifiable pseudorandom density matrices (VPRDMs), which are QPT-indistinguishable from random mixed states while being efficiently verifiable via a secret key, as well as verifiable noise-robust EFI pairs and one-way state generators (OWSGs). Our results establish a new paradigm of quantum information processing with weaker computational assumptions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00951v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tobias Haug, Nikhil Bansal, Wai-Keong Mok, Dax Enshan Koh, Kishor Bharti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exceptional point in a trimer chain of oscillators with a quadratic driving</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01033</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01033v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Exceptional points of a dissipative chain of three coupled oscillators (trimer), which is driven by quadratic photon, are investigated. The exceptional points emerge from the coalescence of both eigenvalues and eigenvectors of the dynamical matrix that describes the first moments of the trimer. At the exceptional point, we found that the optical spectrum is split into two peaks, instead of a conventional single peak, as in the case of a single oscillator. In particular, the positions of these peaks correspond to the natural frequency of the trimer in a \textit{closed system}, which depends only on the coupling strength. Furthermore, after passing the exceptional point, the peak positions do not change, which can be used to estimate the coupling strength between oscillators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01033v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M Shoufie Ukhtary, Albert Andersen, Donny Dwiputra, M. Jauhar Kholili</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detecting high-dimensional entanglement by local randomized projections</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01088</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01088v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The characterization of high-dimensional entanglement plays a crucial role in the field of quantum information science. Conventional methods perform either fixed measurement bases or randomized measurements with high-order moments. Here, we introduce a criterion for estimating the Schmidt number of bipartite high-dimensional states based on local randomized projections with first-order moments. To extract more information from limited experimental data, we propose an estimation algorithm of the Schmidt number. We exhibit the performance of the proposed approach by considering the maximally entangled state under depolarizing and random noise models. Our approach not only obtains a more accurate estimation of the Schmidt number but also reduces the number of projections compared to known methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01088v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jin-Min Liang, Shuheng Liu, Shao-Ming Fei, Qiongyi He</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symmetric quantum computation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01214</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01214v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce a systematic study of "symmetric quantum circuits", a restricted model of quantum computation where the restriction is symmetry-based. This model is well-adapted for studying the role of symmetries in quantum speedups, and it extends a powerful notion of symmetric computation studied in the classical setting.
  We show that symmetric quantum circuits go beyond the capabilities of their classical counterparts by efficiently implementing key quantum subroutines such as amplitude amplification and phase estimation, as well as the linear combination of unitaries technique. In addition, we consider the task of symmetric state preparation and show that it can be performed efficiently in several interesting and nontrivial cases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01214v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Davi Castro-Silva, Tom Gur, Sergii Strelchuk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized Recurrence Criteria for Classes of Open Quantum Walks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01249</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01249v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we study the recurrence of open quantum walks (OQWs) induced by finite-dimensional coins $(L,B,R)$. The focus is on homogeneous OQWs with a set of vertices $\mathbb{Z}$, the set of integers. We present three distinct recurrence criteria, each adapted to different types of coins. The first criterion was developed for a class of Lazy OQWs in any finite dimension, where the presented criterion is associated with an auxiliary map and its only invariant state, resulting in the first recurrence criterion for Lazy OQWs. The second one is restricted to Lazy OQWs of dimension 2, where we provide a complete characterization of the recurrence for this lower dimension. Finally, we present a general criterion for finite-dimensional coins in the non-lazy case $(B=0)$, which generalizes many of the previously known results. This new criterion holds for irreducible and reducible OQWs through a decomposition of the Hilbert space where our quantum states act.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01249v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Newton Loebens</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Four-Qubit Variational Algorithms in Silicon Photonics with Integrated Entangled Photon Sources</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01301</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01301v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Variational quantum algorithms are hybrid quantum-classical approaches extensively studied for their potential to leverage near-term quantum hardware for computational advantages. In this work, we successfully execute two variational quantum algorithms on a silicon photonic integrated circuit at room temperature: a variational quantum eigensolver for the Hydrogen molecule and a variational quantum factorization for semi-prime numbers. In our reconfigurable silicon photonic circuit, four identical spontaneous-four-wave-mixing-based integrated photon pair sources are used to prepare two path-entangled ququarts, whose correlation gives rise to the resource for generic trial states' preparation. This marks a first demonstration of variational quantum algorithms on a photonic quantum simulator with integrated photon pair sources.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01301v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alessio Baldazzi, Matteo Sanna, Massimo Borghi, Stefano Azzini, Lorenzo Pavesi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vacuum-induced atomic grating</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01385</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01385v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Atom-field interactions, induced by the vacuum of the electromagnetic field, exhibit a variety of fundamental phenomena and effects. In this paper, we study the electromagnetically induced atomic grating due to the vacuum state of the radiation field. Using an ensemble of cold atoms, strongly coupled to an optical cavity, we show that a probe field, propagating through the atomic medium, diffracts to zeroth and first-order diffraction peaks with few photons and even by the electromagnetic vacuum field of the cavity mode. As the number of photons in the cavity increases, the intensity of the first-order diffraction peak initially rises and then exhibits a decreasing trend. Furthermore, we observe that the first-order peak intensity reaches its maximum at resonance for both the vacuum and single-photon cavity state. However, as the number of photons increases further, this peak at resonance transforms into a dip, accompanied by two side peaks at off-resonance positions. This transition from a peak to a dip may potentially be used to distinguish the quantum state of the cavity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01385v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevA.110.063717</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. A 110, 063717 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Muhammad Shuraim, Muhammad Waseem, Shahid Qamar, Muhammad Irfan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Casimir Effect in Stochastic Semi-Classical Gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01415</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01415v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This article aims to examine the Casimir effect in the framework of stochastic semi-classical gravity. We commence with the semi-classical Einstein-Langevin equation, which introduces a first-order correction to the semi-classical gravity theory. Subsequently, we analyze the alteration in the Casimir force caused by this type of correction. Our results demonstrate that the corrections exhibit significant sensitivity to both the distance between the two parallel plates and the order parameter of the weak field. This finding underscores the nuanced interplay between these factors and the overall behavior of the system, providing valuable insights into the underlying dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01415v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Hossein. B. Khoshnevis, Sadaf Ebadi, M. Reza Lahooti, Reza Pirmoradian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intuitive Analysis of the Quantization-based Optimization: From Stochastic and Quantum Mechanical Perspective</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00436</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00436v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we present an intuitive analysis of the optimization technique based on the quantization of an objective function. Quantization of an objective function is an effective optimization methodology that decreases the measure of a level set containing several saddle points and local minima and finds the optimal point at the limit level set. To investigate the dynamics of quantization-based optimization, we derive an overdamped Langevin dynamics model from an intuitive analysis to minimize the level set by iterative quantization. We claim that quantization-based optimization involves the quantities of thermodynamical and quantum mechanical optimization as the core methodologies of global optimization. Furthermore, on the basis of the proposed SDE, we provide thermodynamic and quantum mechanical analysis with Witten-Laplacian. The simulation results with the benchmark functions, which compare the performance of the nonlinear optimization, demonstrate the validity of the quantization-based optimization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00436v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jinwuk Seok, Changsik Cho</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ensuring superior learning outcomes and data security for authorized learner</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00754</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00754v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The learner's ability to generate a hypothesis that closely approximates the target function is crucial in machine learning. Achieving this requires sufficient data; however, unauthorized access by an eavesdropping learner can lead to security risks. Thus, it is important to ensure the performance of the "authorized" learner by limiting the quality of the training data accessible to eavesdroppers. Unlike previous studies focusing on encryption or access controls, we provide a theorem to ensure superior learning outcomes exclusively for the authorized learner with quantum label encoding. In this context, we use the probably-approximately-correct (PAC) learning framework and introduce the concept of learning probability to quantitatively assess learner performance. Our theorem allows the condition that, given a training dataset, an authorized learner is guaranteed to achieve a certain quality of learning outcome, while eavesdroppers are not. Notably, this condition can be constructed based only on the authorized-learning-only measurable quantities of the training data, i.e., its size and noise degree. We validate our theoretical proofs and predictions through convolutional neural networks (CNNs) image classification learning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00754v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jeongho Bang, Wooyeong Song, Kyujin Shin, Yong-Su Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Maximally Extendable Product Codes are Good Coboundary Expanders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01411</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01411v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the coboundary expansion property of product codes called product expansion, which plays an important role in the recent constructions of good quantum LDPC codes and classical locally testable codes. Prior research revealed that this property is equivalent to agreement testability and robust testability for products of two codes of linear distance. However, for products of more than two codes, product expansion is a strictly stronger property. In this paper, we prove that the collection of random codes over a sufficiently large field has good product expansion. We believe that in the case of four codes, these ideas can be used to construct good quantum locally testable codes in a way similar to the current constructions using only products of two codes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01411v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gleb Kalachev, Pavel Panteleev</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
