<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>quant-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/quant-ph</link>
    <description>quant-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/quant-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 05:00:02 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Direct Steganography Scheme Based on Modified Generator Projection Directions of Steane Code over a Single-Type Pauli Channel</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07578</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07578v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In quantum mechanics, measurements of a quantum state in various directions yield distinct outcomes, a principle that forms the foundation of quantum communication theory. This paper expands upon this concept by introducing a method to modify generator projection directions (MGPD) within quantum stabilizer codes. Employing the Steane code ($(7,1,3)$ code), as a fundamental carrier, we develop a novel scheme for direct quantum steganography across a single-type Pauli channel. The infeasibility of eavesdropping decoding under MGPD is proven. We detail the steganographic encoding and decoding schemes, corresponding quantum circuits, and eavesdropping detection principles. We also use a 'Sudoku'-style strategy to balance steganographic error probabilities and provide the complete steganography protocol. Relative to existing studies, the MGPD method achieves embedding rates approaching and attaining the upper limit of the information capacity for the $(n,k,d)=(7,1,3)$ code within a noise probability range of approximately $1/(n+1)=12.5\%$. It also reduces the consumption of auxiliary keys from $O(\log{(N)})$ to $O(1)$, while enabling eavesdropping detection and steganography of arbitrary quantum states. We investigate its potential applications in quantum communication and assess its benefits in the context of secret information transmission and eavesdropping detection in noisy channels. Although the MGPD method incorporates certain idealized assumptions and limitations, it provides novel perspectives on the concealment of quantum information.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07578v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chaolong Hao, Quangong Ma, Dan Qu, Dawei Shi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Computing Enhanced Sensing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07625</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07625v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum computing and quantum sensing represent two distinct frontiers of quantum information science. In this work, we harness quantum computing to solve a fundamental and practically important sensing problem: the detection of weak oscillating fields with unknown strength and frequency. We present a quantum computing enhanced sensing protocol that outperforms all existing approaches. Furthermore, we prove our approach is optimal by establishing the Grover-Heisenberg limit -- a fundamental lower bound on the minimum sensing time. The key idea is to robustly digitize the continuous, analog signal into a discrete operation, which is then integrated into a quantum algorithm. Our metrological gain originates from quantum computation, distinguishing our protocol from conventional sensing approaches. Indeed, we prove that broad classes of protocols based on quantum Fisher information, finite-lifetime quantum memory, or classical signal processing are strictly less powerful. Our protocol is compatible with multiple experimental platforms. We propose and analyze a proof-of-principle experiment using nitrogen-vacancy centers, where meaningful improvements are achievable using current technology. This work establishes quantum computation as a powerful new resource for advancing sensing capabilities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07625v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Richard R. Allen, Francisco Machado, Isaac L. Chuang, Hsin-Yuan Huang, Soonwon Choi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vacuum fluctuations induced decoherence of a diamagnetic nanosphere</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07632</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07632v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper provides a simple derivation of the decoherence rate for a diamagnetic nanoparticle in the presence of vacuum fluctuations of the magnetic field. Diamagnetic levitation is one of the key techniques for trapping, cooling, and creating a macroscopic quantum spatial superposition in many experiments. It is widely applied in many theoretical and experimental endeavors to test fundamental physics in matter-wave interferometers. To estimate the decoherence rate originating from magnetic-field fluctuations, we use the fluctuation-dissipation theorem. We show that our resulting decoherence rate expression is analogous to that of dielectric material in the presence of vacuum fluctuations due to the electric background field component; however, it is often relatively suppressed due to the material properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07632v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruiyun Zhang, Martine Schut, Anupam Mazumdar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-Markovian two-time correlation functions for optomechanical systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07678</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07678v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we focus on the two-time correlation function (TTCF) of the cavity optomechanical system, which serves as the most popular tool in precision detection technologies. We utilize the stochastic Schrodinger equation approach to study TTCF for the cavity optomechanical system in the long-time steady state TTCF and time-dependent case. Our numerical simulations support two major conclusions: (1) long-time steady states in Markovian and non-Markovian regimes are different, resulting in the distinct TTCF, and (2) the time-dependent TTCF can reveal more information about the environment, rather than the traditional spectral function method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07678v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yusui Chen, Kaiqi Xiong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantifying the imaginarity via different distance measures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07775</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07775v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The recently introduced resource theory of imaginarity facilitates a systematic investigation into the role of complex numbers in quantum mechanics and quantum information theory. In this work, we propose well-defined measures of imaginarity using various distance metrics, drawing inspiration from recent advancements in quantum entanglement and coherence. Specifically, we focus on quantitatively evaluating imaginarity through measures such as Tsallis relative $\alpha$-entropy, Sandwiched R\'{e}nyi relative entropy, and Tsallis relative operator entropy. Additionally, we analyze the decay rates of these measures. Our findings reveal that the Tsallis relative $\alpha$-entropy of imaginarity exhibits higher decay rate under quantum channels compared to other measures. Finally, we examine the ordering of single-qubit states under these imaginarity measures, demonstrating that the order remains invariant under the bit-flip channel for specific parameter ranges. This study enhances our understanding of imaginarity as a quantum resource and its potential applications in quantum information theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07775v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1002/qute.202400562</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Adv. Quantum Technol. 2025, 2400562</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Meng-Li Guo, Si-Yin Huang, Bo Li, Shao-Ming Fei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exact amplitudes of parametric processes in driven Josephson circuits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07784</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07784v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a general approach for analyzing arbitrary parametric processes in Josephson circuits within a single degree of freedom approximation. Introducing a systematic normal-ordered expansion for the Hamiltonian of parametrically driven superconducting circuits we present a flexible procedure to describe parametric processes and to compare different circuit designs for particular applications. We obtain formally exact amplitudes (`supercoefficients') of these parametric processes for driven SNAIL-based and SQUID-based circuits. The corresponding amplitudes contain complete information about the circuit topology, the form of the nonlinearity, and the parametric drive, making them, in particular, well-suited for the study of the strong drive regime. We present a closed-form expression for supercoefficients describing circuits without stray inductors and a tractable formulation for those with it. We demonstrate the versatility of the approach by applying it to the estimation of Kerr-cat qubit Hamiltonian parameters and by examining the criterion for the emergence of chaos in Kerr-cat qubits. Additionally, we extend the approach to multi-degree-of-freedom circuits comprising multiple linear modes weakly coupled to a single nonlinear mode. We apply this generalized framework to study the activation of a beam-splitter interaction between two cavities coupled via driven nonlinear elements. Finally, utilizing the flexibility of the proposed approach, we separately derive supercoefficients for the higher-harmonics model of Josephson junctions, circuits with multiple drives, and the expansion of the Hamiltonian in the exact eigenstate basis for Josephson circuits with specific symmetries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07784v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Roman Baskov, Daniel K. Weiss, Steven M. Girvin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Decomposition of unitary matrix into quantum gates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07786</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07786v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: An algorithm is proposed to convert arbitrary unitary matrix to a sequence of $X$ gates and fully controlled $R_y, R_z$ and $R_1$ gates. This algorithm is used to generate Q# implementation for arbitrary unitary matrix. Some optimizations are considered and complexity of the result is analyzed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07786v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dmytro Fedoriaka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Klein-Gordon equation with relativistic mass: a relativistic Schr\"odinger equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07798</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07798v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Klein-Gordon equation describes the wave-like behavior of spinless particles since it is Lorentz invariant. While it seemed initially ripe for explaining the electronic structure of the hydrogen atom, the disagreement with experimental results and the lack of a positive probability density really limited its applications. Yet, it is intimately connected with fermions. Any solution of the Dirac equation is automatically a solution of the Klein-Gordon equation. What is even more surprising, the Klein-Gordon equation for a free particle turns into the Schr\"odinger equation in the non-relativistic limit. However, when we replace the rest mass of a particle with its relativistic mass, the Klein-Gordon equation losses its Lorentz invariance and cannot describe spinless particles anymore. Instead, it gains most of the features present the Schr\"odinger equation, including the unconditional positivity of probability density, while keeping most of its relativistic characteristics intact, including the matter-wave dispersion relation. What is even more surprising, the non-relativistic, quasi-static limit of the Klein-Gordon equation with relativistic mass is simply the Schr\"odinger equation. It can be argued that this Klein-Gordon equation is a sort of relativistic Schr\"odinger equation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07798v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>P. -A. Gourdain</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Qudit Cirq Library: An Extension of Google's Cirq Library for Qudits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07812</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07812v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This document contains a guide on how to use the Qudit Cirq library, an extension of Google's Cirq library for qudits. While Cirq provides necessary building blocks for quantum computation on qudits, the gates, curcuits and simulation of qudit systems need to be developed from scratch. Our extension to the Cirq library has built-in methods for creating qudits, applying common qudit gates, building circuits and simulating quantum computation on these circuits. This is ideal for researchers who want to use an off-the-shelf library to simulate qudit systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07812v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Svyatoslav Kushnarev, Hassan Jameel Asghar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New Quantum Algorithm for Principal Component Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07891</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07891v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum principal component analysis (QPCA) ignited a new development toward quantum machine learning algorithms. Initially showcasing as an active way for analyzing a quantum system using the quantum state itself, QPCA also found potential application in analyzing a large-scale dataset, represented by the so-called covariance matrix. Inspired by recent advancement in quantum algorithms, we give an alternatively new quantum framework for performing principal component analysis. By analyzing the performance in detail, we shall identify the regime in which our proposal performs better than the original QPCA. In addition, we also provide a new approach for preparing the covariance matrix, given classical dataset, on a quantum computer. Thus, our work provides an efficient complementary framework for revealing features of the quantum state, while keeping the philosophy of original QPCA, as the state could play an active role in analyzing itself.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07891v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nhat A. Nghiem</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vacuum Propellion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07908</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07908v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Investigations show that a time-varying $\delta-\delta'$ mirror gives rise to asymmetrical vacuum radiation on its two sides, enabling one to extract propelling forces from the vacuum fluctuation. In this work, we propose a design of Casimir device to gain propulsions out of vacuum with conventional $\delta$ mirrors. We call this device a ``vacuum propellion'', which is experimentally feasible. It consists of a cavity made up of a perfectly reflective left mirror and a right mirror with time dependent transparency. All particles generated from this propellion are preferentially right-moving, so the cavity obtains a left-pointing propelling force.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07908v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu-Song Cao, YanXia Liu, Ding-Fang Zeng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Retrieving Lost Atomic Information: Monte Carlo-based Parameter Reconstruction of an Optical Quantum System</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07951</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07951v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In regimes of low signal strengths and therefore a small signal-to-noise ratio, standard data analysis methods often fail to accurately estimate system properties. We present a method based on Monte Carlo simulations to effectively restore robust parameter estimates from large sets of undersampled data. This approach is illustrated through the analysis of photoluminescence excitation spectroscopy data for optical linewidth characterization of a nitrogen-vacancy color center in diamond. We evaluate the quality of parameter prediction using standard statistical data analysis methods, such as the median, and the Monte Carlo method. Depending on the signal strength, we find that the median can be precise (narrow confidence intervals) but very inaccurate. A detailed analysis across a broad range of parameters allows to identify the experimental conditions under which the median provides a reliable predictor of the quantum emitter's linewidth. We also explore machine learning to perform the same task, forming a promising addition to the parameter estimation toolkit. Finally, the developed method offers a broadly applicable tool for accurate parameter prediction from low signal data, opening new experimental regimes previously deemed inaccessible.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07951v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Laura Orphal-Kobin, Gregor Pieplow, Alok Gokhale, Kilian Unterguggenberger, Tim Schr\"oder</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>QGHNN: A quantum graph Hamiltonian neural network</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07986</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07986v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Representing and learning from graphs is essential for developing effective machine learning models tailored to non-Euclidean data. While Graph Neural Networks (GNNs) strive to address the challenges posed by complex, high-dimensional graph data, Quantum Neural Networks (QNNs) present a compelling alternative due to their potential for quantum parallelism. However, much of the current QNN research tends to overlook the vital connection between quantum state encoding and graph structures, which limits the full exploitation of quantum computational advantages. To address these challenges, this paper introduces a quantum graph Hamiltonian neural network (QGHNN) to enhance graph representation and learning on noisy intermediate-scale quantum computers. Concretely, a quantum graph Hamiltonian learning method (QGHL) is first created by mapping graphs to the Hamiltonian of the topological quantum system. Then, QGHNN based on QGHL is presented, which trains parameters by minimizing the loss function and uses the gradient descent method to learn the graph. Experiments on the PennyLane quantum platform reveal that QGHNN outperforms all assessment metrics, achieving the lowest mean squared error of \textbf{$0.004$} and the maximum cosine similarity of \textbf{$99.8\%$}, which shows that QGHNN not only excels in representing and learning graph information, but it also has high robustness ability. QGHNN can reduce the impact of quantum noise and has significant potential application in future research of quantum knowledge graphs and recommendation systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07986v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wenxuan Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Noise-resistant adaptive Hamiltonian learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08017</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08017v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Mitigating and reducing noise influence is crucial for obtaining precise experimental results from noisy intermediate-scale quantum (NISQ) devices. In this work, an adaptive Hamiltonian learning (AHL) model for data analysis and quantum state simulation is proposed to overcome problems such as low efficiency and the noise influence of quantum machine learning algorithms. First, an adaptive parameterized quantum circuit with noise resistant ability is constructed by decomposing the unitary operators that include penalty Hamiltonian in the topological quantum system. Then, a noise-resistant quantum neural network (RQNN) based on AHL is developed, which improves the noise robustness of the quantum neural network by updating iterative parameters. Finally, the experiments on Paddle Quantum demonstrate that RQNN can simulate the mathematical function and get accurate classification results on NISQ devices. Compared with the quantum neural network, RQNN ensures high accuracy with the same non-linear discrete data classification under the impact of amplitude damping noise, with an accuracy of 98.00 $\%$. It provides new possibilities for solving practical issues on NISQ devices and also benefits in the resolution of increasingly complicated problems, which will expand the range of potential applications for quantum machine learning models in the future.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08017v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wenxuan Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Decoding Quantum LDPC Codes using Collaborative Check Node Removal</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08036</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08036v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The fault tolerance of quantum devices requires on-par contributions from error-correcting codes and suitable decoders.
  One of the most explored error-correcting codes is the family of Quantum Low-Density Parity Check (QLDPC) codes.
  Although faster than many of the reported decoders for QLDPC codes, iterative decoders fail due to the colossal degeneracy and short cycles intrinsic to these codes.
  We present a strategy to improve the performance of the iterative decoders based on a collaborative way to use the message passing of the iterative decoders and check node removal from the code's Tanner graph.
  We use the concept of bit separation and generalize it to qubit separation.
  This gives us a metric to analyze and improve the decoder's performance towards harmful configurations of QLDPC codes.
  We present a simple decoding architecture to overcome iterative decoding failures by increasing the separation of trapped qubits without incurring any significant overhead.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08036v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mainak Bhattacharyya, Ankur Raina</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Decoherence time of the ground state spin of $V_{B}$ centers in hexagonal boron nitride</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08055</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08055v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The ground-state spin of optically active defects in hexagonal boron nitride (hBN) offers a promising platform for quantum information applications, such as qubits for quantum computing and nanoscale sensing. A key characteristic of a qubit is its decoherence time, as its duration and controllability are critical for practical applications in quantum technologies. In this work, we investigate the electron spin decoherence time of the negatively charged boron vacancies, $V_{B}$ centers, in the hBN lattice by considering the dipolar hyperfine as well as spin-phonon interactions. We employ an approximate method based on the Holstein-Primakoff transformation to take into account a large number of nuclear spins and Debye model to consider the effect of lattice phonons. We show that, in the presence of the dipolar hyperfine interactions, Hahn-echo coherence time of the $V_{B}$ electron spin is approximately $30\: \mathrm{\mu s}$ at room temperature, close to the previously reported results. Our findings suggest that the major source of decoherence is the noise caused by nuclear spins in the lattice. Our results provide a step forward in understanding the $V_{B}$ defect decoherence in the hBN, which might be used for quantum information applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08055v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fatemeh Tarighi Tabesh, Saleh Rahimi-Keshari, Mehdi Abdi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interfacing superconducting nanowire single photon detectors with cryogenic opto-electronics for quantum photonic applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08125</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08125v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Interfacing single-photon detectors with active photonic components is a cornerstone photonic quantum technology. We describe how the output signal of commercial superconducting nanowire single-photon detectors can be used in situ to drive photonic components such as lasers and electro-optic modulators, co-located in the cryostat. This is enabled by developing custom circuitry using cryogenic-compatible discrete components in the SiGe-BiCMOS platform. We have demonstrated this with a number of experiments, in particular optical readout of an SNSPD and low-latency feed-forward modulation based on single-photon measurement events, all at or below 4 K. This manuscript is an abridged version of the Master thesis of the primary author N. Lamberty.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08125v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Niklas Lamberty, Frederik Thiele, Thomas Hummel, Tim J. Bartley</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optical information encryption using general temporal ghost imaging with practical experimental condition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08136</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08136v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Temporal Ghost Imaging (TGI), which reconstructs fast temporal signals using a slow detector, holds significant potential in optical communication, high-speed imaging, and quantum information processing. However, achieving high-quality information reconstruction has been a major challenge for the practical application of TGI. A theoretical model [\emph{ Applied Optics}, 62(5): 1175-1182 (2023)] was proposed to investigate the influence of experimental parameters of the slow detector on image quality; however, its experimental verification was hitherto lacking. In this study, we implemented a multi-bit information transmission scheme based on both quantum and classical TGI methods. Experimental validation confirmed the accuracy of the theoretical model and demonstrated its application in encrypting noisy multi-bit information. The experimental results demonstrate that as the information coding density increases, the decoding accuracy becomes highly sensitive to the detection accuracy and threshold of the slow detector. When these parameters degrade, the decoding quality deteriorates significantly. Additionally, our system shows notable robustness against detection noise, but loses the ability to accurately decode when the noise amplitude becomes too high. Our work endows TGI with optical information encryption capabilities in practical systems and furnishes comprehensive guidelines for the further application of TGI.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08136v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Juan Wu, Xiaohai Zhan, Fang-Xiang Wang, Zhenqiu Zhong, Shuang Wang, Wei Chen, Zhen-Qiang Yin, Zheng-Fu Han</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
