<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>quant-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/quant-ph</link>
    <description>quant-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/quant-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 05:00:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Optimization of Quantum-Repeater Networks using Stochastic Automatic Differentiation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.06291</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.06291v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum repeaters are envisioned to enable long-distance entanglement distribution. Analysis of quantum-repeater networks could hasten their realization by informing design decisions and research priorities. Determining derivatives of network properties is crucial towards that end, facilitating optimizations and revealing parameter sensitivity. Doing so, however, is difficult because the networks are discretely random. Here we use a recently developed technique, stochastic automatic differentiation, to automatically extract derivatives from discrete Monte Carlo simulations of repeater networks. With these derivatives, we optimize rate-fidelity tradeoffs in a repeater chain, determine the chain's sensitivity with respect to the coherence times of different nodes, and finally choose the locations of quantum repeaters in a two-dimensional plane to optimize the guaranteed quality of service between four end nodes. In particular, the technique enabled us to discover how the best achievable quality of service, the minimal number of repeaters required to improve a network, and the number of repeaters required to saturate the network scale with the physical size of the network.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.06291v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guus Avis, Stefan Krastanov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Arithmetic sequences as quantum states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.06292</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.06292v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider arithmetic sequences, here defined as ordered lists of positive integers. Any such a sequence can be cast onto a quantum state, enabling the quantification of its `surprise' through von Neumann entropy. We identify typical sequences that maximize entanglement entropy across all bipartitions and derive an analytical approximation as a function of the sequence length. This quantum-inspired approach offers a novel perspective for analyzing randomness in arithmetic sequences.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.06292v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruge Lin, Germ\'an Sierra, Jos\'e I. Latorre</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Classical Attack on Bell Inequalities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.06331</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.06331v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Representing multi-mode squeezed light with a Gaussian random vector, our locally deterministic detection model challenges the CHSH game, achieving fidelities exceeding 96\%. Squeezing strength, detector threshold, and efficiency influence the security of the quantum bound.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.06331v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1364/QUANTUM.2024.QTh3A.7</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Quantum 2.0 Conference and Exhibition, Technical Digest Series (Optica Publishing Group, 2024), paper QTh3A.7</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Aishi Guha, Noah A. Davis, Brian R. La Cour</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neutral atom entangling gate in the ultrastrong coupling regime</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.06359</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.06359v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a method to deterministically entangle qubits or ensembles of qubits interacting with a shared bosonic mode in the ultrastrong coupling regime. We show that the resulting gate is a product of two unitaries: one unitary acts only on the quantum state of the qubits and entangles them, while the other acts only on the quantum state of the boson, producing a phase shift. We find that the gate time is inversely proportional to the qubit-boson interaction strength, and by tuning the qubit-boson interaction strength, one can prepare a maximally entangled state or a squeezed state. Applying the quantum gate to multiple qubit ensembles, we show that the quantum gate prepares a Schr\"odinger cat state. We also examine imperfections such as including free evolution of the qubits, and show that this produces an effective mixing. Our proposal is feasible for ultrastrong coupling experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.06359v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ebubechukwu O. Ilo-Okeke, Tongzhou Wang, Valentin Ivannikov, Tim Byrnes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Experimental Test of Nonlocality Limits from Relativistic Independence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.06385</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.06385v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum correlations, like entanglement, represent the characteristic trait of quantum mechanics, and pose essential issues and challenges to the interpretation of this pillar of modern physics. Although quantum correlations are largely acknowledged as a major resource to achieve quantum advantage in many tasks of quantum technologies, their full quantitative description and the axiomatic basis underlying them are still under investigation. Previous works suggested that the origin of nonlocal correlations is grounded in principles capturing (from outside the quantum formalism) the essence of quantum uncertainty. In particular, the recently-introduced principle of Relativistic Independence gave rise to a new bound intertwining local and nonlocal correlations. Here we test such a bound by realizing together sequential and joint weak measurements on entangled photon pairs, allowing to simultaneously quantify both local and nonlocal correlations by measuring incompatible observables on the same quantum system without collapsing its state, a task typically forbidden in the traditional (projective) quantum measurement framework. Our results demonstrate the existence of a fundamental limit on the extent of quantum correlations, shedding light on the profound role of uncertainty in both enabling and balancing them.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.06385v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PRXQuantum.5.040351</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>PRX Quantum 5, 040351 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Francesco Atzori, Salvatore Virz\`i, Enrico Rebufello, Alessio Avella, Fabrizio Piacentini, Iris Cusini, Henri Haka, Federica Villa, Marco Gramegna, Eliahu Cohen, Ivo Pietro Degiovanni, Marco Genovese</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A graph-based approach to entanglement entropy of quantum error correcting codes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.06407</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.06407v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We develop a graph-based method to study the entanglement entropy of Calderbank-Shor-Steane quantum codes. This method offers a straightforward interpretation for the entanglement entropy of quantum error correcting codes through graph-theoretical concepts, shedding light on the origins of both the local and long-range entanglement. Furthermore, it inspires an efficient computational scheme for evaluating the entanglement entropy. We illustrate the method by calculating the von Neumann entropy of subsystems in toric codes and a special type of quantum low-density-parity check codes, known as bivariate bicycle codes, and by comparing the scaling behavior of entanglement entropy with respect to subsystem size. Our method provides a new perspective for understanding the entanglement structure in quantum many-body systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.06407v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wuxu Zhao, Menglong Fang, Daiqin Su</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probability Density in Relativistic Quantum Mechanics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.06518</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.06518v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the realm of relativistic quantum mechanics, we address a fundamental question: Which one, between the Dirac or the Foldy-Wouthuysen density, accurately provide a probability density for finding a massive particle with spin $1/2$ at a certain position and time. Recently, concerns about the Dirac density's validity have arisen due to the Zitterbewegung phenomenon, characterized by a peculiar fast-oscillating solution of the coordinate operator that disrupts the classical relation among velocity, momentum, and energy. To explore this, we applied Newton and Wigner's method to define proper position operators and their eigenstates in both representations, identifying 'localized states' orthogonal to their spatially displaced counterparts. Our analysis shows that both densities could represent the probability of locating a particle within a few Compton wavelengths. However, a critical analysis of Lorentz transformation properties reveals that only the Dirac density meets all essential physical criteria for a relativistic probability density. These criteria include covariance of the position eigenstate, adherence to a continuity equation, and Lorentz invariance of the probability of finding a particle. Our results provide a clear and consistent interpretation of the probability density for a massive spin-$1/2$ particle in relativistic quantum mechanics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.06518v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Taeseung Choi, Yeong Deok Han</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gaussian R\'enyi-2 correlations in a nondegenerate three-level laser</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.06556</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.06556v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum correlation is a key component in various quantum information processing tasks. Decoherence process imposes limitations on achieving these quantum tasks. Therefore, understanding the behavior of quantum correlations in dissipative-noisy systems is of paramount importance. Here, on the basis of the Gaussian R\'{e}nyi-2 entropy, we analyze entanglement and quantum discord in a two-mode Gaussian state $\rho_{AB}$. The mode $A$($B$) is generated within the first(second) transition of a nondegenerate three-level cascade laser. Using realistic experimental parameters, we show that both entanglement and discord could be generated and enhanced by inducing more quantum coherence. Under thermal noise, entanglement is found more fragile having a tendency to disappear rapidly. While, quantum discord exhibits a freezing behavior, where it can be captured within a wide range of temperature. Surprisingly, we find that entanglement can exceed quantum discord in contrary to the expectation based on the assumption that the former is only a part of the later. Finally, we show numerically as well as analytically that optimal quantum discord can be captured by performing Gaussian measurements on mode $B$. The obtained results suggest that nondegenerate three-level lasers may be a valuable resource for some quantum information tasks, especially, for those do not require entanglement.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.06556v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s11128-024-04294-0</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Quantum Information Processing, (2024) 23:83</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jamal El Qars</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gauge invariance of the natural lineshape and dissipative dynamics of a two-level atom</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.06594</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.06594v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The natural lineshape of an excited two-level atom (TLA) has long been known to be gauge-dependent, with certain experiments in better agreement with the lineshape calculated with the dipole gauge. We show that by using a Coulomb gauge Hamiltonian truncated in a manner consistent with the gauge principle, the correct output spectrum can be obtained. For TLAs undergoing dynamics arising from additional Hamiltonian couplings, we also show that the master equation is gauge-invariant under the same conditions of validity as the Born-Markov approximation, despite different gauges having different spectral densities. These results highlight the importance of using correctly truncated gauge-invariant Hamiltonians in input-output theory for accurate frequency-dependent spectra, even in weak coupling regimes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.06594v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chris Gustin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-Markovian Noise in Symmetry-Preserving Quantum Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.06619</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.06619v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In quantum dynamics, symmetries are vital for identifying and assessing conserved quantities that govern the evolution of a quantum system. When promoted to the open quantum system setting, dynamical symmetries can be negatively altered by system-environment interactions, thus, complicating their analysis. Previous work on noisy symmetric quantum dynamics has focused on the Markovian setting, despite the ubiquity of non-Markovian noise in a number of widely used quantum technologies. In this study, we develop a framework for quantifying the impact of non-Markovian noise on symmetric quantum evolution via root space decompositions and the filter function formalism. We demonstrate analytically that symmetry-preserving noise maintains the symmetric subspace, while non-symmetric noise leads to highly specific leakage errors. We support our findings with a numerical study of the transverse field Ising model subject to spatiotemporally correlated noise. Our results are broadly applicable, providing new analytic insights into the control and characterization of open quantum system dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.06619v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>William M. Watkins, Gregory Quiroz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Synthetic $\pi$-flux system in 2D superconducting qubit array with tunable coupling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.06743</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.06743v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Flat-band systems provide an ideal platform for exploring exotic quantum phenomena, where the strongly suppressed kinetic energy in these flat energy bands suggests the potential for exotic phases driven by geometric structure, disorder, and interactions. While intriguing phenomena and physical mechanisms have been unveiled in theoretical models, synthesizing such systems within scalable quantum platforms remains challenging. Here, we present the experimental realization of a $\pi$-flux rhombic system using a two-dimensional superconducting qubit array with tunable coupling. We experimentally observe characteristic dynamics, e.g., $\pi$-flux driven destructive interference, and demonstrate the protocol for eigenstate preparation in this rhombic array with coupler-assisted flux. Our results provide future possibilities for exploring the interplay of geometry, interactions, and quantum information encoding in such degenerate systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.06743v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yiting Liu, Jiawei Zhang, Zechen Guo, Peisheng Huang, Wenhui Huang, Yongqi Liang, Jiawei Qiu, Xuandong Sun, Zilin Wang, Changrong Xie, Xiaohan Yang, Jiajian Zhang, Libo Zhang, Ji Chu, Weijie Guo, Ji Jiang, Xiayu Linpeng, Song Liu, Jingjing Niu, Yuxuan Zhou, Wenhui Ren, Ziyu Tao, Youpeng Zhong, Dapeng Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comfortability of quantum walks on embedded graphs on surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.06765</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.06765v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, a quantum walk model which reflects the underlying embedding on the surface is proposed. We obtain the scattering matrix of this quantum walk model characterized by the faces on the surface, and find a detection of the orientablility of the underlying embedding by the scattering information. The comfortability is the square norm of the stationary state restricted to the internal and reflected by the underlying embedding. We find that quantum walker feels more comfortable to a surface with small genus in some natural setting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.06765v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yusuke Higuchi, Etsuo Segawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optical phase estimation via homodyne measurement in the presence of saturation effect of photodetectors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.06768</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.06768v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: For optical phase estimation via homodyne measurement, we generalize the theory from detector's linear to nonlinear response regime, which accounts for the presence of saturation effect. For optical coherent light, we carry out analytic expressions for detector's current and estimate precision. Using specific device parameters, we illustrate the improved estimation after accounting for the saturation effect.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.06768v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jialin Li, Yazhi Niu, Lupei Qin, Xin-Qi Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capability of anti-degradable quantum channel with additional entanglement</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.06839</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.06839v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum communication theory focuses on the study of quantum channels for transmitting quantum information, where the transmission rate is measured by quantum channel capacity. This quantity exhibits several intriguing properties, such as non-additivity, superactivation and so on. In this work, we show that a type of quantum channel known as the anti-degradable one-mode Gaussian channel -- whose capacity is believed to be zero -- can be ``activated" to transmit quantum information through the introduction of quantum entanglement. Although the channel's output alone cannot be used to retrieve the input signal, combining it with extra entanglement makes this possible. Beyond its theoretical implications, this activation can also be realized in practical systems. For example, in electro-optic systems used for quantum transduction in the two-mode squeezing interaction regime, the transduction channel is anti-degradable. We demonstrate that this system can transmit microwave-optical quantum information with the assistance of entanglement with an ancillary mode. This results in a new type of quantum transducer that exhibits positive quantum capacity over a wide parameter space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.06839v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Changchun Zhong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the eternal non-Markovianity of qubit maps</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.06846</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.06846v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: As is well known, unital Pauli maps can be eternally non-CP-divisible. In contrast, here we show that in the case of non-unital maps, eternal non-Markovianity in the non-unital part is ruled out. In the unital case, the eternal non-Markovianity can be obtained by a convex combination of two dephasing semigroups, but not all three of them. We study these results and the ramifications arising from them.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.06846v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vinayak Jagadish, R. Srikanth</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is Born-Jordan really the universal Path Integral Quantization Rule?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.06979</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.06979v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: It has been argued that the Feynman path integral formalism leads to a quantization rule, and that the Born-Jordan rule is the unique quantization rule consistent with the correct short-time propagator behavior of the propagator for non-relativistic systems. We examine this short-time approximation and conclude, contrary to prevailing views, that the asymptotic expansion applies only to Hamiltonian functions that are at most quadratic in the momentum and with constant mass. While the Born-Jordan rule suggests the appropriate quantization of functions in this class, there are other rules which give the same answer, most notably the Weyl quantization scheme.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.06979v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>John E. Gough</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>QSteed: Quantum Software of Compilation for Supporting Real Quantum Device</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.06993</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.06993v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present QSteed, a quantum compilation system that can be deployed on real quantum computing devices and quantum computing clusters. It is designed to meet the challenges of effectively compiling quantum tasks and managing multiple quantum backends. The system integrates two core components: a quantum compiler and a quantum computing resource virtualization manager, both of which provide standardized interfaces. The resource manager models quantum chips into different abstract layers, including the real quantum processing unit (QPU), the standard QPU (StdQPU), the substructure QPU (SubQPU), and the virtual QPU (VQPU), and stores this information in a quantum computing resource virtualization database, thus realizing the unified management of quantum computing devices. The quantum compiler adopts a modular and extensible design, providing a flexible framework for customizing compilation optimization strategies. It provides hardware-aware compilation algorithms that account for quantum gate noise and qubit coupling structures. By selecting the most suitable computing resources from the VQPU library, the compiler maps quantum tasks to the optimal qubit regions of the target device. We validated the effectiveness of the QSteed on the superconducting devices of the Quafu quantum cloud computing cluster. The quantum computing resource virtualization management technology of QSteed and the flexible and extensible design of its compiler make it possible to achieve unified management and task compilation for backend devices of multiple physical systems such as neutral-atom and ion-trap.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.06993v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hong-Ze Xu, Zheng-An Wang, Yu-Long Feng, Yu Chen, Xinpeng Zhang, Jingbo Wang, Xu-Dan Chai, Wei-Feng Zhuang, Yu-Xin Jin, Yirong Jin, Haifeng Yu, Heng Fan, Meng-Jun Hu, Dong E. Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum signal processing without angle finding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07002</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07002v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum signal processing (QSP) has emerged as a unifying subroutine in quantum algorithms. In QSP, we are given a function $f$ and a unitary black-box $U$, and the goal is to construct a quantum circuit for implementing $f(U)$ to a given precision. The existing approaches to performing QSP require a classical preprocessing step to compute rotation angle parameters for quantum circuits that implement $f$ approximately. However, this classical computation often becomes a bottleneck, limiting the scalability and practicality of QSP. In this work, we propose a novel approach to QSP that bypasses the computationally intensive angle-finding step. Our method leverages a quantum circuit for implementing a diagonal operator that encodes $f$, which can be constructed from a classical circuit for evaluating $f$. This approach to QSP simplifies the circuit design significantly while enabling nearly optimal implementation of functions of block-encoded Hermitian matrices for black-box functions. Our circuit closely resembles the phase estimation-based circuit for function implementation, challenging conventional skepticism about its efficiency. By reducing classical overhead, our work significantly broadens the applicability of QSP in quantum computing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07002v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abhijeet Alase</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improving key rates by tighter information reconciliation leakage estimation for quantum key distribution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07006</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07006v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Previous research has aimed to precisely estimate information leakage to improve the secure key rate (SKR) and maximum transmission distance in quantum key distribution (QKD). However, existing methods repeatedly considerd the information of the multi-photon pulses known to Eve before and after information reconciliation, resulting in an overestimation of the leakage amount. We propose a novel approach that considers the quantum part's effect on post-processing, providing a more accurate estimation of information reconciliation leakage to improve the SKR. Theoretical analysis shows that our method more accurately estimates the information reconciliation leakage, significantly improving the SKR at any distance as well as the maximum transmission distance. It is worth mentioning that previous studies treat information leakage of the error correction as Shannon bound $Nh(e)$, and our method can estimate it more tightly. Simulation results for decoy-BB84 and measurement-device-independent (MDI) protocols using Cascade are consistent with the theoretical analysis. The farther the transmission distance, the greater the growth rate of SKR. When the error rate is 33%, compared with the original method, the SKR growth rate of decoy-BB84 at 100KM is 100.4%, and the transmission distance of MDI increases by 22KM.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07006v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hao-Kun Mao, Bo Yang, Yu-Cheng Qiao, Bing-Ze Yan, Qiang Zhao, Bing-Jie Xu, Qiong Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Periodically poled thin-film lithium niobate ring Mach Zehnder coupling interferometer for efficient quantum frequency conversion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07010</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07010v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum frequency conversion is unavoidable for a true quantum communication network as most quantum memories work in the visible spectrum. Here, we propose a unique design of a quantum frequency converter based on a ring-Mach Zehnder interferometer coupled with a periodically poled thin-film lithium niobate waveguide. The proposed device can be-directionally convert quantum signals i.e. single photons from quantum memory such as SiV-center in diamond to the telecom wavelength offering conversion efficiency as high as 90% at mW pump power with noise photon rate below 0.1Hz.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07010v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mrinmoy Kundu, Bejoy Sikder, Mark Earnshaw, A. Sayem</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Necessary and sufficient condition for constructing a single qudit insertion/deletion code and its decoding algorithm</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07027</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07027v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper shows that Knill-Laflamme condition, known as a necessary and sufficient condition for quantum error-correction, can be applied to quantum errors where the number of particles changes before and after the error. This fact shows that correctabilities of single deletion errors and single insertion errors are equivalent. By applying Knill-Laflamme condition, we generalize the previously known correction conditions for single insertion and deletion errors to necessary and sufficient level. By giving an example that satisfies this condition, we construct a new single qudit insertion/deletion code and explain its decoding algorithm.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07027v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Taro Shibayama</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New Circuit for Quantum Adder by Constant</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07060</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07060v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a new circuit for in-place addition of a classical $n$-bit constant to a quantum $n$-qubit integer modulo $2^n$. Our circuit uses $n-3$ ancilla qubits and has a T-count of $4n-5$. We also propose controlled version of this circuit that uses $n-2$ ancillas and has a T-count of $11n-15$. We implement these circuits in Q#.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07060v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dmytro Fedoriaka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PPO-Q: Proximal Policy Optimization with Parametrized Quantum Policies or Values</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07085</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07085v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum machine learning (QML), which combines quantum computing with machine learning, is widely believed to hold the potential to outperform traditional machine learning in the era of noisy intermediate-scale quantum (NISQ). As one of the most important types of QML, quantum reinforcement learning (QRL) with parameterized quantum circuits as agents has received extensive attention in the past few years. Various algorithms and techniques have been introduced, demonstrating the effectiveness of QRL in solving some popular benchmark environments such as CartPole, FrozenLake, and MountainCar. However, tackling more complex environments with continuous action spaces and high-dimensional state spaces remains challenging within the existing QRL framework. Here we present PPO-Q, which, by integrating hybrid quantum-classical networks into the actor or critic part of the proximal policy optimization (PPO) algorithm, achieves state-of-the-art performance in a range of complex environments with significantly reduced training parameters. The hybrid quantum-classical networks in the PPO-Q incorporate two additional traditional neural networks to aid the parameterized quantum circuits in managing high-dimensional state encoding and action selection. When evaluated on 8 diverse environments, including four with continuous action space, the PPO-Q achieved comparable performance with the PPO algorithm but with significantly reduced training parameters. Especially, we accomplished the BipedalWalker environment, with a high-dimensional state and continuous action space simultaneously, which has not previously been reported in the QRL. More importantly, the PPO-Q is very friendly to the current NISQ hardware. We successfully trained two representative environments on the real superconducting quantum devices via the Quafu quantum cloud service.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07085v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu-Xin Jin, Zi-Wei Wang, Hong-Ze Xu, Wei-Feng Zhuang, Meng-Jun Hu, Dong E. Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bosonic Amplitude-Damping Codes Beyond Binomial Schemes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07093</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07093v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce two new families of bosonic quantum error correction (QEC) codes to address collective coherent and amplitude-damping errors, building upon our previous multi-qubit QEC codes. These new bosonic codes enhance existing binomial codes for oscillators and permutation-invariant codes for qubits by reducing the required excitations per input qubit from linear to sub-linear growth. The mappings from multi-qubit stabilizer codes to bosonic codes establish a bridge between QEC code construction for qubits and oscillators, offering a unified approach to error correction across different quantum systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07093v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>En-Jui Chang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tensor decomposition technique for qubit encoding of maximal-fidelity Lorentzian orbitals in real-space quantum chemistry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07211</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07211v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: To simulate the real- and imaginary-time evolution of a many-electron system on a quantum computer based on the first-quantized formalism, we need to encode molecular orbitals (MOs) into qubit states for typical initial-state preparation. We propose an efficient scheme for encoding an MO as a many-qubit state from a Gaussian-type solution that can be obtained from a tractable solver on a classical computer. We employ the discrete Lorentzian functions (LFs) as a fitting basis set, for which we maximize the fidelity to find the optimal Tucker-form state to represent a target MO. For $n_{\mathrm{prod}}$ three-dimensional LFs, we provide the explicit circuit construction for the state preparation involving $\mathcal{O} (n_{\mathrm{prod}})$ CNOT gates. Furthermore, we introduce a tensor decomposition technique to construct a canonical-form state to approximate the Tucker-form state with controllable accuracy. Rank-$R$ decomposition reduces the CNOT gate count to $\mathcal{O} (R n_{\mathrm{prod}}^{1/3}).$ We demonstrate via numerical simulations that the proposed scheme is a powerful tool for encoding MOs of various quantum chemical systems, paving the way for first-quantized calculations using hundreds or more logical qubits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07211v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Taichi Kosugi, Xinchi Huang, Hirofumi Nishi, Yu-ichiro Matsushita</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Characterization of Entanglement in Higher Dimensional Bipartite as well as Multipartite Quantum System and its Application</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07242</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07242v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In recent years considerable progress has been made towards developing a general theory of quantum entanglement. In particular, criteria to decide whether a given quantum state is entangled are of high theoretical and practical interest. This problem is additionally complicated by the existence of bound entanglement, which are weak entangled states and hard to detect. In this thesis, we have worked on the characterization of bipartite and tripartite entanglement. We have established a few separability criteria that successfully detect Negative Partial Transpose (NPT) as well as Positive Partial Transpose (PPT) entangled states. Although the topic of detection of entanglement has been extensively studied in the literature through many approaches, the majority of these criteria are not physically realizable. This means that they are well accepted in the mathematical language but cannot be implemented in a laboratory setting. In this thesis, we propose some theoretical ideas to realize these entanglement detection criteria experimentally.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07242v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shruti Aggarwal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multipartite quantum correlated bright frequency combs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07252</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07252v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This experimental work demonstrates multipartite quantum correlation in bright frequency combs out of a microresonator integrated on silicon nitride working above its oscillation threshold. Multipartite features, going beyond so far reported two-mode correlation, naturally arise due to a cascade of non-linear optical processes, making a single-color laser pump sufficient to initiate their generation. Our results show the transition from two-mode to multipartite correlation, witnessed by noise reductions as low as $-2.5$\,dB and $-2$\,dB, respectively, compared to corresponding classical levels. A constant of the movement of the non-linear interaction Hamiltonian is identified and used to asses the multipartite behavior. Reported demonstrations pave the way to next generation on-chip multipartite sources for quantum technologies applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07252v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adrien Bensemhoun, Silvia Cassina, Carlos Gonzalez-Arciniegas, Mohamed Fauzi Melalkia, Giuseppe Patera, Jonathan Faugier-Tovar, Quentin Wilmart, S\'egol\`ene Olivier, Alessandro Zavatta, Anthony Martin, Jean Etesse, Laurent Labont\'e, Olivier Pfister, Virginia D'Auria, S\'ebastien Tanzilli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Selective band interaction and long-range hopping in a structured environment with giant atoms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07254</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07254v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Giant atoms, which couple to the environment at multiple discrete points, exhibit various nontrivial phenomena in quantum optics due to their nonlocal couplings. In this study, we propose a one-dimensional cross-stitch ladder lattice featuring both a dispersive band and a flat band. By modulating the relative phase between the coupling points, the giant atom selectively interacts with either band. First, we analyze the scenario where the dispersive and flat bands intersect at two points, and the atomic frequency lies within the band. Unlike the small atom, which simultaneously interacts with both bands, a single giant atom with a controllable phase interacts exclusively with the dispersive or flat band. Second, in the bandgap regime, where two atoms interact through bound-state overlaps manifesting as dipole-dipole interactions, we demonstrate that giant atoms enable deterministic long-range hopping and energy exchange with higher fidelity compared to small atoms. These findings provide promising applications in quantum information processing, offering enhanced controllability and selectivity for quantum systems and devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07254v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ying Xia, Jia-Qi Li, Xin Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Estimating quantum relative entropies on quantum computers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07292</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07292v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum relative entropy, a quantum generalization of the well-known Kullback-Leibler divergence, serves as a fundamental measure of the distinguishability between quantum states and plays a pivotal role in quantum information science. Despite its importance, efficiently estimating quantum relative entropy between two quantum states on quantum computers remains a significant challenge. In this work, we propose the first quantum algorithm for estimating quantum relative entropy and Petz R\'{e}nyi divergence from two unknown quantum states on quantum computers, addressing open problems highlighted in [Phys. Rev. A 109, 032431 (2024)] and [IEEE Trans. Inf. Theory 70, 5653-5680 (2024)]. This is achieved by combining quadrature approximations of relative entropies, the variational representation of quantum f-divergences, and a new technique for parameterizing Hermitian polynomial operators to estimate their traces with quantum states. Notably, the circuit size of our algorithm is at most 2n+1 with n being the number of qubits in the quantum states and it is directly applicable to distributed scenarios, where quantum states to be compared are hosted on cross-platform quantum computers. We validate our algorithm through numerical simulations, laying the groundwork for its future deployment on quantum hardware devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07292v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuchen Lu, Kun Fang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Secure quantum bit commtiment from separable operations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07351</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07351v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Bit commitment is a fundamental cryptographic primitive and a cornerstone for numerous two-party cryptographic protocols, including zero-knowledge proofs. However, it has been proven that unconditionally secure bit commitment, both classical and quantum, is impossible. In this work, we demonstrate that imposing a restriction on the committing party to perform only separable operations enables secure quantum bit commitment schemes. Specifically, we prove that in any perfectly hiding bit commitment protocol, an honestly-committing party limited to separable operations will be detected with high probability if they attempt to alter their commitment. To illustrate our findings, we present an example protocol.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07351v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ziad Chaoui, Anna Pappa, Matteo Rosati</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhancing the sensitivity of single microwave photon detection with bandwidth tunability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07354</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07354v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report on the characteristics of a microwave photon counter device based on a superconducting transmon qubit. Its design is similar to [arXiv:2307.03614], with an additional bandwidth tuning circuit that allows optimizing the device efficiency and noise. Owing to this new feature and to improvements in device fabrication, a power sensitivity of $3 \cdot 10^{-23} \mathrm{W}/\sqrt{\mathrm{Hz}}$ is reached. We confirm the high performance of the device by measuring single spin microwave fluorescence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07354v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Louis Pallegoix, Jaime Travesedo, Alexandre S. May, L\'eo Balembois, Denis Vion, Patrice Bertet, Emmanuel Flurin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient Quantum Circuit Compilation for Near-Term Quantum Advantage</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07387</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07387v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum noise in real-world devices poses a significant challenge in achieving practical quantum advantage, since accurately compiled and executed circuits are typically deep and highly susceptible to decoherence. To facilitate the implementation of complex quantum algorithms on noisy hardware, we propose an approximate method for compiling target quantum circuits into brick-wall layouts. This new circuit design consists of two-qubit CNOT gates that can be directly implemented on real quantum computers, in conjunction with optimized one-qubit gates, to approximate the essential dynamics of the original circuit while significantly reducing its depth. Our approach is evaluated through numerical simulations of time-evolution circuits for the critical Ising model, quantum Fourier transformation, and Haar-random quantum circuits, as well as experiments on IBM quantum platforms. By accounting for compilation error and circuit noise, we demonstrate that time evolution and quantum Fourier transformation circuits achieve high compression rates, while random quantum circuits are less compressible. The degree of compression is related to the rate of entanglement accumulation in the target circuit. In particular, experiments on IBM platforms achieve a compression rate of $12.5$ for $N=12$, significantly extending the application of current quantum devices. Furthermore, large-scale numerical simulations for system sizes up to $N=30$ reveal that the optimal depth $d_{\mathrm{max}}$ to achieve maximal overall fidelity is independent of system size $N$, suggesting the scalability of our method for large quantum devices in terms of quantum resources.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07387v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuchen Guo, Shuo Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reconstruction of quantum states by applying an analytical optimization model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07404</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07404v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: When working with quantum states, analysis of the final quantum state generated through probabilistic measurements is essential. This analysis is typically conducted by constructing the density matrix from either partial or full tomography measurements of the quantum state. While full tomography measurement offers the most accurate reconstruction of the density matrix, limited measurements pose challenges for reconstruction algorithms, often resulting in non-physical density matrices with negative eigenvalues. This is often remedied using maximum likelihood estimators, which have a high computing time or by other estimation methods that decrease the reconstructed fidelity. In this study, we show that when restricting the measurement sample size, improvement over existing algorithms can be achieved. Our findings underline the multiplicity of solutions in the reconstruction problem, depending upon the generated state and measurement model utilized, thus motivating further research towards identifying optimal algorithms tailored to specific experimental contexts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07404v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rohit Prasad, Pratyay Ghosh, Ronny Thomale, Tobias Huber-Loyola</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Characterisation of Open Quantum System Dynamics based on Information Back-flow</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07422</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07422v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: For unital dynamics, we show that a generalized trace distance measure offers no advantage over the trace distance measure for witnessing non-Markovianity. We determine the class of non-unital channels where the standard trace distance measure is insufficient here and the generalized measure is necessary. Finally, we assess the status of the GTD measure as an indicator of information flow between an open system and its environment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07422v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vijay Pathak, R. Srikanth</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Equivalence between exponential concentration in quantum machine learning kernels and barren plateaus in variational algorithms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07433</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07433v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We formalize a rigorous connection between barren plateaus (BP) in variational quantum
  algorithms and exponential concentration of quantum kernels for machine learning. Our
  results imply that recently proposed strategies to build BP-free quantum circuits can be
  utilized to construct useful quantum kernels for machine learning. This is illustrated by
  a numerical example employing a provably BP-free quantum neural network to construct
  kernel matrices for classification datasets of increasing dimensionality without exponential
  concentration.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07433v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pranav Kairon, Jonas J\"ager, Roman V. Krems</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological Operations Around Exceptional Points via Shortcuts to Adiabaticity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07454</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07454v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The existence of singularities in the spectrum of non-Hermitian Hamiltonians leads to a non-trivial spectral topology which can be exploited to generate topological operations. However, their implementation has remained elusive due to the difficulty of generating a true adiabatic evolution. Here, we develop fast, robust control protocols that generate a desired topological operation. Our strategy relies on shortcuts to adiabaticity, but is not a trivial extension. The presence of spectral singularities renders the strategy developed for Hermitian Hamiltonians impractical as it will lead to faulty control protocols. Moreover, due to the dynamics sensitivity to parameter uncertainties, not all shortcuts to adiabaticity can be used in a realistic setting. We illustrate our method in the context of a two-mode non-Hermitian Hamiltonian and discuss why in general celebrated shortcuts to adiabaticiy like transitionless driving and superadiabatic transitionless driving are not appropriate control protocols for non-Hermitian systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07454v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vishnu Chavva, Hugo Ribeiro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stabilization of quantum properties under intrinsic decoherence in presence of external magnetic fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07464</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07464v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The dynamical behavior of quantum state properties under intrinsic decoherence models can be modified by the presence of external magnetic fields. Although generically external magnetic fields are detrimental to preserve quantumness in the presence of intrinsic decoherence, judicious adjustment of the magnetic field can stabilize such features. This stabilization arises from novel resonances between energy eigenstates resulting from the presence of an external magnetic field. Here, we present our findings using as a model system two spin 1-particles confined in a double-well potential under intrinsic decoherence. We stress, however, that our results are generic and independent on the used model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07464v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Essalha Chaouki, Anna Sanpera, Mostafa Mansour</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamics in an emergent quantum-like state space generated by a nonlinear classical network</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07500</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07500v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work exploits a framework whereby a graph (in the mathematical sense) serves to connect a classical system to a state space that we call `quantum-like' (QL). The QL states comprise arbitrary superpositions of states in a tensor product basis. The graph plays a special dual role by directing design of the classical system and defining the state space. We study a specific example of a large, dynamical classical system -- a system of coupled phase oscillators -- that maps, via a graph, to the QL state space. We investigate how mixedness of the state diminishes or increases as the underlying classical system synchronizes or de-synchronizes respectively. This shows the interplay between the nonlinear dynamics of the variables of the classical system and the QL state space. We prove that maps from one time point to another in the state space are linear maps. In the limit of a strongly phase-locked classical network -- that is, where couplings between phase oscillators are very large -- the state space evolves according to unitary dynamics, whereas in the cases of weaker synchronization, the classical variables act as a hidden environment that promotes decoherence of superpositions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07500v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gregory D. Scholes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Floquet-engineered system-reservoir interaction in the transverse field Ising model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07527</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07527v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Periodically driving a quantum many-body system can drastically change its properties, leading to exotic non-equilibrium states of matter without a static analog. In this scenario, parametric resonances and the complexity of an interacting many-body system are pivotal in establishing non-equilibrium states. We report on a Floquet-engineered transverse field Ising model for the controlled propagation in one dimension of spin waves. The underlying mechanisms behind our proposal rely on high-frequency drivings using characteristic parametric resonances of the spin lattice. Many-body resonances modulating spin-sping exchange or individual spin gaps inhibit interactions between spins thus proving a mechanism for controlling spin-wave propagation and a quantum switch. Our schemes may have applications in coupling-decoupling schemes for system-reservoir interaction, and routing in quantum networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07527v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maritza Ahumada, Natalia Valderrama-Quinteros, Guillermo Romero</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tensorization of neural networks for improved privacy and interpretability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.06300</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.06300v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a tensorization algorithm for constructing tensor train representations of functions, drawing on sketching and cross interpolation ideas. The method only requires black-box access to the target function and a small set of sample points defining the domain of interest. Thus, it is particularly well-suited for machine learning models, where the domain of interest is naturally defined by the training dataset. We show that this approach can be used to enhance the privacy and interpretability of neural network models. Specifically, we apply our decomposition to (i) obfuscate neural networks whose parameters encode patterns tied to the training data distribution, and (ii) estimate topological phases of matter that are easily accessible from the tensor train representation. Additionally, we show that this tensorization can serve as an efficient initialization method for optimizing tensor trains in general settings, and that, for model compression, our algorithm achieves a superior trade-off between memory and time complexity compared to conventional tensorization methods of neural networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.06300v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jos\'e Ram\'on Pareja Monturiol, Alejandro Pozas-Kerstjens, David P\'erez-Garc\'ia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Black-box optimization and quantum annealing for filtering out mislabeled training instances</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.06916</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.06916v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This study proposes an approach for removing mislabeled instances from contaminated training datasets by combining surrogate model-based black-box optimization (BBO) with postprocessing and quantum annealing. Mislabeled training instances, a common issue in real-world datasets, often degrade model generalization, necessitating robust and efficient noise-removal strategies. The proposed method evaluates filtered training subsets based on validation loss, iteratively refines loss estimates through surrogate model-based BBO with postprocessing, and leverages quantum annealing to efficiently sample diverse training subsets with low validation error. Experiments on a noisy majority bit task demonstrate the method's ability to prioritize the removal of high-risk mislabeled instances. Integrating D-Wave's clique sampler running on a physical quantum annealer achieves faster optimization and higher-quality training subsets compared to OpenJij's simulated quantum annealing sampler or Neal's simulated annealing sampler, offering a scalable framework for enhancing dataset quality. This work highlights the effectiveness of the proposed method for supervised learning tasks, with future directions including its application to unsupervised learning, real-world datasets, and large-scale implementations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.06916v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Makoto Otsuka, Kento Kodama, Keisuke Morita, Masayuki Ohzeki</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
