<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>quant-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/quant-ph</link>
    <description>quant-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/quant-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2025 05:00:09 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>IQPopt: Fast optimization of instantaneous quantum polynomial circuits in JAX</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.04776</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.04776v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: IQPopt is a software package designed to optimize large-scale instantaneous quantum polynomial circuits on classical hardware. By exploiting an efficient classical simulation algorithm for expectation value estimation, circuits with thousands of qubits and millions of gates can be optimized, provided the relevant objective function has an efficient description in terms of Pauli-Z type observables. Since sampling from instantaneous quantum polynomial circuits is widely believed to be hard for classical computers, this provides a method to identify powerful circuit instances before deployment and sampling on quantum hardware, where computational advantages may exist. The package leverages automatic differentiation in JAX, can be accelerated with access to hardware accelerators such as graphics processing units, and contains a dedicated module that can be used to train and evaluate quantum generative models via the maximum mean discrepancy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.04776v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Erik Recio-Armengol, Joseph Bowles</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Using quantum nonlocality for device-independent confirmation of relativistic effects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.04780</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.04780v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Synchronizing clocks to measure time is a fundamental process underpinning every practical communication task from GPS to parallel computation. However, as the current protocols are based on classical communication between the sender and receiver, they are prone to simple attacks that could cause a slight delay in the signal which would then cause a massive error in further operations. In this work, we first explain a simple attack that in principle can cause an arbitrary delay in the signal between sender and receiver. We then propose a way to overcome this problem by using a recently contrived idea of device-independent certification which utilises quantum nonlocality. Consequently, clocks can be synchronized in a highly secure way without trusting any devices in the setup. We then extend this proposal to observe relativistic time dilation in a device-independent manner.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.04780v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shubhayan Sarkar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Hybrid Support Vector Machines for Stress Detection in Older Adults</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.04831</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.04831v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Stress can increase the possibility of cognitive impairment and decrease the quality of life in older adults. Smart healthcare can deploy quantum machine learning to enable preventive and diagnostic support. This work introduces a unique technique to address stress detection as an anomaly detection problem that uses quantum hybrid support vector machines. With the help of a wearable smartwatch, we mapped baseline sensor reading as normal data and stressed sensor reading as anomaly data using cortisol concentration as the ground truth. We have used quantum computing techniques to explore the complex feature spaces with kernel-based preprocessing. We illustrate the usefulness of our method by doing experimental validation on 40 older adults with the help of the TSST protocol. Our findings highlight that using a limited number of features, quantum machine learning provides improved accuracy compared to classical methods. We also observed that the recall value using quantum machine learning is higher compared to the classical method. The higher recall value illustrates the potential of quantum machine learning in healthcare, as missing anomalies could result in delayed diagnostics or treatment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.04831v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Md Saif Hassan Onim, Travis S. Humble, Himanshu Thapliyal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An examination of the extended Hong-Ou-Mandel effect and considerations for experimental detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.04849</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.04849v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In recent works we have explored a multi-photon extension of the celebrated two-photon Hong-Ou-Mandel (HOM) effect in which the quantum amplitudes for a two-photon input to a lossless, balanced 50:50 beamsplitter (BS) undergoes complete destructive interference. In the extended Hong-Ou-Mandel (eHOM) effect the multi-photon scattering of photons from the two input ports to the two output ports of the BS for Fock number basis input states (FS) $|n,m\rangle_{12}$ exhibit complete destructive interference pairwise within the quantum amplitudes containing many scattering components, generalizing the two-photon HOM effect. This has profound implications for arbitrary bipartite photonic input states constructed from such basis states: if the input state to one input port of the BS is of odd parity, i.e. constructed from only of odd numbers of photons, then regardless of the input state to the second 50:50 BS port, there will be a central nodal line (CNL) of zeros in the joint output probability distribution along the main diagonal for coincidence detection. The first goal of this present work is to show diagrammatically how the extended HOM effect can be seen as a succession of multi-photon HOM effects when the latter is viewed as a pairwise cancellation of mirror image scattering amplitudes. The second goal of this work is to explore considerations for the experimental realization of the extended Hong-Ou-Mandel effect. We examine the case of a single photon interfering with a coherent state (an idealized laser) on a balanced 50:50 beamsplitter and consider prospects for experimental detection of the output destructive interference by including additional effects such as imperfect detection efficiency, spatio-temporal mode functions, and time delay between the detected output photons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.04849v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paul M. Alsing, Richard J. Birrittella</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beyond Integral-Domain Stabilizer Codes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.04888</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.04888v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum error-correcting codes aim to protect information in quantum systems to enable fault-tolerant quantum computations. The most prevalent method, stabilizer codes, has been well developed for many varieties of systems, however, largely the case of composite number of levels in the system has been avoided. This relative absence is due to the underlying ring theoretic tools required for analyzing such systems. Here we explore composite local-dimension quantum stabilizer codes, providing a pair of constructions for transforming known stabilizer codes into valid ones for composite local-dimensions. In addition remarks on logical encodings and the counts possible are discussed. This work lays out central methods for working with composite dimensional systems, enabling full use of the computational space of some systems, and expanding the understanding of the symplectic spaces involved.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.04888v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lane G. Gunderman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entanglement-Assisted Concatenated Quantum Codes: Parameters and Asymptotic Performance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.04921</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.04921v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Entanglement-assisted concatenated quantum codes (EACQCs) are constructed by concatenating two entanglement-assisted quantum error-correcting codes (EAQECCs). By selecting the inner and outer component codes carefully, it is able to construct state-of-the-art EACQCs with parameters better than previous quantum codes. In this work, we use almost maximum-distance-separable (MDS) codes and $\hbar$-MDS codes as the outer codes to construct EACQCs. Because the range of code length of almost MDS and $\hbar$-MDS codes is much more free than that of the commonly used MDS codes. We derive several families of new EACQCs with parameters better than the previously best known EAQECCs and standard quantum error-correcting codes (QECCs) of the same length and net transmissions. Moreover, we demonstrate that EACQCs are with maximal entanglement if both the inner and outer component codes are with maximal entanglement. As a result, we construct three new maximal-entanglement EACQCs which have optimal parameters. In addition, we present several new maximal-entanglement EACQCs whose minimum distance is only one less than the minimum distance of the optimal codes. In particular, we propose two new families of asymptotically good maximal-entanglement EACQCs with explicit constructions by using entanglement-assisted quantum algebraic geometry codes as the outer codes. At last, we prove that EACQCs can attain the quantum Gilbert-Varshamov bound for EAQECCs asymptotically.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.04921v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jihao Fan, Wei Cheng, Gaojun Luo, Zhou Li, Meng Cao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Synchronization in microwave optomechanical circuits via coupling engineering to a common environment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.04922</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.04922v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Synchronization is one of the essential collective behaviors and has extensive applications. Exploiting a common environment, we establish synchronization in microwave optomechanical circuits. Through analysis and numerical calculations, we study the synchronization dynamics of three nonidentical and mechanically isolated optomechanical resonators. Each resonator supports a microwave mode and a mechanical mode, which are coupled via radiation-pressure type optomechanical interaction. The common environment induces indirect coupling between any two resonators, which can be described by an effective non-Hermitian interaction Hamiltonian. Combined with the Hermitian interaction regulated by the tunable coupler, we demonstrate that the common environment breaks the reciprocity of the interaction. We propose several special microwave optomechanical circuits with nonreciprocal or even unidirectional interactions, and study the regulation of synchronization dynamics by the common environment. By utilizing the excellent tunability of superconducting circuits, we show that different synchronization states can be switched in a controllable way. This work may open up a new way for synchronization research and have potential applications in synchronization networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.04922v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yun-Qiu Ge, Min-Chen Qiao, Yu-xi Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-fidelity Generation of Bell and W States in Giant Atom System via Bound State in the Continuum</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.04954</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.04954v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we propose a high-fidelity scheme for generating entangled states in a system of two and three giant atoms coupled to the coupled resonator waveguide. Our approach leverages the bound state in the continuum, which is robust against waveguide disorder. Specifically, we achieve a fidelity exceeding $98\%$ for Bell state generation, overcoming the limitations of conventional decoherence-free interaction mechanisms. This scheme can be readily extended to a three-giant-atom system for generating W states. In both the two- and three-atom setups, the maximally entangled states are generated in a short time and remain stable even as time approaches infinity. Our proposal is feasible for implementation on state-of-the-art solid-state quantum platforms and significantly broadens the applications of giant atoms and waveguide QED system in quantum information processing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.04954v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mingzhu Weng, Hongwei Yu, Zhihai Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Experimental Realization of Criticality-Enhanced Global Quantum Sensing via Non-Equilibrium Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.04955</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.04955v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum critical systems offer promising advancements in quantum sensing and metrology, yet face limitations like critical slowing down and a restricted criticality-enhanced region. Here, we introduce a critical sensing scheme that mitigate critical slowing down by leveraging the non-equilibrium dynamics of a perturbed Ising spin model, coupled with an adaptive strategy to enlarge its sensing interval. We validate the proposed scheme on a superconducting quantum processor and demonstrate that our scheme achieves a Heisenberg scaling with respect to the encoding duration. Additionally, the adaptive strategy tunes the model to operate near its critical point with limited prior information about the parameter, enabling what is known as global sensing. Our work showcases the metrological applications empowered by non-equilibrium critical dynamics and hence opens up a pathway for devising critical quantum sensors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.04955v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yefei Yu, Ran Liu, Guangming Xue, Chuhong Yang, Chenlu Wang, Jingning Zhang, Jiangyu Cui, Xiaodong Yang, Jun Li, Jiaxiu Han, Haifeng Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improved finite-size analysis for measurement-device-independent quantum digital signature</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.04957</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.04957v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum digital signatures (QDS), based on the principles of quantum mechanics, provide information-theoretic security, ensuring the integrity, authenticity, and non-repudiation of data transmission. With present QDS protocols, measurement-device-independent QDS (MDI-QDS) can resist all attacks on detections, yet it suffers from finite-size effect. In this work, we present and compare three parameter estimation models for finite-size analysis of two-decoy MDI-QDS. The first model is a commonly used model in previous schemes, and we propose two new models to improve the performance. Subsequently, we perform numerical simulations to evaluate the performance of the three models. The results demonstrate that the proposed methods are less affected by finite-size effect, thereby effectively enhancing the signature rate. This work contributes to the practical development of QDS.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.04957v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jia-Li Zhu, Chun-Hui Zhang, Yue-Ying Wang, Qin Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Theoretical study of the Spectroscopic measurements of Kerr non-linear resonators with four-body interaction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.04981</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.04981v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum annealing provides a promising way to solve combinational optimization problems where the solutions correspond to the ground state of the Ising Hamiltonian. We can implement quantum annealing using the Kerr non-linear resonators, with bifurcation phenomena emerging when subjected to a parametric drive. These bifurcated states can function as bases of qubits. Moreover, integrating four-body interactions between physical qubits enables the establishment of effective all-to-all long-range interactions between logical qubits, which is essential for practical quantum annealing. While theoretical proposals exist for creating four-body interactions within Kerr non-linear resonators, there has not been experimental verification through their spectroscopic signatures. In this paper, we theoretically investigate the spectroscopic measurements of Kerr non-linear resonators featuring four-body interaction. We identify six distinct frequencies exhibiting population changes by employing resonant driving on one resonator and weak driving on another. Analytical and numerical calculations validate these findings. Our study demonstrates the potential of spectroscopy in characterizing systems with four-body interactions, offering insights for realizing quantum annealing with Kerr parametric oscillators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.04981v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuichiro Matsuzaki, Yuichiro Mori, Aiko Yamaguchi, Yohei Kawakami, Tsuyoshi Yamamoto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum-enhanced causal discovery for a small number of samples</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.05007</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.05007v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The discovery of causal relationships from observed data has attracted significant interest from disciplines such as economics, social sciences, epidemiology, and biology. In practical applications, considerable knowledge of the underlying systems is often unavailable, and real data are often associated with nonlinear causal structures, which make the direct use of most conventional causality analysis methods difficult. This study proposes a novel quantum Peter-Clark (qPC) algorithm for causal discovery that does not assume any underlying model structures. Based on the independence conditional tests in a class of reproducing kernel Hilbert spaces characterized by quantum circuits, the proposed qPC algorithm can explore causal relationships from the observed data drawn from arbitrary distributions. We conducted systematic experiments on fundamental graph parts of causal structures, demonstrating that the qPC algorithm exhibits a significantly better performance, particularly with smaller sample sizes compared to its classical counterpart. Furthermore, we proposed a novel optimization approach based on Kernel Target Alignment (KTA) for determining hyperparameters of quantum kernels. This method effectively reduced the risk of false positives in causal discovery, enabling more reliable inference. Our theoretical and experimental results demonstrate that the proposed quantum algorithm can empower classical algorithms for robust and accurate inference in causal discovery, supporting them in regimes where classical algorithms typically fail. Additionally, the effectiveness of this method was validated using the Boston Housing dataset as a real-world application. These findings demonstrate the new potential of quantum circuit-based causal discovery methods in addressing practical challenges, particularly in small-sample scenarios where traditional approaches have shown limitations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.05007v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yota Maeda, Ken Arai, Yu Tanaka, Yu Terada, Hiroshi Ueno, Hiroyuki Tezuka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhanced Min-Sum Decoding of Quantum Codes Using Previous Iteration Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.05021</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.05021v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we propose a novel message-passing decoding approach that leverages the degeneracy of quantum low-density parity-check codes to enhance decoding performance, eliminating the need for serial scheduling or post-processing. Our focus is on two-block Calderbank-Shor-Steane (CSS) codes, which are composed of symmetric stabilizers that hinder the performance of conventional iterative decoders with uniform update rules. Specifically, our analysis shows that, under the isolation assumption, the min-sum decoder fails to converge when constant-weight errors are applied to symmetric stabilizers, as variable-to-check messages oscillate in every iteration. To address this, we introduce a decoding technique that exploits this oscillatory property by applying distinct update rules: variable nodes in one block utilize messages from previous iterations, while those in the other block are updated conventionally. Logical error-rate results demonstrate that the proposed decoder significantly outperforms the normalized min-sum decoder and achieves competitive performance with belief propagation enhanced by order-zero ordered statistics decoding, all while maintaining linear complexity in the code's block length.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.05021v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dimitris Chytas, Nithin Raveendran, Bane Vasic</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Predicting Spin-Dependent Coulomb Interaction Based on the Yang-Mills Equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.05103</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.05103v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The standard Coulomb interaction is one of four fundamental interactions in Nature. It is interesting to know how will the standard Coulomb interaction be modified when it meets spin. Since the standard Coulomb potential is a simple but fundamental solution of Maxwell's equations, hence Maxwell's equations can predict the existence of the standard Coulomb potential. The Yang-Mills equations are the natural generalizations of Maxwell's equations from the Abelian potentials to the non-Abelian ones, thus based on the Yang-Mills equations, one can predict the reasonable form of spin-dependent Coulomb potential, which naturally reduces the standard Coulomb potential if without considering the spin. Our work sheds a new light to how to couple spin with fundamental interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.05103v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiang-Lin Zhou, Choo Hiap Oh, Jing-Ling Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards Optimizing the Expected Performance of Sampling-Based Quantum-Inspired Algorithms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.05184</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.05184v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum-inspired classical algorithms has received much attention due to its exponential speedup compared to existing algorithms, under certain data storage assumptions. The improvements are noticeable in fundamental linear algebra tasks. In this work, we analyze two major subroutines in sampling-based quantum-inspired algorithms, specifically, inner product estimation and sampling from a linear combination of vectors, and discuss their possible improvements by generalizing the data structure. The idea is to consider the average behavior of the subroutines under certain assumptions regarding the data elements. This allows us to determine the optimal data structure, and the high-dimensional nature of data makes our assumptions reasonable. Experimental results from recommendation systems also highlight a consistent preference for our proposed data structure. Motivated by this observation, we tighten the upper bound on the number of required measurements for direct fidelity estimation. We expect our findings to suggest optimal implementations for various quantum and quantum-inspired machine learning algorithms that involve extremely high-dimensional operations, which has potential for many applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.05184v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hyunho Cha, Jungwoo Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Almost Optimal Synthesis of Reversible Function in Qudit Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.05237</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.05237v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum oracles are widely adopted in problems, like query oracle in Grover's algorithm, cipher in quantum cryptanalytic and data encoder in quantum machine learning. Notably, the bit-flip oracle, capable of flipping the state based on a given classical function, emerges as a fundamental component in the design and construction of quantum algorithms. Devising methods to optimally implement the bit-flip oracle essentially translates to the efficient synthesis of reversible functions. Prior research has primarily focused on the qubit model, leaving the higher dimensional systems, i.e. qudit model, largely unexplored. By allowing more than two computational bases, qudit model can fully utilize the multi-level nature of the underlying physical mechanism. We propose a method to synthesize even permutations in $A_{d^{n}}$ using $\Theta(d)$ $(n - 1)$-qudit sub-circuits, which achieve asymptotic optimality in the count of sub-circuits. Moreover, we introduce a technique for synthesizing reversible functions employing $O\left( n d^{n} \right)$ gates and only a single ancilla. This is asymptotically tight in terms of $d$ and asymptotically almost tight in terms of $n$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.05237v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Buji Xu, Junhong Nie, Xiaoming Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Grid Cost Allocation in Peer-to-Peer Electricity Markets: Benchmarking Classical and Quantum Optimization Approaches</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.05253</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.05253v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper presents a novel optimization approach for allocating grid operation costs in Peer-to-Peer (P2P) electricity markets using Quantum Computing (QC). We develop a Quadratic Unconstrained Binary Optimization (QUBO) model that matches logical power flows between producer-consumer pairs with the physical power flow to distribute grid usage costs fairly. The model is evaluated on IEEE test cases with up to 57 nodes, comparing Quantum Annealing (QA), hybrid quantum-classical algorithms, and classical optimization approaches. Our results show that while the model effectively allocates grid operation costs, QA performs poorly in comparison despite extensive hyperparameter optimization. The classical branch-and-cut method outperforms all solvers, including classical heuristics, and shows the most advantageous scaling behavior. The findings may suggest that binary least-squares optimization problems may not be suitable candidates for near-term quantum utility.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.05253v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Bucher, Daniel Porawski, Benedikt Wimmer, Jonas N\"u{\ss}lein, Corey O'Meara, Giorgio Cortiana, Claudia Linnhoff-Popien</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Research on quantum compilation of neutral atom quantum computing platform</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.05266</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.05266v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum compilation is the process of decomposing high-level quantum algorithms or arbitrary unitary operations into quantum circuits composed of a specific set of quantum gates. Neutral atom quantum computing platform is a quantum computing implementation method with high controllability and scalability, but its quantum compilation method is not mature. We systematically review the quantum compilation methods based on matrix decomposition, and propose a compilation algorithm suitable for neutral atom quantum computing, which can effectively decompose any unitary operation into a series of quantum gates suitable for the neutral atom platform, and ensure that the generated quantum circuits can run directly on the platform.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.05266v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chongyuan Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The application of annealing in quantum cooling protocols</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.05268</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.05268v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Inspired by simulated annealing algorithm, we propose a quantum cooling protocol which includes an annealing process. This protocol can be universally and efficiently applied to various quantum simulators, driving the system from an arbitrary initial state to the ground state with high fidelity. We have described the cooling process based on perturbation theory, validated the advantages of bath under time-modulated Zeeman field compared to bath under static one, and provided a justification for the necessity of an annealing process when the system to be cooled is unknown. We applied tensor network methods to numerically simulate our cooling protocol, using the transverse field Ising model (TFIM) as an example to verify the effectiveness of the protocol in cooling one-dimensional systems, two-dimensional systems, and systems with quantum noise. We compared the overall performance of cooling protocols with and without the annealing process on a test set generated with random parameters $g_P$. The results indicate that the cooling protocol with annealing process can achieve both accuracy and efficiency. Our results also show that the cooling protocol's resistance to noise depends on the type of quantum noise.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.05268v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chongyuan Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Molecular Properties from Quantum Krylov Subspace Diagonalization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.05286</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.05286v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum Krylov subspace diagonalization is a prominent candidate for early fault tolerant quantum simulation of many-body and molecular systems, but so far the focus has been mainly on computing ground-state energies. We go beyond this by deriving analytical first-order derivatives for quantum Krylov methods and show how to obtain relaxed one and two particle reduced density matrices of the Krylov eigenstates. The direct approach to measuring these matrices requires a number of distinct measurement that scales quadratically with the Krylov dimension $D$. Here, we show how to reduce this scaling to a constant. This is done by leveraging quantum signal processing to prepare Krylov eigenstates, including exited states, in depth linear in $D$. We also compare several measurement schemes for efficiently obtaining the expectation value of an operator with states prepared using quantum signal processing. We validate our approach by computing the nuclear gradient of a small molecule and estimating its variance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.05286v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oumarou Oumarou, Pauline J. Ollitrault, Cristian L. Cortes, Maximilian Scheurer, Robert M. Parrish, Christian Gogolin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Secure Multi-Party Biometric Verification using QKD assisted Quantum Oblivious Transfer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.05327</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.05327v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a practical implementation of a secure multiparty computation application enabled by quantum oblivious transfer (QOT) on an entanglement-based physical layer. The QOT protocol uses polarization-encoded entangled states to share oblivious keys between two parties with quantum key distribution (QKD) providing authentication. Our system integrates the post-processing for QKD and QOT, both sharing a single physical layer, ensuring efficient key generation and authentication. Authentication involves hashing messages into a crypto-context, verifying tags, and replenishing keys through a parallel QKD pipeline, which handles both key post-processing and authentication. Oblivious keys are generated over 12.9 km with a channel loss of 8.47 dB. In a back-to-back setup, a QOT rate of $9.3\times10^{-3}$ OTs/second is achieved, corresponding to 1 minute and 48 seconds per OT, primarily limited by the entanglement source. Using pre-distributed keys improved the rate to 0.11 OTs/second, or 9.1 seconds per OT. The considered QOT protocol is statistically correct, computationally secure for an honest receiver, and statistically secure for an honest sender, assuming a computationally hiding, statistically binding commitment, and a verifiable error-correcting scheme. A practical use case is demonstrated for privacy-preserving fingerprint matching against no-fly lists from Interpol and the United Nations. The fingerprint is secret-shared across two sites, ensuring security, while the matching is performed using the MASCOT protocol, supported by QOT. The application required 128 OTs, with the highest security achieved in 20 minutes and 39 seconds. This work demonstrates the feasibility of QOT in secure quantum communication applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.05327v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mariana F. Ramos, Michael Hentschel, Federico Valbusa, Costin Luchian, Martin Achleitner, Alessandro Trenti, Marie-Christine Slater, Mariano Lemus, Thomas Lor\"unser, Hannes H\"ubel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Approaching the Quantum Speed Limit in Quantum Gates with Geometric Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.05330</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.05330v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a geometric optimization method for implementing quantum gates by optimally controlling the Hamiltonian parameters, aiming to approach the Mandelstam-Tamm Quantum Speed Limit (MT-QSL). Achieving this bound requires satisfying precise geometric conditions governing the evolution of quantum states. We extend this geometric framework to quantum unitary operators in arbitrary dimensions and analyze the conditions necessary for saturation of the bound. Additionally, we demonstrate that the quantum brachistochrone, when generalized to operators, does not generally reach the MT-QSL bound. Finally, we propose a systematic optimal control strategy based on geometric principles to approach the quantum speed limit for unitary driving.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.05330v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>F. Impens, D. Gu\'ery-Odelin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A learning agent-based approach to the characterization of open quantum systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.05350</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.05350v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Characterizing quantum processes is crucial for the execution of quantum algorithms on available quantum devices. A powerful framework for this purpose is the Quantum Model Learning Agent (QMLA) which characterizes a given system by learning its Hamiltonian via adaptive generations of informative experiments and their validation against simulated models. Identifying the incoherent noise of a quantum device in addition to its coherent interactions is, however, as essential. Precise knowledge of such imperfections of a quantum device allows to devise strategies to mitigate detrimental effects, for example via quantum error correction. We introduce the open Quantum Model Learning Agent (oQMLA) framework to account for Markovian noise through the Liouvillian formalism. By simultaneously learning the Hamiltonian and jump operators, oQMLA independently captures both the coherent and incoherent dynamics of a system. The added complexity of open systems necessitates advanced algorithmic strategies. Among these, we implement regularization to steer the algorithm towards plausible models and an unbiased metric to evaluate the quality of the results. We validate our implementation in simulated scenarios of increasing complexity, demonstrating its robustness to hardware-induced measurement errors and its ability to characterize systems using only local operations. Additionally, we develop a scheme to interface oQMLA with a publicly available superconducting quantum computer, showcasing its practical utility. These advancements represent a significant step toward improving the performance of quantum hardware and contribute to the broader goal of advancing quantum technologies and their applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.05350v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lorenzo Fioroni, Ivan Rojkov, Florentin Reiter</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Blind calibration of a quantum computer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.05355</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.05355v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum system calibration is limited by the ability to characterize a quantum state under unknown device errors. We develop an accurate calibration protocol that is blind to the precise preparation of a specific quantum state. It extracts device errors from simple tomographic data only, and does not require bespoke experiments for a priori specified error mechanisms. Using a trapped-ion quantum computer, we experimentally demonstrate the accuracy of the method by recovering intentional miscalibrations. We then use blind calibration to estimate the native calibration parameters of the experimental system. The recovered calibrations are close to directly measured values and perform similarly in predicting state properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.05355v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Liam M. Jeanette, Jadwiga Wilkens, Ingo Roth, Anton Than, Alaina M. Green, Dominik Hangleiter, Norbert M. Linke</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Equilibrium and nonequilibrium steady states with the repeated interaction protocol: Relaxation dynamics and energetic cost</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.05392</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.05392v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the dynamics of a qubit system interacting with thermalized bath-ancilla spins via a repeated interaction scheme. Considering generic initial conditions for the system and employing a Heisenberg-type interaction between the system and the ancillas, we analytically prove the following: (i) The population and coherences of the system qubit evolve independently toward a nonequilibrium steady-state solution, which is diagonal in the qubit's energy eigenbasis. The population relaxes to this state geometrically, whereas the coherences decay through a more compound behavior. (ii) In the long time limit, the system approaches a steady state that generally differs from the thermal state of the ancilla. We derive this steady-state solution and show its dependence on the interaction parameters and collision frequency. (iii) We bound the number of interaction steps required to achieve the steady state within a specified error tolerance, and we evaluate the energetic cost associated with the process. Our key finding is that deterministic system-ancilla interactions do not typically result in the system thermalizing to the thermal state of the ancilla. Instead, they generate a distinct nonequilibrium steady state, which we explicitly derive. However, we also identify an operational regime that leads to thermalization with a few long and possibly randomized collisions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.05392v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alessandro Prositto, Madeline Forbes, Dvira Segal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Innovative Designs and Insights into Quantum Thermal Machines</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.05406</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.05406v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a comprehensive theoretical investigation about the operational regions of quantum systems, specifically examining their roles as working media functioning between two thermal reservoirs in Quantum Thermal Machines (QTMs). This study provides relevant and novel insights, including a complete spectrum of QTMs within the operational region of these quantum systems, and introduces new QTM designs never before described in the literature. Additionally, this work introduces a standardized and cohesive classification scheme for QTMs, ensuring robustness in nomenclature and operational distinctions, which enhances both theoretical understanding and practical application. Notably, one of these designs directly addresses the need for a more appropriate explanation of the operation of a laser (or maser) as a QTM. Initial calculations were performed to achieve results applicable to any quantum system subjected to rules analogous to those used in classical thermal machine studies. These results were then used to analyze two-level quantum systems as the working medium of QTMs in the Otton cycle. In particular, we analyzed two specific quantum systems: the laser and a spinless electron in a one-dimensional quantum ring, yielding consistent and innovative results. Overall, this study offers valuable insights into the operation and classification of QTMs, establishing a clear and unified framework for their nomenclature while opening new avenues for the design and enhancement of these devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.05406v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aline D. Lucio, Cleverson Filgueiras, Moises Rojas</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
