<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>quant-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/quant-ph</link>
    <description>quant-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/quant-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 05:00:06 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Comment on "The unphysicality of Hilbert spaces" (arXiv:2308.06669v3)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03294</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03294v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A pivotal claim in "The unphysicality of Hilbert spaces" by Carcassi, Calder\'on and Aidala (arXiv:2308.06669v3) is that "unitary transformations in a Hilbert space can map states with finite expectation values to those with infinite ones". In the present comment it is shown that this statement is incorrect and the source of the mistake is pointed out. In consequence, the purported example of a time evolution that makes "the expectation value oscillate from finite to infinite in finite time" is also faulty, and the assertion that Hilbert spaces "turn a potential infinity into an actual infinity" is unsubstantiated.
  These errors weaken dramatically, if not invalidate, the authors' contention that Hilbert spaces are unphysical.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03294v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nivaldo A. Lemos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>W-class states-identification and quantification of Bell-CHSH inequalities' violation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03373</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03373v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We discuss a family of W-class states describing three-qubit systems. For such systems, we analyze the relations between the entanglement measures and the nonlocality parameter for a two-mode mixed state related to the two-qubit subsystem. We find the conditions determining the boundary values of the negativity, parameterized by concurrence, for violating the Bell-CHSH inequality. Additionally, we derive the value ranges of the mixedness measure, parameterized by concurrence and negativity for the qubit--qubit mixed state, guaranteeing the violation and non-violation of the Bell-CHSH inequality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03373v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3390/e26121107</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Entropy 26, 1107 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Joanna K. Kalaga, Wies{\l}aw Leo\'nski, Jan Pe\v{r}ina Jr</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Transfer Learning for Deep-Unfolded Combinatorial Optimization Solver with Quantum Annealer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03518</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03518v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum annealing (QA) has attracted research interest as a sampler and combinatorial optimization problem (COP) solver. A recently proposed sampling-based solver for QA significantly reduces the required number of qubits, being capable of large COPs. In relation to this, a trainable sampling-based COP solver has been proposed that optimizes its internal parameters from a dataset by using a deep learning technique called deep unfolding. Although learning the internal parameters accelerates the convergence speed, the sampler in the trainable solver is restricted to using a classical sampler owing to the training cost. In this study, to utilize QA in the trainable solver, we propose classical-quantum transfer learning, where parameters are trained classically, and the trained parameters are used in the solver with QA. The results of numerical experiments demonstrate that the trainable quantum COP solver using classical-quantum transfer learning improves convergence speed and execution time over the original solver.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03518v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ryo Hagiwara, Shunta Arai, Satoshi Takabe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inductive Construction of Variational Quantum Circuit for Constrained Combinatorial Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03521</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03521v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this study, we propose a new method for constrained combinatorial optimization using variational quantum circuits. Quantum computers are considered to have the potential to solve large combinatorial optimization problems faster than classical computers. Variational quantum algorithms, such as Variational Quantum Eigensolver (VQE), have been studied extensively because they are expected to work on noisy intermediate scale devices. Unfortunately, many optimization problems have constraints, which induces infeasible solutions during VQE process. Recently, several methods for efficiently solving constrained combinatorial optimization problems have been proposed by designing a quantum circuit so as to output only the states that satisfy the constraints. However, the types of available constraints are still limited. Therefore, we have started to develop variational quantum circuits that can handle a wider range of constraints. The proposed method utilizes a forwarding operation that maps from feasible states for subproblems to those for larger subproblems. As long as appropriate forwarding operations can be defined, iteration of this process can inductively construct variational circuits outputting feasible states even in the case of multiple and complex constraints. In this paper, the proposed method was applied to facility location problem and was found to increase the probability for measuring feasible solutions or optimal solutions. In addition, the cost of the obtained circuit was comparable to that of conventional variational circuits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03521v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hyakka Nakada, Kotaro Tanahashi, Shu Tanaka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Four-body coupler for superconducting qubits based on Josephson parametric oscillators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03578</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03578v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We theoretically propose a circuit of the four-body coupler for superconducting qubits based on Josephson parametric oscillators (JPOs). Our coupler for the four-body interaction has a superconducting loop, similar to a capacitively shunted flux qubit, where an external magnetic flux set to half a flux quantum is threaded. This coupler circuit is a specific setup of the circuit called superconducting nonlinear asymmetric inductive elements (SNAIL) and also is a generalization of the previously proposed one for the four-body interaction of JPOs. We clarify roles of circuit parameters in the four-body interaction and, in particular, show that the four-body coupling constant in our circuit can be significantly increased by tuning capacitance of the coupler or the area ratio of the Josephson junctions of the coupler.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03578v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ryoji Miyazaki, Tsuyoshi Yamamoto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Supercorrelated decay in a quasiperiodic nonlinear waveguide: From Markovian to non-Markovian transitions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03607</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03607v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Mobility edges (MEs) are critical boundaries in disordered quantum systems that separate localized from extended states, significantly affecting transport properties and phase transitions. Although MEs are well-understood in single-photon systems, their manifestation in many-body contexts remains an active area of research. In this work, we investigate a one-dimensional Bose-Hubbard chain with a quasiperiodic potential modulating photon-photon interactions, effectively creating a mosaic lattice. We identify MEs for doublon states (i.e, bound photon pairs resulting from strong interactions) within the two-photon subspace. Our analytical solutions and numerical simulations confirm the existence of these MEs, extending single-photon MEs theories to the two-photon regime. Additionally, we analyze the dynamics of two emitters coupled to the waveguide, enabling the emission of supercorrelated photon pairs into the waveguide. Our findings reveal that coupling to extended states results in Markovian dynamics, characterized by exponentially supercorrelated decay, while coupling to localized states gives rise to non-Markovian dynamics, marked by suppressed decay and persistent oscillations. Here, a transition from Markovian to non-Markovian behavior occurs around the MEs of the doublons. Finally, we propose a feasible experimental implementation using superconducting circuits, providing a platform to observe the interplay between interactions and disorder in quantum systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03607v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jia-Qi Li, Tian-Yu Zhou, Xin Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiparticle quantum walks for distinguishing hard graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03683</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03683v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum random walks have been shown to be powerful quantum algorithms for certain tasks on graphs like database searching, quantum simulations etc. In this work we focus on its applications for the graph isomorphism problem. In particular we look at how we can compare multi-particle quantum walks and well known classical WL tests and how quantum walks can be used to distinguish hard graphs like CFI graphs which k-WL tests cannot distinguish. We provide theoretical proofs and empirical results to show that a k-QW with input superposition states distinguishes k-CFI graphs. In addition we also prove that a k-1 QW with localized input states distinguishes k-CFI graphs. We also prove some additional results about strongly regular graphs (SRGs).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03683v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sachin Kasture, Shaheen Acheche, Loic Henriet, Louis-Paul Henry</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dissipative evolution of a two-level system through a geometry-based classical mapping</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03760</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03760v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this manuscript, we introduce a geometry-based formalism to obtain a Meyer-Miller-Stock-Thoss mapping in order to study the dynamics of both isolated and interacting two-level systems. After showing the description of the isolated case using canonically conjugate variables, we implement an interaction model by bilinearly coupling the corresponding population differences {\it \`a la} Caldeira-Leggett, showing that the dynamics behave as a Gross-Pitaevskii-like one. We also find a transition between oscillatory and tunneling-suppressed dynamics that can be observed by varying the coupling constant. After extending our model to the {\it system plus environment} case, where the environment is considered as a collection of two-level systems, we show tunneling-suppressed dynamics in the strong coupling limit and the usual damping effect similar to that of a harmonic oscillator bath in the weak coupling one. Finally, we observe that our interacting model turns an isolated symmetric two-level system into an environment-assisted asymmetric one.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03760v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Mart\'inez Gil, Pedro Bargue\~no, Salvador Miret-Art\'es</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient Protein Ground State Energy Computation via Fragmentation and Reassembly</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03766</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03766v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Protein characterization is one of the key components for understanding the human body and advancing drug discovery processes. While the future of quantum hardware holds the potential to accurately characterize these molecules, current efforts focus on developing strategies to fragment large molecules into computationally manageable subsystems. In this work, we propose a novel strategy to enable quantum simulation using existing quantum algorithms. Our approach involves fragmenting proteins into their corresponding amino acids, simulating them independently, and then reassembling them post-simulation while applying chemical corrections. This methodology demonstrates its accuracy by calculating the ground state of relatively small peptides through reassembling, achieving a mean relative error of only $0.00263 \pm 0.01724\% $. Future directions include investigating, with larger quantum computers, whether this approach remains valid for larger proteins.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03766v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Laia Coronas Sala (Lighthouse Disruptive Innovation Group S.L), Parfait Atchade-Adelemou (Lighthouse Disruptive Innovation Group S.L, MIT Media Lab)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Linear Multistep Method for Using a Quantum Oracle with Differential Equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03781</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03781v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Differential equations are a crucial mathematical tool used in a wide range of applications. If the solution to an initial value problem (IVP) can be transformed into an oracle, it can be utilized in various fields such as search and optimization, achieving quadratic speedup with respect to the number of candidates compared to its classical counterpart. In the past, attempts have been made to implement such an oracle using the Euler method. In this study, we propose a quantum linear multistep method (QLMM) that applies the linear multistep method, commonly used to numerically solve IVPs on classical computers, to generate a numerical solution of the IVP for use in a quantum oracle. We also propose a method to find the optimal form of QLMM for a given IVP. Finally, through computer simulations, we derive the QLMM formulation for an example IVP and show that the solution from the optimized QLMM can be used in an optimization problem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03781v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kyoung Keun Park, Kwangyeul Choi, Minwoo Kim, Giwon Song, Taehyun Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Some properties and applications of the new quantum $f$-divergences</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03799</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03799v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recently, a new definition for quantum $f$-divergences was introduced based on an integral representation. These divergences have shown remarkable properties, for example when investigating contraction coefficients under noisy channels. At the same time, many properties well known for other definitions have remained elusive for the new quantum $f$-divergence because of its unusual representation. In this work, we investigate alternative ways of expressing these quantum $f$-divergences. We leverage these expressions to prove new properties of these $f$-divergences and demonstrate some applications. In particular, we give a new proof of the achievability of the quantum Chernoff bound by establishing a strengthening of an inequality by Audenaert et al. We also establish inequalities between some previously known Renyi divergences and the new Renyi divergence. We further investigate some monotonicity and convexity properties of the new $f$-divergences, and prove inequalities between these divergences for various functions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03799v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Salman Beigi, Christoph Hirche, Marco Tomamichel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wigner Function of Observed Quantum Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03885</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03885v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Wigner function was introduced as an attempt to describe quantum mechanical fields with the tools inherited from classical statistical mechanics. In particular, it is widely used to describe properties of radiation fields. In fact, a useful way to distinguish between classical and nonclassical states of light is to ask whether their Wigner function has a Gaussian profile or not, respectively. In this manuscript, I use the basis of Fock states to provide the closed-form expression for the Wigner function of an arbitrary quantum state. Further, to illustrate the power of my expression, I provide the Wigner function of the most fundamental quantum system: Resonance Fluorescence. Thus, I discuss the conditions to obtain negative-valued Wigner function and the relation that they have with population inversion. Finally, I tackle the problem of the observation of the radiation field, introducing physical detectors into the description of the emission. Notably, I show that the Wigner function can still expose the quantumness of the radiation field, even if the detection has finite spectral resolution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03885v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Juan Camilo L\'opez Carre\~no</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modes, states and superselection rules in quantum optics and quantum information</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03943</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03943v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A convenient way to represent quantum optical states is through the quadrature basis of single-modes of the field. This framework provides intuitive definitions for quasi-classical states, their phase-space representations, and a robust toolbox for quantum state manipulation using universal gates. In this widely adopted representation of quantum optics, most pure states consist of coherent superpositions of photon-number states. However, this approach neglects the particle-number superselection rule - which prohibits coherence between states of differing photon numbers - and implicitly assumes a common phase reference - even though global phases are unmeasurable in quantum optics. We adopt a representation of quantum optical states that respects the superselection rule and revisit key tools and results in quantum optics and information encoding within quantum optics. In the introduced framework, general pure states are described using two orthogonal modes in the Fock basis. We show that this approach preserves the intuitive aspects of the traditional quadrature representation while unifying insights from quantum optics with those from symmetric spin-like and angular momentum systems. Moreover, the superselection rule-compliant representation provides a consistent definition of non-purity and coherence for optical modes and states. It offers a clearer and general perspective on quantum universality, non-classicality, and the (im)possibility of efficient classical simulation across various quantum information encoding schemes involving quantum optical modes and states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03943v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eloi Descamps, Astghik Saharyan, Adrien Chivet, Arne Keller, P\'erola Milman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cartan-covariant Quantum Channels and the PPT$^{2}$ conjecture</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03959</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03959v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Two-parameter generalizations of depolarizing channels are introduced and studied. These so-called Cartan-covariant channels have a covariance Lie group that forms a Cartan decomposition of SU$(D)$. The regions of completely positive and completely co-positive Cartan-covariant trace-preserving maps are found through a spectral analysis of the Choi state. Furthermore, we prove that the PPT$^{2}$ conjecture holds for these channels in any dimension.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03959v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sean Prudhoe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entangled Schr\"odinger cat states, vacuum projector and Bell-CHSH inequality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03960</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03960v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Use of the vacuum projector and of the unitary displacement operators enables us to construct Hermitian dichotomic operators. These operators are employed to scrutinize the violation of the Bell-CHSH inequality for entangled coherent Entangled Schr\"odinger cat states, vacuum projector and Bell-CHSH inequality cat states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03960v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. P. Sorella</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Performance of Practical Quantum Oblivious Key Distribution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03973</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03973v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Motivated by the applications of secure multiparty computation as a privacy-protecting data analysis tool, and identifying oblivious transfer as one of its main practical enablers, we propose a practical realization of randomized quantum oblivious transfer. By using only symmetric cryptography primitives to implement commitments, we construct computationally-secure randomized oblivious transfer without the need for public-key cryptography or assumptions imposing limitations on the adversarial devices. We show that the protocol is secure under an indistinguishability-based notion of security and demonstrate an experimental implementation to test its real-world performance. Its security and performance are then compared to both quantum and classical alternatives, showing potential advantages over existing solutions based on the noisy storage model and public-key cryptography.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03973v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mariano Lemus, Peter Schiansky, Manuel Goul\~ao, Mathieu Bozzio, David Elkouss, Nikola Paunkovi\'c, Paulo Mateus, Philip Walther</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
