<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>quant-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/quant-ph</link>
    <description>quant-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/quant-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 05:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>A Faster Quantum Fourier Transform</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12414</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12414v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present an asymptotically improved algorithm for implementing the Quantum Fourier Transform (QFT) in both the exact and approximate settings. Historically, the approximate QFT has been implemented in $\Theta(n \log n)$ gates, and the exact in $\Theta(n^2)$ gates. In this work, we show that these costs can be reduced by leveraging a novel formulation of the QFT that recurses on two partitions of the qubits. Specifically, our approach yields an $\Theta(n(\log \log n)^2)$ algorithm for the approximate QFT using $\Theta(\log n)$ ancillas, and an $\Theta(n(\log n)^2)$ algorithm for the exact QFT requiring $\Theta(n)$ ancillas.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12414v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ronit Shah</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tight relations and equivalences between smooth relative entropies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12447</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12447v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The precise one-shot characterisation of operational tasks in classical and quantum information theory relies on different forms of smooth entropic quantities. A particularly important connection is between the hypothesis testing relative entropy and the smoothed max-relative entropy, which together govern many operational settings. We first strengthen this connection into a type of equivalence: we show that the hypothesis testing relative entropy is equivalent to a variant of the smooth max-relative entropy based on the information spectrum divergence, which can be alternatively understood as a measured smooth max-relative entropy. Furthermore, we improve a fundamental lemma due to Datta and Renner that connects the different variants of the smoothed max-relative entropy, introducing a modified proof technique based on matrix geometric means and a tightened gentle measurement lemma. We use the unveiled connections and tools to strictly improve on previously known one-shot bounds and duality relations between the smooth max-relative entropy and the hypothesis testing relative entropy, sharpening also bounds that connect the max-relative entropy with R\'enyi divergences.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12447v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bartosz Regula, Ludovico Lami, Nilanjana Datta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Waveguide arrays interaction to second neighbors: Exact solution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12550</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12550v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We provide an analytical framework for describing the propagation of light in waveguide arrays, considering both infinite and semi-infinite cases. The interaction up to second neighbors is taken into account, which makes for a more realistic setup. We show that these solutions follow a distinctive structural pattern. This pattern reflects a transition from conventional Bessel functions to the lesser-known one-parameter generalized Bessel functions, offering new insights into the propagation dynamics in these systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12550v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. A. Tapia-Valerdi, I. Ramos-Prieto, F. Soto-Eguibar, H. M. Moya-Cessa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Classical and quantum algorithms for characters of the symmetric group</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12579</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12579v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Characters of irreducible representations are ubiquitous in group theory. However, computing characters of some groups such as the symmetric group $S_n$ is a challenging problem known to be $\#P$-hard in the worst case. Here we describe a Matrix Product State (MPS) algorithm for characters of $S_n$. The algorithm computes an MPS encoding all irreducible characters of a given permutation. It relies on a mapping from characters of $S_n$ to quantum spin chains proposed by Crichigno and Prakash. We also provide a simpler derivation of this mapping. We complement this result by presenting a $poly(n)$ size quantum circuit that prepares the corresponding MPS, obtaining an efficient quantum algorithm for certain sampling problems based on characters of $S_n$. To assess classical hardness of these problems we present a general reduction from strong simulation (computing a given probability) to weak simulation (sampling with a small error). This reduction applies to any sampling problem with a certain granularity structure and may be of independent interest.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12579v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sergey Bravyi, David Gosset, Vojtech Havlicek, Louis Schatzki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entanglement dynamics in collision models and entanglement quilts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12629</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12629v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the entanglement dynamics of a family of quantum collision models by analytically solving the pairwise concurrence for all qubit pairs. We introduce a diagrammatic method that offers an intuitive, frame-by-frame understanding of these dynamics. This allows us to monitor how a single collision affects the entanglement of the whole many-body system in some special cases. We focus on a class of models where the square of concurrence is a conserved quantity in the qubit collisions, aiding us to formulate general rules of entanglement propagation. In particular, among the multiple examples we will be showing, we identify a type of genuine multipartite entanglement, which we refer to as \textit{entanglement quilt}, where every qubit is entangled with every other qubit. We find that in some models, an entanglement quilt is hypersensitive to local excitation fluctuations: The presence of even a single excited qubit can destroy the entanglement quilts. We offer a detailed mathematical treatment on the phenomena, which can help us understand the disappearance of long-range entanglement in condensed matter systems above zero temperature. We also speculate about a possible property of the entanglement quilt: Every subsystem of it is entangled with every other subsystem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12629v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Le Hu, Andrew N. Jordan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Linear-optical four-dimensional Bell state measurement with two-photon interference</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12655</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12655v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We theoretically investigate the distinguishability of a set of mutually orthogonal four-dimensional Bell states of photon system in path degree of freedom using only linear optics, resorting to the two-photon interference. With quantum interference effect, we find that the 16 four-dimensional Bell states can be classified into 7 groups, which can support the transmission of $log_2 7 = 2.81$ bits classical information with just sending one photon in the quantum superdense coding protocol. When an auxiliary two-dimensional polarization entanglement is introduced, the 16 four-dimensional Bell states then can be classified into 12 groups, which can promote the channel capacity to $log_2 12 = 3.58$ bits with encoding one photon. Our results are significant for photonic superdense coding, and can be useful for other quantum information technologies involved linear-optical high-dimensional Bell state measurement.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12655v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhi Zeng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Practical quantum federated learning and its experimental demonstration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12709</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12709v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Federated learning is essential for decentralized, privacy-preserving model training in the data-driven era. Quantum-enhanced federated learning leverages quantum resources to address privacy and scalability challenges, offering security and efficiency advantages beyond classical methods. However, practical and scalable frameworks addressing privacy concerns in the quantum computing era remain undeveloped. Here, we propose a practical quantum federated learning framework on quantum networks, utilizing distributed quantum secret keys to protect local model updates and enable secure aggregation with information-theoretic security. We experimentally validate our framework on a 4-client quantum network with a scalable structure. Extensive numerical experiments on both quantum and classical datasets show that adding a quantum client significantly enhances the trained global model's ability to classify multipartite entangled and non-stabilizer quantum datasets. Simulations further demonstrate scalability to 200 clients with classical models trained on the MNIST dataset, reducing communication costs by $75\%$ through advanced model compression techniques and achieving rapid training convergence. Our work provides critical insights for building scalable, efficient, and quantum-secure machine learning systems for the coming quantum internet era.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12709v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhi-Ping Liu, Xiao-Yu Cao, Hao-Wen Liu, Xiao-Ran Sun, Yu Bao, Yu-Shuo Lu, Hua-Lei Yin, Zeng-Bing Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cavity Mode Initialization via a Rabi Driven Qubit</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12710</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12710v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Microwave cavity modes with long coherence times are used in many different quantum computing systems. During normal operation of such systems, these modes, called memory modes, often need to be set to different coherent photonic occupations. In this work we present a novel technique we call Rabi Driven Reset in which the state of a memory mode is transferred into a decaying mode. This is done through a Rabi driven qubit which is coupled to both modes via sideband driving tones. The outcome of the method is the initialization of the memory mode at any required coherent state. Simulations are presented to demonstrate the effectiveness of this technique, along with a comparison to an existing coupling method. Our simulations predict an improvement of an order of magnitude in initialization times compared to existing methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12710v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevApplied.23.014043</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Applied 23, 014043 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>N. Karaev, E. Blumenthal, G. Moshel, A. A. Diringer, S. Hacohen-Gourgy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Data re-uploading in Quantum Machine Learning for time series: application to traffic forecasting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12776</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12776v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Accurate traffic forecasting plays a crucial role in modern Intelligent Transportation Systems (ITS), as it enables real-time traffic flow management, reduces congestion, and improves the overall efficiency of urban transportation networks. With the rise of Quantum Machine Learning (QML), it has emerged a new paradigm possessing the potential to enhance predictive capabilities beyond what classical machine learning models can achieve. In the present work we pursue a heuristic approach to explore the potential of QML, and focus on a specific transport issue. In particular, as a case study we investigate a traffic forecast task for a major urban area in Athens (Greece), for which we possess high-resolution data. In this endeavor we explore the application of Quantum Neural Networks (QNN), and, notably, we present the first application of quantum data re-uploading in the context of transport forecasting. This technique allows quantum models to better capture complex patterns, such as traffic dynamics, by repeatedly encoding classical data into a quantum state. Aside from providing a prediction model, we spend considerable effort in comparing the performance of our hybrid quantum-classical neural networks with classical deep learning approaches. Our results show that hybrid models achieve competitive accuracy with state-of-the-art classical methods, especially when the number of qubits and re-uploading blocks is increased. While the classical models demonstrate lower computational demands, we provide evidence that increasing the complexity of the quantum model improves predictive accuracy. These findings indicate that QML techniques, and specifically the data re-uploading approach, hold promise for advancing traffic forecasting models and could be instrumental in addressing challenges inherent in ITS environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12776v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nikolaos Schetakis, Paolo Bonfini, Negin Alisoltani, Konstantinos Blazakis, Symeon I. Tsintzos, Alexis Askitopoulos, Davit Aghamalyan, Panagiotis Fafoutellis, Eleni I. Vlahogianni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Continuous-variable quantum communication</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12801</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12801v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Tremendous progress in experimental quantum optics during the past decades enabled the advent of quantum technologies, one of which is quantum communication. Aimed at novel methods for more secure or efficient information transfer, quantum communication has developed into an active field of research and proceeds toward full-scale implementations and industrialization. Continuous-variable methods of multi-photon quantum state preparation, manipulation, and coherent detection, as well as the respective theoretical tools of phase-space quantum optics, offer the possibility to make quantum communication efficient, applicable and accessible, thus boosting the development of the field. We review the methodology, techniques and protocols of continuous-variable quantum communication, from the first theoretical ideas, through milestone implementations, to the recent developments, covering quantum key distribution as well as other quantum communication schemes, suggested on the basis of continuous-variable states and measurements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12801v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vladyslav C. Usenko, Antonio Ac\'in, Romain All\'eaume, Ulrik L. Andersen, Eleni Diamanti, Tobias Gehring, Adnan A. E. Hajomer, Florian Kanitschar, Christoph Pacher, Stefano Pirandola, Valerio Pruneri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonreciprocal and nonconservative forces on binary systems of identical atoms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12813</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12813v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The dynamical and radiative features of an excited system of two identical atoms are analysed. The metastability of the system, the directionality of its emission and its internal forces are studied. Closed-form expressions are derived for the time-evolution of the system, for the angular distribution of its spontaneous emission, and for its internal dipole forces, both conservative and nonconservative. The latter reveals the presence of nonreciprocal forces, which leads to a net oscillatory force upon the system. We estimate that, for a free binary system of Li Rydberg atoms, the net internal force may cause a displacement of its center of mass as large as $120 nm$ over a lifetime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12813v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Julio S\'anchez-C\'anovas, Manuel Donaire</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Deimginarity Cost of Quantum States</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12891</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12891v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Here we address a task denoted as deimaginarity, which is to transform a state into a real state with the aid of random covariant-free unitary operations. We consider the minimum cost of randomness required for deimaginarity in the scenario of infinite copies and suiciently small error, and we prove that the deimaginarity cost of a state $\rho$ is equal to its regularized relative entropy of imaginarity, which can be seen as an operational interpretation of the relative entropy of imaginarity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12891v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xian Shi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unraveling quantum phase estimation: exploring the impact of multi-photon interference on the quantum Fisher information</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12945</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12945v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum interference is known to become extinct with distinguishing information, as illustrated by the ubiquitous double-slit experiment or the two-photon HOM effect. In the former case single particle interference is destroyed with which-path information while in the latter bunching interference tails-off as photons become distinguishable. It has been observed that when more than two particles are involved, these interference patterns are in general a non monotonic function of the distinguishability. Here we perform a comprehensive characterization, both theoretically and experimentally, of four-photon interference by analyzing the corresponding correlation functions, contemplating several degrees of distinguishability across different parameters. This study provides all the necessary tools to quantify the impact of multi-photon interference on precision measurements of parameters such as phase, frequency, and time difference. We apply these insights to quantify the precision in the estimation of an interferometric phase in a two-port interferometer using a four-photon state. Our results reveal that, for certain phase values, partially distinguishable multi-photon states can achieve higher Fisher information values compared to the two-photon experiment. These findings highlight the potential of distinguishable multi-photon states for enhanced precision in quantum metrology and related applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12945v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Annameng Ma, Agustina G. Magnoni, Miguel A. Larotonda, Laura T. Knoll</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient simulation of parametrized quantum circuits under non-unital noise through Pauli backpropagation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.13050</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.13050v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: As quantum devices continue to grow in size but remain affected by noise, it is crucial to determine when and how they can outperform classical computers on practical tasks. A central piece in this effort is to develop the most efficient classical simulation algorithms possible. Among the most promising approaches are Pauli backpropagation algorithms, which have already demonstrated their ability to efficiently simulate certain classes of parameterized quantum circuits-a leading contender for near-term quantum advantage-under random circuit assumptions and depolarizing noise. However, their efficiency was not previously established for more realistic non-unital noise models, such as amplitude damping, that better capture noise on existing hardware. Here, we close this gap by adapting Pauli backpropagation to non-unital noise, proving that it remains efficient even under these more challenging conditions. Our proof leverages a refined combinatorial analysis to handle the complexities introduced by non-unital channels, thus strengthening Pauli backpropagation as a powerful tool for simulating near-term quantum devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.13050v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Victor Martinez, Armando Angrisani, Ekaterina Pankovets, Omar Fawzi, Daniel Stilck Fran\c{c}a</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Preparing low-variance states using a distributed quantum algorithm</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.13097</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.13097v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum computers are a highly promising tool for efficiently simulating quantum many-body systems. The preparation of their eigenstates is of particular interest and can be addressed, e.g., by quantum phase estimation algorithms. The routine then acts as an effective filtering operation, reducing the energy variance of the initial state. In this work, we present a distributed quantum algorithm inspired by iterative phase estimation to prepare low-variance states. Our method uses a single auxiliary qubit per quantum device, which controls its dynamics, and a postselection strategy for a joint quantum measurement on such auxiliary qubits. In the multi-device case, the result of this measurement heralds the successful runs of the protocol. This allows us to demonstrate that our distributed algorithm reduces the energy variance significantly faster compared to single-device implementations, thereby highlighting the potential of distributed algorithms for near-term and early fault-tolerant devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.13097v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaoyu Liu, Benjamin F. Schiffer, Jordi Tura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simulating quantum circuits with arbitrary local noise using Pauli Propagation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.13101</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.13101v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a polynomial-time classical algorithm for estimating expectation values of arbitrary observables on typical quantum circuits under any incoherent local noise, including non-unital or dephasing. Although previous research demonstrated that some carefully designed quantum circuits affected by non-unital noise cannot be efficiently simulated, we show that this does not apply to average-case circuits, as these can be efficiently simulated using Pauli-path methods. Specifically, we prove that, with high probability over the circuit gates choice, Pauli propagation algorithms with tailored truncation strategies achieve an inversely polynomially small simulation error. This result holds for arbitrary circuit topologies and for any local noise, under the assumption that the distribution of each circuit layer is invariant under single-qubit random gates. Under the same minimal assumptions, we also prove that most noisy circuits can be truncated to an effective logarithmic depth for the task of {estimating} expectation values of observables, thus generalizing prior results to a significantly broader class of circuit ensembles. We further numerically validate our algorithm with simulations on a $6\times6$ lattice of qubits under the effects of amplitude damping and dephasing noise, as well as real-time dynamics on an $11\times11$ lattice of qubits affected by amplitude damping.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.13101v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Armando Angrisani, Antonio A. Mele, Manuel S. Rudolph, M. Cerezo, Zoe Holmes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Achievability of Covert Quantum Communication</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.13103</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.13103v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We explore covert communication of qubits over the general quantum channel. Covert communication conceals the transmissions in the channel noise, ensuring that an adversary is unable to detect their presence. We show achievability of a \emph{square root law} (SRL) for quantum covert communication similar to that for classical: $M(n)\propto\sqrt{n}$ qubits can be transmitted covertly and reliably over $n$ uses of a general quantum channel. We lower bound $M(n)$ with and without the assistance from a full-duplex covert classical channel. In the former case, we quantify the number of classical covert bits sufficient for our protocol.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.13103v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Evan J. D. Anderson, Michael S. Bullock, Filip Rozp\k{e}dek, Boulat A. Bash</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
