<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>quant-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/quant-ph</link>
    <description>quant-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/quant-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 05:00:02 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Large-Range Tuning and Stabilization of the Optical Transition of Diamond Tin-Vacancy Centers by In-Situ Strain Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09788</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09788v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The negatively charged tin-vacancy (SnV-) center in diamond has emerged as a promising platform for quantum computing and quantum networks. To connect SnV- qubits in large networks, in-situ tuning and stabilization of their optical transitions are essential to overcome static and dynamic frequency offsets induced by the local environment. Here we report on the large-range optical frequency tuning of diamond SnV- centers using micro-electro-mechanically mediated strain control in photonic integrated waveguide devices. We realize a tuning range of &gt;40 GHz, covering a major part of the inhomogeneous distribution. In addition, we employ real-time feedback on the strain environment to stabilize the resonant frequency and mitigate spectral wandering. These results provide a path for on-chip scaling of diamond SnV-based quantum networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09788v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Julia M. Brevoord, Leonardo G. C. Wienhoven, Nina Codreanu, Tetsuro Ishiguro, Elvis van Leeuwen, Mariagrazia Iuliano, Lorenzo De Santis, Christopher Waas, Hans K. C. Beukers, Tim Turan, Carlos Errando-Herranz, Kenichi Kawaguchi, Ronald Hanson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase-Shifted Bell States</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09874</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09874v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Inspired by previous studies and pioneers of the field, we present new results on an extensive EPR-Bell experiment using photons generated by parametric down conversion, where one of the photons is deliberately phase-shifted. Our experiments show some surprising results for particular angles of this phase shift.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09874v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. J. Joshua Davis, Carey L. Jackman, Rainer Leonhardt, Paul J. Werbos, Maarten D. Hoogerland</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantifying the Upper Limit of Backflash Attack in Quantum Key Distribution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09984</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09984v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum Key Distribution (QKD) theoretically provides information-theoretic security based on physical laws. However, imperfections in practice lead to the possibility of quantum hacking on the QKD implementation, especially the passive attacks that are difficult to be detected. In this paper, we study experimentally and theoretically the upper limit of a backflash attack, as one of the vital passive attacks, on a fiber-based QKD system. We experimentally demonstrate the backflash attack on a full equipped fiber-based QKD receiver to show its feasibility and limited distinguish ratio of decoding. More importantly, we have developed a simulation model to analyze the maximum distinguish ratio of decoding can be achieved considering the wide-spectrum feature of backflash photons, which indicates that Eve can extract effective key information from 95.7% of the backflash photons. Consequently, the secure key rate of the decoy-state BB84 QKD system under backflash attack is calculated. This work provides a general methodology to comprehensively evaluate the effect of the backflash attack on a QKD system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09984v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jialei Su, Junxuan Liu, Zihao Chen, Mingyang Zhong, Qingquan Peng, Jiangfang Ding, Yijun Wang, Anqi Huang, Ying Guo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gaussian basis set approach to one-loop self-energy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.10027</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.10027v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report a method for the evaluation of the one-loop self-energy, to all orders in the external binding field, using a Gaussian basis set expansion. This choice of basis is motivated by its widespread use in molecular calculations. For a one-electron atom, our results show excellent agreement with those obtained using the exact Dirac--Coulomb wave functions. The developed method can be of interest for high-precision studies of heavy few-electron molecular systems, where the rigorous computation of QED corrections is currently a formidable task.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.10027v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D\'avid Ferenc, Maen Salman, Trond Saue</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Double descent in quantum machine learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.10077</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.10077v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The double descent phenomenon challenges traditional statistical learning theory by revealing scenarios where larger models do not necessarily lead to reduced performance on unseen data. While this counterintuitive behavior has been observed in a variety of classical machine learning models, particularly modern neural network architectures, it remains elusive within the context of quantum machine learning. In this work, we analytically demonstrate that quantum learning models can exhibit double descent behavior by drawing on insights from linear regression and random matrix theory. Additionally, our numerical experiments on quantum kernel methods across different real-world datasets and system sizes further confirm the existence of a test error peak, a characteristic feature of double descent. Our findings provide evidence that quantum models can operate in the modern, overparameterized regime without experiencing overfitting, thereby opening pathways to improved learning performance beyond traditional statistical learning theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.10077v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marie Kempkes, Aroosa Ijaz, Elies Gil-Fuster, Carlos Bravo-Prieto, Jakob Spiegelberg, Evert van Nieuwenburg, Vedran Dunjko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Advantage in Private Multiple Hypothesis Testing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.10152</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.10152v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: For multiple hypothesis testing based on classical data samples, we demonstrate a quantum advantage in the optimal privacy-utility trade-off (PUT), where the privacy and utility measures are set to (quantum) local differential privacy and the pairwise-minimum Chernoff information, respectively. To show the quantum advantage, we consider some class of hypotheses that we coin smoothed point masses. For such hypotheses, we derive an upper bound of the optimal PUT achieved by classical mechanisms, which is tight for some cases, and propose a certain quantum mechanism which achieves a better PUT than the upper bound. The proposed quantum mechanism consists of a classical-quantum channel whose outputs are pure states corresponding to a symmetric informationally complete positive operator-valued measure (SIC-POVM), and a depolarizing channel.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.10152v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Seung-Hyun Nam, Hyun-Young Park, Joonwoo Bae, Si-Hyeon Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Invariant Theory and Magic State Distillation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.10163</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.10163v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show that the performance of a linear self-orthogonal $GF(4)$ code for magic state distillation of Bravyi and Kitaev's $|T\rangle$-state is characterized by its simple weight enumerator. We compute weight enumerators of all such codes with less than 20 qubits and find none whose threshold exceeds that of the 5-qubit code. Using constraints on weight enumerators from invariant theory and linear programming, we obtain bounds on the exponent characterizing noise suppression of a $|T\rangle$-state distillation protocol. We also obtain new non-negativity constraints on such weight enumerators by demanding consistency of the associated magic state distillation routine. These ``quantum constraints'' lead to new bounds on the distance of classical self-dual and maximal self-orthogonal linear $GF(4)$ codes, in particular, implying the nonexistence of a self-dual $[12m, 6m, 2m+4]_{GF(4)}$ linear code.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.10163v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amolak Ratan Kalra, Shiroman Prakash</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Light-based Chromatic Aberration Correction of Ultrafast Electron Microscopes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.10210</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.10210v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose and theoretically demonstrate a technique that allows one to compensate for chromatic aberrations of traditional electron lenses in ultrafast electron microscopes. The technique is based on space- and time-dependent phase modulation of a pulsed electron beam using interaction with a shaped pulsed ponderomotive lens. The energy-selective focal distance is reached by combining the electron temporal chirp with the time-dependent size of the effective potential, with which the electrons interact. As a result, chromatic aberration can be reduced by up to a factor of seven. This approach paves the way for advanced transverse and longitudinal wavefront shaping of electrons in free space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.10210v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marius Constantin Chirita Mihaila, Neli La\v{s}tovi\v{c}kov\'a Streshkova, Martin Koz\'ak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Continuous variable measurement-device-independent quantum certification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.10217</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.10217v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Secure and reliable certification of quantum resources is a fundamental challenge in the advancement of next-generation quantum technologies, particularly as devices become more complex and integrated into practical applications, where parts of the system may be untrusted or inaccessible by users. Addressing this challenge requires certification methods that rely on minimal assumptions and limited trust while still faithfully and reliably verifying the quantum resources in question. For infinite-dimensional bosonic systems, existing certification methods rely on fully trusted and well calibrated measurement systems, leaving significant security vulnerabilities open. In this work, we present the first experimental demonstration of measurement-device-independent (MDI) certification schemes for infinite-dimensional bosonic systems, where the certification process is conducted using entirely untrusted measurement devices and assuming only the trusted preparation of coherent states. Specifically, we implement schemes for the MDI certification of continuous-variable (CV) entanglement and the operation of an elementary optical CV quantum memory. We leverage techniques of Bayesian metrology and exploit the practicality and accessibility of Gaussian quantum optics to achieve secure and efficient certification. These results demonstrate the potential of the MDI framework to enhance trust in quantum technologies with applications in quantum communication and quantum computing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.10217v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>B. L. Larsen (Center for Macroscopic Quantum States), A. A. E. Hajomer (Center for Macroscopic Quantum States), P. Abiuso (Institute for Quantum Optics and Quantum Information - IQOQI Vienna, Austrian Academy of Sciences, Austria), S. Izumi (Center for Macroscopic Quantum States), T. Gehring (Center for Macroscopic Quantum States), J. S. Neergaard-Nielsen (Center for Macroscopic Quantum States), A. Acin (ICFO-Institut de Ciencies Fotoniques, The Barcelona Institute of Science and Technology, Spain), U. L. Andersen (Center for Macroscopic Quantum States)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>End-to-end compilable implementation of quantum elliptic curve logarithm in Qrisp</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.10228</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.10228v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Elliptic curve cryptography (ECC) is a widely established cryptographic technique, recognized for its effectiveness and reliability across a broad range of applications such as securing telecommunications or safeguarding cryptocurrency wallets. Although being more robust than RSA, ECC is, nevertheless, also threatened by attacks based on Shor's algorithm, which made it a popular field of study in quantum information science. A variety of techniques have been proposed to perform EC arithmetic in quantum devices; however, software support for compiling these algorithms into executables is extremely limited. Within this work, we leverage the Qrisp programming language to realize one of the first fully compilable implementations of EC arithmetic and verify its correctness using Qrisp's built-in sparse matrix simulator.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.10228v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Diego Polimeni, Raphael Seidel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal multicore quantum computing with few interconnects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.10247</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.10247v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Noisy intermediate-scale quantum processors have produced a quantum computation revolution in recent times. However, to make further advances new strategies to overcome the error rate growth are needed. One possible way out is dividing these devices into many cores. On the other hand, the majorization criterion efficiently classifies quantum circuits in terms of their complexity, which can be directly related to their ability of performing non classically simulatable computations. In this paper, we use this criterion to study the complexity behavior of a paradigmatic universal family of random circuits distributed into several cores with different architectures. We find that the optimal complexity is reached with few interconnects, this giving further hope to actual implementations in nowadays available devices. A universal behavior is found irrespective of the architecture and (approximately) of the core size. We also analyze the complexity properties when scaling processors up by means of adding cores of the same size. We provide a conjecture to explain the results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.10247v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. Montes, F. Borondo, Gabriel G. Carlo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Genuine Multipartite Nonlocality sharing under sequential measurement</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.10274</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.10274v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The study of quantum nonlocality sharing has garnered significant attention, particularly for two-qubit and three-qubit entangled systems. In this paper, we extend the investigation to $n$-qubit Greenberger-Horne-Zeilinger (GHZ) systems, analyzing nonlocality sharing under unbiased unsharp measurements. Employing the Seevink and Svetlichny inequalities, we explore both unilateral and multilateral sequential measurement scenarios. In the unilateral scenario, we derive the range for which an observer's multiple copies can share genuine $n$-partite nonlocality with single copies of the remaining parties. In the multilateral scenario, we identify the maximum number of independent observers on $m$ sides who can share genuine $n$-partite nonlocality with other parties. A crucial aspect of our results is that all findings stem from a measurement strategy where each sequential observer utilizes unbiased unsharp measurements. As a specific case, for the four-qubit maximally entangled GHZ state, we demonstrate that at most two copies of an observer (e.g., Alice) can share nonlocality in the unilateral sequential measurement scenario. However, in the multilateral scenario, no additional sharing is possible compared to the unilateral case. This finding highlights the significance of unsharp measurements in optimizing the recycling of qubits for generating quantum nonlocality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.10274v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sk Sahadat Hossain, Indrani Chattopadhyay</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Low-overhead Magic State Circuits with Transversal CNOTs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.10291</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.10291v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: With the successful demonstration of transversal CNOTs in many recent experiments, it is the right moment to examine its implications on one of the most critical parts of fault-tolerant computation -- magic state preparation. Using an algorithm that can recompile and simplify a circuit of consecutive multi-qubit phase rotations, we manage to construct fault-tolerant circuits for CCZ, CS and T states with minimal T-depth and also much lower CNOT depths and qubit counts than before. These circuits can play crucial roles in fault-tolerant computation with transversal CNOTs, and we hope that the algorithms and methods developed in this paper can be used to further simplify other protocols in similar contexts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.10291v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nicholas Fazio, Mark Webster, Zhenyu Cai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum locally recoverable code with intersecting recovery sets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.10354</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.10354v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce the concept of quantum locally recoverable codes (qLRCs) with intersecting recovery sets. We derive a singleton-like bound for these codes by leveraging the additional information provided by the intersecting recovery sets. Furthermore, we provide a construction for qLRCs with intersecting recovery sets by introducing a variation of the hypergraph product. Finally, we apply our qLRC methods to obtain improved results for classical LRCs. These results may provide new insights into the locality of quantum error correction code.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.10354v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kaifeng Bu, Weichen Gu, Xiang Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GenSC-6G: A Prototype Testbed for Integrated Generative AI, Quantum, and Semantic Communication</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09918</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09918v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce a prototyping testbed, GenSC-6G, developed to generate a comprehensive dataset that supports the integration of generative artificial intelligence (AI), quantum computing, and semantic communication for emerging sixth-generation (6G) applications. The GenSC-6G dataset is designed with noise-augmented synthetic data optimized for semantic decoding, classification, and localization tasks, significantly enhancing flexibility for diverse AI-driven communication applications. This adaptable prototype supports seamless modifications across baseline models, communication modules, and goal-oriented decoders. Case studies demonstrate its application in lightweight classification, semantic upsampling, and edge-based language inference under noise conditions. The GenSC-6G dataset serves as a scalable and robust resource for developing goal-oriented communication systems tailored to the growing demands of 6G networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09918v1</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Brian E. Arfeto, Shehbaz Tariq, Uman Khalid, Trung Q. Duong, Hyundong Shin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Implementing Finite Impulse Response Filters on Quantum Computers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.10166</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.10166v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: While signal processing is a mature area, its connections with quantum computing have received less attention. In this work, we propose approaches that perform classical discrete-time signal processing using quantum systems. Our approaches encode the classical discrete-time input signal into quantum states, and design unitaries to realize classical concepts of finite impulse response (FIR) filters. We also develop strategies to cascade lower-order filters to realize higher-order filters through designing appropriate unitary operators. Finally, a few directions for processing quantum states on classical systems after converting them to classical signals are suggested for future work.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.10166v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aishwarya Majumdar, Bojko N. Bakalov, Dror Baron, Yuan Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
