<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>quant-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/quant-ph</link>
    <description>quant-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/quant-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 05:00:02 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Experimental Decoding Scrambled Quantum Information from the Future</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16335</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16335v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum information scrambling describes the rapid spread of initially localized information across an entire quantum many-body system through entanglement generation. Once scrambled, the original local information becomes encoded globally, inaccessible from any single subsystem. In this work, we introduce a protocol that enables information scrambling into the past, allowing decoding even before the original information is generated. This protocol is achieved by simulating a closed timelike curve (a theoretical construct in which particles can traverse backward in time) using probabilistic methods. Remarkably, we find that stronger scrambling dynamics enhance the fidelity of the decoding process. We further present a quantum circuit design and experimentally implement our protocol on cloud-based Quantinuum and IBM quantum computers. Our approach illuminates a unique quantum task: retrieving information encoded in the future without altering the past.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16335v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yi-Te Huang, Siang-Wei Huang, Jhen-Dong Lin, Adam Miranowicz, Neill Lambert, Franco Nori, Yueh-Nan Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Taming quantum systems: A tutorial for using shortcuts-to-adiabaticity, quantum optimal control, and reinforcement learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16436</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16436v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Precise manipulation of quantum effects at the atomic and nanoscale has become an essential task in ongoing scientific and technological endeavours. Quantum control methods are thus routinely exploited for research in areas such as quantum materials, quantum chemistry, and atomic and molecular physics, as well as in the development of quantum technologies like computing, simulation, and sensing. Here, we present a pedagogical introduction to the basics of quantum control methods in tutorial form, with the aim of providing newcomers to the field with the core concepts and practical tools to use these methods in their research. We focus on three areas: shortcuts to adiabaticity, quantum optimal control, and machine-learning-based control. We lay out the basic theoretical elements of each area in a pedagogical way and describe their application to a series of example cases. For these, we include detailed analytical derivations as well as extensive numerical results. As an outlook, we discuss quantum control methods in the broader context of quantum technologies development and complex quantum systems research, outlining potential connections and synergies between them.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16436v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Callum W. Duncan, Pablo M. Poggi, Marin Bukov, Nikolaj Thomas Zinner, Steve Campbell</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optical Nuclear Electric Resonance in LiNa: Selective Addressing of Nuclear Spins Through Pulsed Lasers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16470</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16470v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Optical nuclear electric resonance (ONER), a recently proposed protocol for nuclear spin manipulation in atomic systems via short laser pulses with MHz repetition rate, exploits the coupling between the nuclear quadrupole moment of a suitable atom and the periodic modulations of the electric field gradient generated by an optically stimulated electronic excitation. In this theory paper, we extend the scope of ONER from atomic to molecular systems and show that molecular vibrations do not interfere with our protocol. Exploring the diatomic molecule LiNa as a first benchmark system, our investigation showcases the robustness with respect to molecular vibration, and the ability to address and manipulate each of the two nuclear spins independently, simply by adjusting the repetition rate of a pulsed laser. Our findings suggest that it might be possible to shift complicated spin manipulation tasks required for quantum computing into the time domain by pulse-duration encoded laser signals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16470v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Johannes K. Krondorfer, Matthias Diez, Andreas W. Hauser</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reinforcement Learning for Quantum Circuit Design: Using Matrix Representations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16509</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16509v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum computing promises advantages over classical computing. The manufacturing of quantum hardware is in the infancy stage, called the Noisy Intermediate-Scale Quantum (NISQ) era. A major challenge is automated quantum circuit design that map a quantum circuit to gates in a universal gate set. In this paper, we present a generic MDP modeling and employ Q-learning and DQN algorithms for quantum circuit design. By leveraging the power of deep reinforcement learning, we aim to provide an automatic and scalable approach over traditional hand-crafted heuristic methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16509v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhiyuan Wang, Chunlin Feng, Christopher Poon, Lijian Huang, Xingjian Zhao, Yao Ma, Tianfan Fu, Xiao-Yang Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Experimental demonstration of a scalable room-temperature quantum battery</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16541</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16541v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Harnessing quantum phenomena in energy storage systems offers an opportunity to introduce a new generation of batteries with quantum-enhanced performance. Until now, the quantum battery has largely remained a theoretical concept, with little progress towards experimental realisation, due to the challenges in quantum coherent control. Here, we experimentally demonstrate a scalable room-temperature quantum battery with a multi-layered organic-microcavity design. We show that it exhibits superextensive charging, metastabilisation of stored energy, and generates superextensive electrical power, the latter an unpredicted phenomenon. The combination of these properties in a single device is the first demonstration of the full cycle of a quantum battery, laying the framework for future designs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16541v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kieran Hymas, Jack B. Muir, Daniel Tibben, Joel van Embden, Tadahiko Hirai, Christopher J. Dunn, Daniel E. G\'omez, James A. Hutchison, Trevor A. Smith, James Q. Quach</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analytical solutions for the quantum Brownian motion of a particle during a quantum quench</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16611</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16611v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A particle subjected to a fluctuating force originated from its interaction with an external quantum system undergoes quantum Brownian motion. This phenomenon is investigated in detail for the case of a particle confined by a harmonic potential and allowed to interact with a reservoir modeled as a continuum of oscillators, with particular emphasis on transient effects. Assuming a linear coupling between the particle and the reservoir, canonical quantization of the system is implemented, and analytical expressions for the quantum correlations are derived. These correlations are then applied to analyze energy conservation, and the particle Brownian motion is characterized from the perspective of the energy extracted from the reservoir.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16611v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ygor de Oliveira Souza, Caio C. Holanda Ribeiro, Vitorio A. De Lorenci</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Criteria for optimal entanglement-assisted long baseline imaging protocols</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16670</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16670v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum-entanglement-assisted telescopy protocol have been proposed and studied as a means to extend the baseline of optical interferometric telescopes. However, determining the optimality of specific quantum-assisted protocols remains an open question. We introduce a new framework for systematically characterizing different entanglement-assisted telescopy protocols by integrating tools from quantum metrology with the superselection rule (SSR) established in quantum information theory. We demonstrate that the estimation of interference fringes in a quantum telescopy can be objectively quantified and compared using the quantum Fisher information under the SSR constraint. Our framework demonstrates that interference fringe estimation in quantum telescopy can be objectively evaluated and compared using the quantum Fisher information under the SSR constraint. This approach defines the fundamental limits of astronomical estimation problems with finite entanglement resources. Building on this foundation, we propose new entanglement-assisted protocols that outperform previously known methods. Moreover, we show that these protocols are compatible with linear optical technology and could inspire the development of improved quantum telescopy schemes for near-term, lossy, repeater-less quantum networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16670v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yujie Zhang, Thomas Jennewein</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-fidelity QND readout and measurement back-action in a Tantalum-based high-coherence fluxonium qubit</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16691</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16691v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Implementing a precise measurement of the quantum state of a qubit is very critical for building a practical quantum processor as it plays an important role in state initialization and quantum error correction. While the transmon qubit has been the most commonly used design in small to medium-scale processors, the fluxonium qubit is emerging as a strong alternative with the potential for high-fidelity gate operation as a result of the high anharmonicity and high coherence achievable due to its unique design. Here, we explore the measurement characteristics of a tantalum-based high-coherence fluxonium qubit and demonstrate single-shot measurement fidelity (assignment fidelity) of 96.2% and 97.8% without and with the use of a Josephson Parametric Amplifier respectively. We study the back-action of the measurement photons on the qubit and measure a QND (repeatability) fidelity of 99.6%. We find that the measurement fidelity and QND nature are limited by state-mixing errors and our results suggest that a careful study of measurement-induced transitions in the fluxonium is needed to further optimize the readout performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16691v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gaurav Bothara, Srijita Das, Kishor V Salunkhe, Madhavi Chand, Jay Deshmukh, Meghan P Patankar, R Vijay</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Photon statistics of time dependent electronic excitation of spin injected quantum dots</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16747</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16747v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The time dynamics of spin-injected, electrically contacted quantum dots were investigated with a focus on the time evolution of photon statistics. Photon statistics can provide insights into whether the device functions as an effective single-photon emitter or exhibits higher-order emissions. Through these investigations, we found that the shape of the electrical excitation pulse has a direct impact on photon statistics. Specifically, the rising edge of the pulse corresponds to a significantly higher number of higher-order photon states, which decay much faster than single photons associated with the falling edge of the electrical pulse. This relationship implies that the pulse shape can be tailored to optimize the device as either a better single-photon source or a generator of higher-order photon states, with potential applications in creating deterministic higher-order photon Fock states. The ability to easily modify the pulse shape is a unique feature of electrically excited quantum dots.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16747v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chiran Wijesundara, Jeffrey Carvalho, Yuan Lu, Tim Thomay</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Designing Minimalistic Variational Quantum Ansatz Inspired by Algorithmic Cooling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16776</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16776v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This study introduces a novel minimalistic variational quantum ansatz inspired by algorithmic cooling principles. The proposed Heat Exchange algorithmic cooling ansatz (HE ansatz) facilitates efficient population redistribution without requiring bath resets, simplifying implementation on noisy intermediate-scale quantum (NISQ) devices. The HE ansatz achieves superior approximation ratios with the complete network \textsc{Maxcut} optimization problem compared to the conventional Hardware efficient and QAOA ansatz. We also proposed a new variational algorithm that utilize HE ansatz to compute the ground state of impure dissipative-system variational quantum eigensolver (dVQE) which achieved a sub-$1\%$ error in ground-state energy calculations of the 1D Heisenberg chain with impurity and successfully simulates the edge effect of impure spin chain, highlighting its potential for applications in quantum many-body physics. These results underscore the compatibility of the ansatz with hardware-efficient implementations, offering a scalable approach for solving complex quantum problems in disordered and open quantum systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16776v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Soyoung Shin, Ha Eum Kim, Hyeonjun Yeo, Kabgyun Jeong, Wonho Jhe, Jaewan Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum dynamics at finite temperature: Time-dependent quantum Monte Carlo study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16782</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16782v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work we investigate the ground state and the dissipative quantum dynamics of interacting charged particles in an external potential at finite temperature. The recently devised time-dependent quantum Monte Carlo (TDQMC) method allows a self-consistent treatment of the system of particles together with bath oscillators first for imaginary-time propagation of Schroedinger type of equations where both the system and the bath converge to their finite temperature ground state, and next for real time calculation where the dissipative dynamics is demonstrated. In that context the application of TDQMC appears as promising alternative to the path-integral related techniques where the real time propagation can be a challenge.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16782v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Ann. Phys. 371, 368 (2016)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ivan P. Christov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entanglement-based clock syntonization for quantum key distribution networks. Demonstration over a 50 km-long link</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16796</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16796v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present the implementation of a time synchronization protocol as part of an experimentally deployed entanglement-based quantum key distribution (QKD) link. The system is deployed over 48 km of optical fibers across the M\'etropole C\^ote d'Azur and enables secret cryptographic key exchange between two remote users, with an average rate of 7 kbps. We exploit the time correlation of paired photons generated by a high-quality source of energy-time entanglement implemented in the QKD link to synchronize two rubidium clocks located at the end stations. The level of stability achieved guarantees a time offset between the clocks under 12 ps at all time. We also show that this protocol requires less hardware than a typical synchronization protocol for QKD that would distribute a reference clock signal between the users.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16796v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yoann Pelet, Gr\'egory Sauder, S\'ebastien Tanzilli, Olivier Alibart, Anthony Martin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum XYZ cyclic codes for biased noise</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16827</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16827v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In some quantum computing architectures, Pauli noise is highly biased. Tailoring Quantum error-correcting codes to the biased noise may benefit reducing the physical qubit overhead without reducing the logical error rate. In this paper, we propose a family of quantum XYZ cyclic codes, which are the only one family of quantum cyclic codes with code distance increasing with code length to our best knowledge and have good error-correcting performance against biased noise. Our simulation results show that the quantum XYZ cyclic codes have $50\%$ code-capacity thresholds for all three types of pure Pauli noise and around $13\%$ code-capacity threshold for depolarizing noise. In the finite-bias regime, when the noise is biased towards Pauli $Z$ errors with noise bias ratios $\eta_Z=1000$, the corresponding code-capacity threshold is around $49\%$. Besides, we show that to reach the same code distance, the physical qubit overhead of XYZ cyclic code is much less than that of the XZZX surface code.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16827v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhipeng Liang, Fusheng Yang, Zhengzhong Yi, Xuan Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coherence-Assisted Entanglement Activation During Pure Dephasing Evolution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16834</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16834v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the system-environment entanglement activation during pure dephasing evolution, also called controlled unitary. A lower bound of generated entanglement is formulated with the initial coherence in the system and using relative entropy measure. For a qubit-environment case, this lower becomes a closed form by replacing conditional entropy with the overlap on the states in environment. Applying this result to the spin-boson model, we illustrate how the lower bound evolves as a function of time multiplied cutoff frequency, shown plots. The different behaviors of lower bounds with respect to Ohmicity, s=2 and s=3, corresponding to Markovian and non-Markovian evolution. In addition, we show that the decoherence in the system throughout the pure dephasing evolution represents another lower bound and upper bound of generated entanglement, indicating that larger entanglement generation leads more decoherence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16834v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Masaya Takahashi, Jaros{\l}aw K. Korbicz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Port-based telecloning of an unknown quantum state</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16878</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16878v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Telecloning is a protocol introduced by Murao et al. to distribute copies of an unknown quantum state to many receivers in a way that beats the trivial ``clone-and-teleport'' protocol. In the last decade, a new type of teleportation called port-based teleportation, in which the receiver can recover the state without having to actively perform correction operations, but simply by looking at the correct port, has been widely studied. In this paper, we consider the analog of telecloning, where conventional teleportation is replaced by the port-based variant. To achieve this, we generalize the optimal measurement used in port-based teleportation and develop a new one that achieves port-based telecloning. Numerical results show that, in certain cases, the proposed protocol is strictly better than the trivial clone-and-teleport approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16878v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Reiji Okada, Kohtaro Kato, Francesco Buscemi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Classical and quantum complex dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16938</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16938v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A generalization of classical mechanics is obtained from a complex parametrization of the phase space. The formalism supports complex Hamiltonian functions describing non-conservative classical mechanical systems. A quantization scheme that is general enough to incorporate non-stationary physical processes is also achieved.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16938v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sergio Giardino</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generative quantum combinatorial optimization by means of a novel conditional generative quantum eigensolver</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16986</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16986v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum computing is entering a transformative phase with the emergence of logical quantum processors, which hold the potential to tackle complex problems beyond classical capabilities. While significant progress has been made, applying quantum algorithms to real-world problems remains challenging. Hybrid quantum-classical techniques have been explored to bridge this gap, but they often face limitations in expressiveness, trainability, or scalability. In this work, we introduce conditional Generative Quantum Eigensolver (conditional-GQE), a context-aware quantum circuit generator powered by an encoder-decoder Transformer. Focusing on combinatorial optimization, we train our generator for solving problems with up to 10 qubits, exhibiting nearly perfect performance on new problems. By leveraging the high expressiveness and flexibility of classical generative models, along with an efficient preference-based training scheme, conditional-GQE provides a generalizable and scalable framework for quantum circuit generation. Our approach advances hybrid quantum-classical computing and contributes to accelerate the transition toward fault-tolerant quantum computing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16986v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shunya Minami, Kouhei Nakaji, Yohichi Suzuki, Al\'an Aspuru-Guzik, Tadashi Kadowaki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dephasing-induced leakage in multi-level superconducting quantum circuits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17008</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17008v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Superconducting quantum circuits, such as the transmon, have multiple quantum states beyond the computational subspace. These states can be populated during quantum logic operations; residual population in such states is known as leakage. While control methods can eliminate this error in ideal systems, leakage will arise from transient population in the presence of dephasing. This dephasing-induced leakage effect is analyzed, both analytically and numerically, for common single and two-qubit operations used in transmon-based approaches to quantum information processing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17008v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Frederick W. Strauch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simulating methylamine using symmetry adapted qubit-excitation-based variational quantum eigensolver</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17035</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17035v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we analyze the resources that are needed to simulate certain molecules on a medium-scale quantum computer with the use of the variational quantum eigensolver (VQE) approach. As the conventional realization of the VQE approach significant amount of resources for simulation, %requires prohibitively large we propose and analyze optimization techniques based on molecular point group symmetries (symmetry adaption) and compact excitation circuits (qubit-excitation-based). These optimizations allows significant reduction of the essential computational capabilities yet ensuring the convergence to the required energies. We first apply this approach for small molecules, such as LiH and BeH$_2$, to evaluate their compatibility, accuracy, and potential applicability to larger problems. Then we demonstrate that instead of 600,000 two-qubit operations (in the STO-3G basis using a naive version of the Unitary Coupled Cluster ansatz), we are able to simulate methylamine molecules with 26 qubits and about 12,000 of two-qubit gates using our method. We accomplish our analysis by estimating required resources for a formic acid molecule, whose simulation requires about 15,000 of two-qubit gates. Thus, the proposed combination of certain optimization methods can reduce the number of two-qubit operations by several orders of magnitude.Although, we present alternative approaches that are of interest in the context of the further optimization in the number of two-qubit operation, we note that these approaches do not perform well enough in terms of the convergence to required energies. While these challenges persist, our resource analysis represents a valuable step towards the practical use of quantum computers and the development of better methods for optimizing computing resources.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17035v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Konstantin M. Makushin, Aleksey K. Fedorov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the sampling complexity of coherent superpositions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17071</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17071v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider the problem of sampling from the distribution of measurement outcomes when applying a POVM to a superposition $|\Psi\rangle = \sum_{j=0}^{\chi-1} c_j |\psi_j\rangle$ of $\chi$ pure states. We relate this problem to that of drawing samples from the outcome distribution when measuring a single state $|\psi_j\rangle$ in the superposition. Here $j$ is drawn from the distribution $p(j)=|c_j|^2/\|c\|^2_2$ of normalized amplitudes. We give an algorithm which $-$ given $O(\chi \|c\|_2^2 \log1/\delta)$ such samples and calls to oracles evaluating the involved probability density functions $-$ outputs a sample from the target distribution except with probability at most $\delta$.
  In many cases of interest, the POVM and individual states in the superposition have efficient classical descriptions allowing to evaluate matrix elements of POVM elements and to draw samples from outcome distributions. In such a scenario, our algorithm gives a reduction from strong classical simulation (i.e., the problem of computing outcome probabilities) to weak simulation (i.e., the problem of sampling). In contrast to prior work focusing on finite-outcome POVMs, this reduction also applies to continuous-outcome POVMs. An example is homodyne or heterodyne measurements applied to a superposition of Gaussian states. Here we obtain a sampling algorithm with time complexity $O(N^3 \chi^3 \|c\|_2^2 \log1/\delta)$ for a state of $N$ bosonic modes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17071v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Beatriz Dias, Robert Koenig</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhancing the fidelity of stimulated Raman transitions with simple phase shifts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17093</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17093v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We demonstrate that in stimulated Raman transitions, introducing one or two simple phase shifts to the control fields significantly enhances the fidelity of state manipulation while simultaneously reducing leakage to the intermediate excited state. Our approach achieves high-fidelity quantum gate operations between the two target states under arbitrary detuning conditions. Notably, the average population in the intermediate excited state is approximately halved, without extending the overall evolution time. Additionally, our method exhibits greater robustness to static amplitude and detuning errors compared to conventional adiabatic elimination techniques, and maintains higher fidelity even in the presence of dissipation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17093v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hua-Yang Wang, Xu-Yang Chen, Zhen-Yu Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Search with the Signless Laplacian</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17128</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17128v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Continuous-time quantum walks are typically effected by either the discrete Laplacian or the adjacency matrix. In this paper, we explore a third option: the signless Laplacian, which has applications in algebraic graph theory and may arise in layered antiferromagnetic materials. We explore spatial search on the complete bipartite graph, which is generally irregular and breaks the equivalence of the three quantum walks for regular graphs, and where the search oracle breaks the equivalence of the Laplacian and signless Laplacian quantum walks on bipartite graphs without the oracle. We prove that a uniform superposition over all the vertices of the graph partially evolves to the marked vertices in one partite set, with the choice of set depending on the jumping rate of the quantum walk. We boost this success probability to 1 by proving that a particular non-uniform initial state completely evolves to the marked vertices in one partite set, again depending on the jumping rate. For some parameter regimes, the signless Laplacian yields the fastest search algorithm of the three, suggesting that it could be a new tool for developing faster quantum algorithms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17128v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Molly E. McLaughlin, Thomas G. Wong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entanglement-based Quantum Key Distribution in the Daylight and Uplink Satellite Configuration: Proof-of-Principal Demonstration and Feasibility Test</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17130</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17130v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Experimental realization of entanglement-based quantum key distribution (QKD) in a daylight uplink (ground-to-satellite) communication channel is highly challenging due to the very low signal-to-noise ratio (SNR) of this configuration and it has yet to be successfully implemented to date. While current research efforts focus on weak coherent pulse (WCP) sources for daylight QKD, we present a proof-of-principle demonstration of uplink-daylight QKD in a free-space-fiber hybrid configuration using polarization-entangled photon pairs generated via a spontaneous parametric down-conversion (SPDC) process. The simulated uplink channel attenuation reaches up to 50 dB, equivalent to low-earth-orbit (LEO) distances. Furthermore, the detected noise level (up to a few MHz) in the receiver telescope is representative of daylight conditions. The enhancement of SNR is achieved by implementing rigorous filtering on spatial, spectral, and temporal modes. Our ultra-bright source of entangled photons, characterized by a narrow spectral bandwidth of 0.54 nm FWHM, ensures minimal signal attenuation. We also propose a novel theoretical model of entanglement-based QKD link that fits our experimental data perfectly and is consistent with the prevailing models in the field. Our model considers a non-ideal entangled photon source and is applicable to both continuous wave (CW) and pulse-pumped sources. Using this model, we demonstrate that entanglement-based QKD is feasible under uplink daylight conditions in LEO satellites, but only up to a distance of 400 km, utilizing current state-of-the-art single-mode fiber (SMF) coupling technology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17130v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kaushik Joarder, Jakub Szlachetka, Piotr Kolenderski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UDiTQC: U-Net-Style Diffusion Transformer for Quantum Circuit Synthesis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16380</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16380v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Quantum computing is a transformative technology with wide-ranging applications, and efficient quantum circuit generation is crucial for unlocking its full potential. Current diffusion model approaches based on U-Net architectures, while promising, encounter challenges related to computational efficiency and modeling global context. To address these issues, we propose UDiT,a novel U-Net-style Diffusion Transformer architecture, which combines U-Net's strengths in multi-scale feature extraction with the Transformer's ability to model global context. We demonstrate the framework's effectiveness on two tasks: entanglement generation and unitary compilation, where UDiTQC consistently outperforms existing methods. Additionally, our framework supports tasks such as masking and editing circuits to meet specific physical property requirements. This dual advancement, improving quantum circuit synthesis and refining generative model architectures, marks a significant milestone in the convergence of quantum computing and machine learning research.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16380v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhiwei Chen, Hao Tang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum advantage in decentralized control of POMDPs: A control-theoretic view of the Mermin-Peres square</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16690</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16690v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Consider a decentralized partially-observed Markov decision problem (POMDP) with multiple cooperative agents aiming to maximize a long-term-average reward criterion. We observe that the availability, at a fixed rate, of entangled states of a product quantum system between the agents, where each agent has access to one of the component systems, can result in strictly improved performance even compared to the scenario where common randomness is provided to the agents, i.e. there is a quantum advantage in decentralized control. This observation comes from a simple reinterpretation of the conclusions of the well-known Mermin-Peres square, which underpins the Mermin-Peres game. While quantum advantage has been demonstrated earlier in one-shot team problems of this kind, it is notable that there are examples where there is a quantum advantage for the one-shot criterion but it disappears in the dynamical scenario. The presence of a quantum advantage in dynamical scenarios is thus seen to be a novel finding relative to the current state of knowledge about the achievable performance in decentralized control problems.
  This paper is dedicated to the memory of Pravin P. Varaiya.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16690v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Venkat Anantharam</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Benchmarking Quantum Convolutional Neural Networks for Signal Classification in Simulated Gamma-Ray Burst Detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17041</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17041v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This study evaluates the use of Quantum Convolutional Neural Networks (QCNNs) for identifying signals resembling Gamma-Ray Bursts (GRBs) within simulated astrophysical datasets in the form of light curves. The task addressed here focuses on distinguishing GRB-like signals from background noise in simulated Cherenkov Telescope Array Observatory (CTAO) data, the next-generation astrophysical observatory for very high-energy gamma-ray science. QCNNs, a quantum counterpart of classical Convolutional Neural Networks (CNNs), leverage quantum principles to process and analyze high-dimensional data efficiently. We implemented a hybrid quantum-classical machine learning technique using the Qiskit framework, with the QCNNs trained on a quantum simulator. Several QCNN architectures were tested, employing different encoding methods such as Data Reuploading and Amplitude encoding. Key findings include that QCNNs achieved accuracy comparable to classical CNNs, often surpassing 90\%, while using fewer parameters, potentially leading to more efficient models in terms of computational resources. A benchmark study further examined how hyperparameters like the number of qubits and encoding methods affected performance, with more qubits and advanced encoding methods generally enhancing accuracy but increasing complexity. QCNNs showed robust performance on time-series datasets, successfully detecting GRB signals with high precision. The research is a pioneering effort in applying QCNNs to astrophysics, offering insights into their potential and limitations. This work sets the stage for future investigations to fully realize the advantages of QCNNs in astrophysical data analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17041v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Farida Farsian, Nicol\`o Parmiggiani, Alessandro Rizzo, Gabriele Panebianco, Andrea Bulgarelli, Francesco Schillir\`o, Carlo Burigana, Vincenzo Cardone, Luca Cappelli, Massimo Meneghetti, Giuseppe Murante, Giuseppe Sarracino, Roberto Scaramella, Vincenzo Testa, Tiziana Trombetti</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
