<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>quant-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/quant-ph</link>
    <description>quant-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/quant-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 05:00:02 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Entanglement-assisted variational algorithm for discrete optimization problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09078</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09078v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: From fundamental sciences to economics and industry, discrete optimization problems are ubiquitous. Yet, their complexity often renders exact solutions intractable, necessitating the use of approximate methods. Heuristics inspired by classical physics have long played a central role in this domain. More recently, quantum annealing has emerged as a promising alternative, with hardware implementations realized on both analog and digital quantum devices. Here, we develop a heuristic inspired by quantum annealing, using Generalized Coherent States as a parameterized variational Ansatz to represent the quantum state. This framework allows for the analytical computation of energy and gradients with low-degree polynomial complexity, enabling the study of large problems with thousands of spins. Concurrently, these states capture non-trivial entanglement, crucial for the effectiveness of quantum annealing. We benchmark the heuristic on the three-dimensional Edwards-Anderson model and compare the solution quality and runtime of our method to other popular heuristics. Our findings suggest that it offers a scalable way to leverage quantum effects for complex optimization problems, potentially surpassing conventional alternatives in large-scale applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09078v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lorenzo Fioroni, Vincenzo Savona</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Demonstrating quantum error mitigation on logical qubits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09079</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09079v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A long-standing challenge in quantum computing is developing technologies to overcome the inevitable noise in qubits. To enable meaningful applications in the early stages of fault-tolerant quantum computing, devising methods to suppress post-correction logical failures is becoming increasingly crucial. In this work, we propose and experimentally demonstrate the application of zero-noise extrapolation, a practical quantum error mitigation technique, to error correction circuits on state-of-the-art superconducting processors. By amplifying the noise on physical qubits, the circuits yield outcomes that exhibit a predictable dependence on noise strength, following a polynomial function determined by the code distance. This property enables the effective application of polynomial extrapolation to mitigate logical errors. Our experiments demonstrate a universal reduction in logical errors across various quantum circuits, including fault-tolerant circuits of repetition and surface codes. We observe a favorable performance in multi-round error correction circuits, indicating that this method remains effective when the circuit depth increases. These results advance the frontier of quantum error suppression technologies, opening a practical way to achieve reliable quantum computing in the early fault-tolerant era.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09079v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aosai Zhang, Haipeng Xie, Yu Gao, Jia-Nan Yang, Zehang Bao, Zitian Zhu, Jiachen Chen, Ning Wang, Chuanyu Zhang, Jiarun Zhong, Shibo Xu, Ke Wang, Yaozu Wu, Feitong Jin, Xuhao Zhu, Yiren Zou, Ziqi Tan, Zhengyi Cui, Fanhao Shen, Tingting Li, Yihang Han, Yiyang He, Gongyu Liu, Jiayuan Shen, Han Wang, Yanzhe Wang, Hang Dong, Jinfeng Deng, Hekang Li, Zhen Wang, Chao Song, Qiujiang Guo, Pengfei Zhang, Ying Li, H. Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>More resourceful states improve quantum channel discrimination</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09205</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09205v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: One of the key issues in quantum discrimination problems is understanding the extent of the advantages in discrimination performance when using resource states compared to resourceless states. We show that in any resource theory of states, which may not be convex, the extent to which the maximum average success probability can be improved in quantum channel discrimination problems without using auxiliary systems can be precisely quantified by the robustness measure. Furthermore, we demonstrate that the robustness measure can also quantify the improvement in channel discrimination problems that use auxiliary systems. Using these findings, resources can be fully characterized to achieve higher success probabilities than any state without the given resource in channel discrimination problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09205v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kenji Nakahira</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diatomic and Polyatomic Heteronuclear Ultralong-Range Rydberg Molecules</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09282</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09282v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Ultra-long-range Rydberg molecules (ULRMs) have attracted significant interest due to their unique electronic properties and potential applications in quantum technologies. We theoretically investigate the formation and characteristics of heteronuclear ULRMs, focusing on Rb-Cs systems. We explore the vibrational energy levels of heteronuclear nD ULRMs and compare them with homonuclear counterparts. We also predict the formation of polyatomic heteronuclear ULRMs, discussing how the binding energy and spectral features evolve as the number of ground-state atoms increases. Our theoretical predictions are presented in terms of molecular spectra and provide insight into the formation dynamics of these systems. The study further explores the potential applications of heteronuclear ULRMs in quantum information processing, quantum simulation, and precision measurements, offering new avenues for future research in many-body physics and quantum technologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09282v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qing Li, Shi-Yao Shao, Li-Hua Zhang, Bang Liu, Zheng-Yuan Zhang, Jun Zhang, Qi-Feng Wang, Han-Chao Chen, Yu Ma, Tian-Yu Han, Dong-Sheng Ding, Bao-Sen Shi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>General detectability measure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09303</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09303v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Distinguishing resource states from resource-free states is a fundamental task in quantum information. We have approached the state detection problem through a hypothesis testing framework, with the alternative hypothesis set comprising resource-free states in a general context. Consequently, we derived the optimal exponential decay rate of the failure probability for detecting a given $n$-tensor product state when the resource-free states are separable states, positive partial transpose (PPT) states, or the convex hull of the set of stabilizer states. This optimal exponential decay rate is determined by the minimum of the reverse relative entropy, indicating that this minimum value serves as the general detectability measure. The key technique of this paper is a quantum version of empirical distribution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09303v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Masahito Hayashi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Indefinite causal order strategy nor adaptive strategy does not improve the estimation of group action</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09312</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09312v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider estimation of unknown unitary operation when the set of possible unitary operations is given by a projective unitary representation of a compact group. We show that indefinite causal order strategy nor adaptive strategy does not improve the performance of this estimation when error function satisfies group covariance. That is, the optimal parallel strategy gives the optimal performance even under indefinite causal order strategy and adaptive strategy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09312v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Masahito Hayashi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Creation and manipulation of Schr\"odinger cat states based on semiclassical predictions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09318</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09318v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider the generation of Schr\"odinger cat states using a quantum measurement-induced logical gate where entanglement between the input state of the target oscillator and the Fock state of the ancillary system produced by the quantum non-demolition entangling $C_Z$ operation is combined with the homodyne measurement. We utilize the semiclassical approach to construct both the input-output mapping of the field variables in the phase space and the wave function of the output state. This approach is found to predict that the state at the gate output is represented by a minimum disturbed cat-like state which is a superposition of two initial state copies symmetrically displaced by momentum variable. For the target oscillator prepared in the coherent state, we show that the fidelity between the exact solution for the gate output state and the "perfect" Schr\"odinger cat reconstructed from the semiclassical theory can reach high values exceeding 0.99.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09318v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>N. G. Veselkova, Roman Goncharov, Alexei D. Kiselev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient measure of information backflow with quasi-stochastic process</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09374</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09374v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Characterization and quantification of non-Markovian dynamics in open quantum systems is a topical issue in the rapidly developing field of quantum computation and quantum communication. A standard approach based on the notion of information backflow detects the flow of information from the environment back to the system. Numerous measures of information backflow have been proposed using different definitions of distinguishability between pairs of quantum states. These measures, however, necessitate optimization over the state space which can be analytically challenging or numerically demanding. Here, we propose an alternative witness and measure of information backflow that is explicitly state-independent by utilizing the concept of quasiprobability representation and recent advances in the theory of majorization for quasiprobabilities. We illustrate its use over several paradigmatic examples, demonstrating consistent Markovian conditions with known results and also reported necessary and sufficient condition for qutrit system in random unitary channel. The paper concludes with discussions on the foundational implications of quantum dynamical evolution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09374v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kelvin Onggadinata, Teck Seng Koh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Testing Born's rule via photoionization of helium</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09438</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09438v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: It is shown how state-of-the-art attosecond photoionization experiments can test Born's rule -- a postulate of quantum mechanics -- via the so-called Sorkin test. A simulation of the Sorkin test under consideration of typical experimental noise and data acquisition efficiencies infers an achievable measurement precision in the range of the best Sorkin tests to date. The implementation of further fundamental tests of quantum mechanics is discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09438v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peter Robert F\"orderer, Andreas Buchleitner, David Busto, Christoph Dittel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comprehensive Survey of QML: From Data Analysis to Algorithmic Advancements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09528</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09528v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum Machine Learning represents a paradigm shift at the intersection of Quantum Computing and Machine Learning, leveraging quantum phenomena such as superposition, entanglement, and quantum parallelism to address the limitations of classical approaches in processing high-dimensional and large-scale datasets. This survey provides a comprehensive analysis of Quantum Machine Learning, detailing foundational concepts, algorithmic advancements, and their applications across domains such as healthcare, finance, and quantum chemistry. Key techniques, including Quantum Support Vector Machine, Quantum Neural Network, Quantum Decision Trees, and hybrid quantum-classical models, are explored with a focus on their theoretical foundations, computational benefits, and comparative performance against classical counterparts. While the potential for exponential speedups and enhanced efficiency is evident, the field faces significant challenges, including hardware constraints, noise, and limited qubit coherence in the current era of Noisy Intermediate-Scale Quantum devices. Emerging solutions, such as error mitigation techniques, hybrid frameworks, and advancements in quantum hardware, are discussed as critical enablers for scalable and fault-tolerant Quantum Machine Learning systems. By synthesizing state-of-the-art developments and identifying research gaps, this survey aims to provide a foundational resource for advancing Quantum Machine Learning toward practical, real-world applications in tackling computationally intensive problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09528v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sahil Tomar, Rajeshwar Tripathi, Sandeep Kumar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strong and Noise-Tolerant Entanglement in Dissipative Optomechanics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09541</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09541v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Macroscopic entanglement, as critical quantum resources in quantum information science, has been extensively studied in optomechanical systems with purely dispersive coupling over the past decades. However, quantum entanglement, induced by purely dissipative coupling, remains unexplored. In this work, we study quantum entanglement in a Michelson-Sagnac interferometer, where the dispersive and the dissipative coupling can be arbitrarily switched on and off. With current experimental parameters, we demonstrate that the steady-state mechanical displacement exhibits a nonlinear (linear) dependence on the driving power with the purely dispersive (dissipative) coupling. Further, we find that quantum entanglement generated by purely dissipative coupling is significantly stronger and more noise-tolerant than that generated by purely dispersive coupling. When both couplings coexist, entanglement is weakened due to interference. Our findings provide a promising path to engineer strong and noise-tolerant quantum entanglement in purely dissipative quantum systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09541v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiaojiao Chen, Wei Xiong, Dong Wang, Liu Ye</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cooperative Decay of N Atoms in a Ring Configuration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09550</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09550v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We provide an analytic expression of the spectrum of the cooperative decay rate of N two-level atoms regularly distributed on a ring in the single-excitation configuration. The results are obtained first for the scalar model and then extended to the vectorial light model, assuming all the dipoles are aligned.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09550v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3390/atoms13010008</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Atoms 2025, 13, 8</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Nicola Piovella</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Performance Analysis for Crosstalk Errors between Parallel Entangling Gates in Trapped Ion Quantum Error Correction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09554</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09554v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The ability to execute a large number of quantum gates in parallel is a fundamental requirement for quantum error correction, allowing an error threshold to exist under the finite coherence time of physical qubits. Recently, two-dimensional ion crystals have been demonstrated as a plausible approach to scale up the qubit number in a trapped ion quantum computer. However, although the long-range Coulomb interaction between the ions enables their strong connectivity, it also complicates the design of parallel gates and leads to intrinsic crosstalk errors. Here we examine the effects of crosstalk errors on a rotated surface code. We show that, instead of the distance-3 code considered in previous works, a distance-5 code is necessary to correct the two-qubit crosstalk error. We numerically calculate the logical error rates and coherence times under various crosstalk errors, gate infidelities and coherence times of the physical qubits, and we optimize the parallelism level according to the competition between different error sources. We show that a break-even point can be reached under realistic parameters. We further analyze the spatial dependence of the crosstalk, and discuss the scaling of the logical error rate versus the code distance for the long-term goal of a logical error rate below $10^{-10}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09554v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fangxuan Liu, Gaoxiang Tang, Luming Duan, Yukai Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive-depth randomized measurement for fermionic observables</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09574</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09574v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Accurate estimation of fermionic observables is essential for advancing quantum physics and chemistry. The fermionic classical shadow (FCS) method offers an efficient framework for estimating these observables without requiring a transformation into a Pauli basis. However, the random matchgate circuits in FCS require polynomial-depth circuits with a brickwork structure, which presents significant challenges for near-term quantum devices with limited computational resources. To address this limitation, we introduce an adaptive-depth fermionic classical shadow (ADFCS) protocol designed to reduce the circuit depth while maintaining the estimation accuracy and the order of sample complexity. Through theoretical analysis and numerical fitting, we establish that the required depth for approximating a fermionic observable $H$ scales as $\max\{d^2_{\text{int}}(H)/\log n, d_{\text{int}}(H)\}$ where $d_{\text{int}}$ is the interaction distance of $H$. We demonstrate the effectiveness of the ADFCS protocol through numerical experiments, which show similar accuracy to the traditional FCS method while requiring significantly fewer resources. Additionally, we apply ADFCS to compute the expectation value of the Kitaev chain Hamiltonian, further validating its performance in practical scenarios. Our findings suggest that ADFCS can enable more efficient quantum simulations, reducing circuit depth while preserving the fidelity of quantum state estimations, offering a viable solution for near-term quantum devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09574v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kaiming Bian, Bujiao Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimizing hypergraph product codes with random walks, simulated annealing and reinforcement learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09622</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09622v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Hypergraph products are quantum low-density parity-check (LDPC) codes constructed from two classical LDPC codes. Although their dimension and distance depend only on the parameters of the underlying classical codes, optimizing their performance against various noise channels remains challenging. This difficulty partly stems from the complexity of decoding in the quantum setting. The standard, ad hoc approach typically involves selecting classical LDPC codes with large girth. In this work, we focus on optimizing performance against the quantum erasure channel. A key advantage of this channel is the existence of an efficient maximum-likelihood decoder, which enables us to employ optimization techniques based on sampling random codes, such as Reinforcement Learning (RL) and Simulated Annealing (SA). Our results indicate that these techniques improve performance relative to the state-of-the-art.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09622v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bruno C. A. Freire, Nicolas Delfosse, Anthony Leverrier</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermodynamics of coherent energy exchanges between lasers and two-level systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09625</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09625v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the quantum thermodynamics of a coherent macroscopic electromagnetic field (laser) coupled to a two-level system (qubit) near resonance, from weak to strong driving regimes. This combined system is, in turn, weakly coupled to a thermal radiation field, and can be described by an autonomous quantum master equation. We show that the laser acts as an autonomous work source and that, in the macroscopic limit, the work produced is independent of the phase of the laser. Using the dressed qubit approach, we show that the variation of energy in the laser is not the work transferred to the dressed qubit, which is instead obtained from the ''dressed laser'' -- a coherent superposition of the laser and the qubit. Using a two-point measurement technique with counting fields, we obtain the full counting statistics for the work of the laser and dressed laser, and show that they satisfy Crooks fluctuation theorems. We then use these theorems as criteria to investigate the thermodynamic consistency of quantum master equations, first in the autonomous setup for the combined system, then in the non-autonomous setup where the coherent field is eliminated and effectively described by a time dependent external field. Treating the laser as an external field in known to yield expressions for the work which are in contradiction with quantum thermodynamics predictions in the strong drive regime. We show that these inconsistencies stem from a confusion between the laser and dressed laser, and show how to correct them. We also derive a new master equation, thermodynamically consistent at all driving regimes, from which the Bloch and Floquet master equations can be obtained using additional approximations (of which we also examine the consistency).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09625v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ariane Soret, Massimiliano Esposito</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A symmetry-protected topological optical lattice clock</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09658</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09658v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We theoretically propose a tunable implementation of symmetry-protected topological phases in a synthetic superlattice, taking advantage of the long coherence time and exquisite spectral resolutions offered by gravity-tilted optical lattice clocks. We describe a protocol similar to Rabi spectroscopy that can be used to probe the distinct topological properties of our system. We then demonstrate how the sensitivity of clocks and interferometers can be improved by the topological robustness to unwanted experimental imperfections. The proposed implementation opens a path to exploit the unique opportunities offered by symmetry-protected topological phases in state-of-the-art quantum sensors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09658v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tianrui Xu, Anjun Chu, Kyungtae Kim, James K. Thompson, Jun Ye, Tilman Esslinger, Ana Maria Rey</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Incorporating Quantum Advantage in Quantum Circuit Generation through Genetic Programming</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09682</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09682v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Designing efficient quantum circuits that leverage quantum advantage compared to classical computing has become increasingly critical. Genetic algorithms have shown potential in generating such circuits through artificial evolution. However, integrating quantum advantage into the fitness function of these algorithms remains unexplored. In this paper, we aim to enhance the efficiency of quantum circuit design by proposing two novel approaches for incorporating quantum advantage metrics into the fitness function of genetic algorithms.1 We evaluate our approaches based on the Bernstein-Vazirani Problem and the Unstructured Database Search Problem as test cases. The results demonstrate that our approaches not only improve the convergence speed of the genetic algorithm but also produce circuits comparable to expert-designed solutions. Our findings suggest that automated quantum circuit design using genetic algorithms that incorporate a measure of quantum advantage is a promising approach to accelerating the development of quantum algorithms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09682v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christoph Stein, Michael F\"arber</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Converse bounds for quantum hypothesis exclusion: A divergence-radius approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09712</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09712v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Hypothesis exclusion is an information-theoretic task in which an experimenter aims at ruling out a false hypothesis from a finite set of known candidates, and an error occurs if and only if the hypothesis being ruled out is the ground truth. For the tasks of quantum state exclusion and quantum channel exclusion -- where hypotheses are represented by quantum states and quantum channels, respectively -- efficiently computable upper bounds on the asymptotic error exponents were established in a recent work of the current authors [Ji et al., arXiv:2407.13728 (2024)], where the derivation was based on nonasymptotic analysis. In this companion paper of our previous work, we provide alternative proofs for the same upper bounds on the asymptotic error exponents of quantum state and channel exclusion, but using a conceptually different approach from the one adopted in the previous work. Specifically, we apply strong converse results for asymmetric binary hypothesis testing to distinguishing an arbitrary ``dummy'' hypothesis from each of the concerned candidates. This leads to the desired upper bounds in terms of divergence radii via a geometrically inspired argument.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09712v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kaiyuan Ji, Hemant K. Mishra, Mil\'an Mosonyi, Mark M. Wilde</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
