<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>quant-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/quant-ph</link>
    <description>quant-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/quant-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 05:00:02 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Secure Composition of Quantum Key Distribution and Symmetric Key Encryption</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08435</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08435v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum key distribution (QKD) allows Alice and Bob to share a secret key over an insecure channel with proven information-theoretic security against an adversary whose strategy is bounded only by the laws of physics. Composability-based security proofs of QKD ensure that using the established key with a one-time-pad encryption scheme provides information theoretic secrecy for the message. In this paper, we consider the problem of using the QKD established key with a secure symmetric key-based encryption algorithm and use an approach based on hybrid encryption to provide a proof of security for the composition.
  Hybrid encryption was first proposed as a public key cryptographic algorithm with proven security for messages of unrestricted length. We use an extension of this framework to correlated randomness setting (Sharifian et al. in ISIT 2021) to propose a quantum-enabled Key Encapsulation Mechanism (qKEM) and quantum-enabled hybrid encryption (qHE), and prove a composition theorem for the security of the qHE. We construct a qKEM with proven security using an existing QKD (Portmann et al. in Rev. of Mod. Physics 2022). Using this qKEM with a secure Data Encapsulation Mechanism (DEM), that can be constructed using a one-time symmetric key encryption scheme, results in an efficient encryption system for unrestricted length messages with proved security against an adversary with access to efficient computations on a quantum computer (i.e. post-quantum secure encryption without using any computational assumptions.)</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08435v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kunal Dey, Reihaneh Safavi-Naini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modeling Entanglement-Based Quantum Key Distribution for the NASA Quantum Communications Analysis Suite</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08476</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08476v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: One of the most practical, and sought after, applications of quantum mechanics in the field of information science is the use of entanglement distribution to communicate quantum information effectively. Similar to the continued improvements of functional quantum computers over the past decade, advances in demonstrations of entanglement distribution over long distances may enable new applications in aeronautics and space communications. The existing NASA Quantum Communications Analysis Suite (NQCAS) software models such applications, but limited experimental data exists to verify the model's theoretical results. There is, however, a large body of experimental data in the relevant literature for entanglement-based quantum key distribution (QKD). This paper details a Monte Carlo-based QKD model that uses NQCAS input parameters to generate an estimated QKD link budget for verification of NQCAS. The model generates link budget statistics like key rates, error rates, and S values that can then be compared to the experimental values in the literature. Preliminary comparisons show many similarities between the simulated and experimental data, supporting the model's validity. A verified NQCAS model will inform experimental work conducted in Glenn Research Center's (GRC) NASA Quantum Metrology Laboratory (NQML), supporting the United States Quantum Initiative and potential NASA missions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08476v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.13140/RG.2.2.26965.03041</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Michael J. P. Kuban, Ian R. Nemitz, Yousef K. Chahine</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analysis of quantum mechanics with real-valued Schr\"{o}dinger equation,single-event quantum-path dynamics, Mauprtuis path in parameter space, and branching paths beyond semiclassics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08606</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08606v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We analyze the Schr\"{o}dinger dynamics and the Schr\"{o}dinger function (or the so-called wavefunction) in the following four aspects. (1) The Schr\"{o}dinger equation is reconstructed from scratch in the real field only, without referring to Newtonian mechanics nor optics. Only the very simple conditions such as the space-time translational symmetry and the conservation of flux and energy are imposed on the factorization of the density distribution in configuration space, giving rise to a two-dimensional real vector. On returning to the original Schr\"{o}dinger equation, the imaginary number arises naturally. (2) Like the Langevin equation in a Brownian dynamics, we formulate a single-event path dynamics in quantum mechanics, contrasting with the Schr\"{o}dinger distribution function. The path thus attained is referred to as one-world path, which represents, for instance, a path of a singly launched electron in the double-slit experiment that leaves a spot at the measurement board, while many of accumulated spots give rise to the fringe pattern. We start from the Feynman-Kac formula to draw a relation between a stochastic dynamics and the parabolic differential equations, to one of which the Schr\"{o}dinger equation is transformed. (3) To highlight the roles of the flux and energy conservation in the Schr\"{o}dinger dynamics, we build that the quantum Maupertuis-Hamilton principle, which reveals the symplectic structure in the parameter space. (4) We track how the inherent quantum nature like the Huygens-principle-like properties is built. We show that classical trajectory components in semiclassics are demanded to branch into many coherent pieces beyond the semiclassical regime and dissolve into the deep dynamics of genuine full quantum dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08606v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kazuo Takatsuka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Controlling the spontaneous emission of trapped ions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08627</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08627v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose an experimental setup for manipulating the spontaneous emission of trapped ions, based on a spatial light modulator. Anticipated novelties include the potential to entangle more than two ions through a single photon detection event and control the visibility for spatially distinguishable emitters. The setup can be adapted to most of the existing ion traps commonly used in quantum technology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08627v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tommaso Faorlin, Benjamin Yadin, Yannick Weiser, Gabriel Araneda, Stefan Nimmrichter, Lorenz Panzl, Thomas Lafenthaler, Rainer Blatt, Thomas Monz, Giovanni Cerchiari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Recurrence in discrete-time quantum stochastic walks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08674</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08674v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Interplay between quantum interference and classical randomness can enhance performance of various quantum information tasks. In the present paper we analyze recurrence phenomena in the discrete-time quantum stochastic walk on a line, which is a quantum stochastic process that interpolates between quantum and classical walk dynamics. Surprisingly, we find that introducing classical randomness can reduce the recurrence probability -- despite the fact that the classical random walk returns with certainty -- and we identify the conditions under which this intriguing phenomenon occurs. Numerical evaluation of the first-return generating function allows us to investigate the asymptotics of the return probability as the step number approaches infinity. This provides strong evidence that the suppression of recurrence probability is not a transient effect but a robust feature of the underlying quantum-classical interplay in the asymptotic limit. Our results show that for certain tasks discrete-time quantum stochastic walks outperform both classical random walks and unitary quantum walks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08674v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Martin Stefanak, Vaclav Potocek, Iskender Yalcinkaya, Aurel Gabris, Igor Jex</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Floquet controlled-phase gates in Rydberg atoms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08773</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08773v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Rydberg atoms stand out as a highly promising platform for realizing quantum computation with significant advantages in constructing high-fidelity quantum gates. Floquet frequency modulation (FFM) is a potent approach for achieving resilient quantum gates through the manipulation of modulation parameters, thereby inducing intricate dynamics within quantum systems. This work introduces a method to realize controlled arbitrary phase gates in Rydberg atoms by manipulating system dynamics by the means of FFM. Notably, this method eliminates the need for laser addressing, significantly enhancing the convenience for future practical applications. Furthermore, this approach can be integrated with soft quantum control strategies to enhance the fidelity and robustness of the resultant controlled-phase gates. Finally, this methodology is applied in Grover's quantum search algorithms to prepare quantum states, demonstrating its substantial significance for future quantum information processing applications. This work leveraging Rydberg atoms and Floquet frequency modulation may herald a new era of scalable and reliable quantum computing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08773v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jun Wu, Jin-Lei Wu, Fu-Qiang Guo, Bing-Bing Liu, Shi-Lei Su, Xue-Ke Song, Liu Ye, Dong Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Securities Transaction Settlement Optimization on superconducting quantum devices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08794</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08794v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We describe a quantum variational algorithm for securities transactions settlement optimization, based on a novel mathematical formalization of the problem that includes the most relevant constraints considered in the pan-European securities settlement platform TARGET2-Securities. The proposed algorithm is designed for Noisy Intermediate-Scale Quantum devices, specifically targeting IBM's superconducting qubit machines. We adopt non-linear activation functions to encode inequality constraints in the objective function of the problem, and design customized noise mitigation techniques to alleviate the effect of readout errors. We consider batches of up to 40 trades obtained from real transactional data to benchmark our algorithm on quantum hardware against classical and quantum-inspired solvers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08794v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francesco Martini, Daniele Lizzio Bosco, Carlo Barbanera, Serena Bernardini, Giacomo Ranieri, Francesca Cibrario, Davide Corbelletto, Giuseppe Bruno, Alessandra Di Pierro, Luca Dellantonio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient wireless charging of a quantum battery</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08843</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08843v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We explore the wireless charging of a quantum battery (QB) via $n$ charging units, whose coupling is mediated by a common bosonic reservoir. We consider the general scenarios in which the charger energy is not maximal and the QB has residual ergotropy initially. It is found that the charging performance improves with the increase of the coupling strength. In the strong coupling regime, the charging time is insensitive to the charger energy, the number of charging units, and the residual ergotropy in the QB, while the ergotropy charged on the QB strongly depends on the charger energy and ergotropy, and the residual ergotropy in the QB does not help to enhance its performance. Moreover, the multiple charging units help to enhance the charging performance in the weak and moderate coupling regimes, while they are less efficient in the strong coupling regime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08843v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ming-Liang Hu, Ting Gao, Heng Fan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Information geometry of transitions between quantum nonequilibrium steady states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08858</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08858v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In a transition between nonequilibrium steady states, the entropic cost associated with the maintenance of steady-state currents can be distinguished from that arising from the transition itself through the concepts of excess/housekeeping entropy flux and adiabatic/nonadiabatic entropy production. The thermodynamics of this transition is embodied by the Hatano-Sasa relation. In this letter, we show that for a slow transition between quantum nonequilibrium steady states the nonadiabatic entropy production is, to leading order, given by the path action with respect to a Riemannian metric in the parameter space which can be connected to the Kubo-Mori-Bogoliubov quantum Fisher information. We then demonstrate how to obtain minimally dissipative paths by solving the associated geodesic equation and illustrate the procedure with a simple example of a three-level maser. Furthermore, by identifying the quantum Fisher information with respect to time as a metric in state space, we derive an upper bound on the excess entropy flux that holds for arbitrarily fast processes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08858v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Artur M. Lacerda, Laetitia P. Bettmann, John Goold</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Time-bin encoding quantum key distribution in free-space horizontal links during nighttime and daytime</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08891</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08891v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Free-space quantum key distribution (QKD) represents a groundbreaking advancement in secure communication, enabling secure key exchange over vast distances and offering robust encryption for the future quantum internet. However, the compatibility between fiber and free-space infrastructures continues to pose challenges for QKD protocols. Indeed, free-space and fiber-based networks commonly use different wavelengths and qubits encoding schemes. On the one hand, free-space QKD typically exploits visible light for its beneficial beam divergence compared to longer wavelengths, and polarization encoding for its robustness against turbulence. On the other hand, fiber-based QKD employs infrared light, particularly the C-band, because it shows the minimum losses with silica fibers, and time-bin encoding, due to polarization instability in optical fibers. In our study, we demonstrate the viability of a time-bin encoded QKD protocol operating in the C-band through horizontal turbulent free-space channels. We test the setup into a 50 m and a 500 m long links, achieving an average secure key rate of, respectively, 793 kbps and 40 kbps over several hours of measurements. The results encourage further exploration of the interoperability between free-space and fiber-based infrastructures, opening new possibilities for connecting terminal users with satellites in hybrid infrastructures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08891v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sebastiano Cocchi, Domenico Ribezzo, Giulia Guarda, Pietro Centorrino, Tommaso Occhipinti, Alessandro Zavatta, Davide Bacco</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Photon-Number Conserved Universal Quantum Logic Employing Continuous-Time Quantum Walk on Dual-Rail Qubit Arrays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08904</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08904v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We demonstrate a synergy between dual-rail qubit encoding and continuous-time quantum walks (CTQW) to realize universal quantum logic in superconducting circuits. Utilizing the photon-number-conserving dynamics of CTQW on dual-rail transmons, which systematically transform leakage and relaxation into erasure events, our architecture facilitates the suppression of population leakage and the implementation of high-fidelity quantum gates. We construct single-, two-, and three-qubit operations that preserve dual-rail encoding, facilitated by tunable coupler strengths compatible with current superconducting qubit platforms. Numerical simulations confirm robust behavior against dephasing, relaxation, and imperfections in coupling, underscoring the erasure-friendly nature of the system. This hardware-efficient scheme thus provides a practical pathway to early fault-tolerant quantum computation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08904v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hao-Yu Guan, Yifei Li, Xiu-Hao Deng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Experimental distributed quantum sensing in a noisy environment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08940</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08940v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The precision advantages offered by harnessing the quantum states of sensors can be readily compromised by noise. However, when the noise has a different spatial function than the signal of interest, recent theoretical work shows how the advantage can be maintained and even significantly improved. In this work we experimentally demonstrate the associated sensing protocol, using trapped-ion sensors. An entangled state of multi-dimensional sensors is created that isolates and optimally detects a signal, whilst being insensitive to otherwise overwhelming noise fields with different spatial profiles over the sensor locations. The quantum protocol is found to outperform a perfect implementation of the best comparable strategy without sensor entanglement. While our demonstration is carried out for magnetic and electromagnetic fields over a few microns, the technique is readily applicable over arbitrary distances and for arbitrary fields, thus present a promising application for emerging quantum sensor networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08940v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>James Bate, Arne Hamann, Marco Canteri, Armin Winkler, Zhe Xian Koong, Victor Krutyanskiy, Wolfgang D\"ur, Benjamin Peter Lanyon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improved bounds on collapse models from rotational noise of LISA Pathfinder</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08971</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08971v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Spontaneous wavefunction collapse models offer a solution to the quantum measurement problem, by modifying the Schr\"odinger equation with nonlinear and stochastic terms. The Continuous Spontaneous Localisation (CSL) model is the most studied among these models, with phenomenological parameters that are constrained by experiments. Here, we exploit the recent analysis of LISA Pathfinder's angular motion data to derive a tighter constraint than previously achieved with translational motion. Moreover, we identify the general conditions for preferring rotational measurement over translational ones for constraining the CSL model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08971v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Davide Giordano Ario Altamura, Andrea Vinante, Matteo Carlesso</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Balanced cross-Kerr coupling for superconducting qubit readout</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09010</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09010v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Dispersive readout, the standard method for measuring superconducting qubits, is limited by multiphoton qubit-resonator processes arising even at moderate drive powers. These processes degrade performance, causing dispersive readout to lag behind single- and two-qubit gates in both speed and fidelity. In this work, we propose a novel readout method, termed "junction readout". Junction readout leverages the nonperturbative cross-Kerr interaction resulting from coupling a qubit and a resonator via a Josephson junction. Furthermore, by adding a capacitive coupling in parallel to the junction, Purcell decay can be suppressed without the need for a Purcell filter. We also show that junction readout is more robust against deleterious multiphoton processes, and offers greater flexibility for resonator frequency allocation. Crucially, junction readout achieves superior performance compared to dispersive readout while maintaining similar hardware overhead. Numerical simulations show that junction readout can achieve fidelities exceeding $99.99\%$ in under $30$ ns, making it a promising alternative for superconducting qubit readout with current hardware.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09010v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alex A. Chapple, Othmane Benhayoune-Khadraoui, Simon Richer, Alexandre Blais</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Investigating Parameter-Efficiency of Hybrid QuGANs Based on Geometric Properties of Generated Sea Route Graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08678</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08678v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The demand for artificially generated data for the development, training and testing of new algorithms is omnipresent. Quantum computing (QC), does offer the hope that its inherent probabilistic functionality can be utilised in this field of generative artificial intelligence. In this study, we use quantum-classical hybrid generative adversarial networks (QuGANs) to artificially generate graphs of shipping routes. We create a training dataset based on real shipping data and investigate to what extent QuGANs are able to learn and reproduce inherent distributions and geometric features of this data. We compare hybrid QuGANs with classical Generative Adversarial Networks (GANs), with a special focus on their parameter efficiency. Our results indicate that QuGANs are indeed able to quickly learn and represent underlying geometric properties and distributions, although they seem to have difficulties in introducing variance into the sampled data. Compared to classical GANs of greater size, measured in the number of parameters used, some QuGANs show similar result quality. Our reference to concrete use cases, such as the generation of shipping data, provides an illustrative example and demonstrate the potential and diversity in which QC can be used.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08678v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tobias Rohe, Florian Burger, Michael K\"olle, Sebastian W\"olckert, Maximilian Zorn, Claudia Linnhoff-Popien</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
