<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>quant-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/quant-ph</link>
    <description>quant-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/quant-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 05:00:02 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Refinement of Uncertainty Relations in Quantum Mechanics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17165</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17165v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The uncertainty relation of three quantities in quantum mechanics is estimated in terms of commutators. The Pauli matrices are used to find a contribution of third-order commutators. The resulting inequality refines the Heisenberg indeterminacy for two non-conjugate operators when their commutator is not a c-number. The inequality is applied to operators of the kinetic energy and coordinate of one-dimensional system. In addition, uncertainty of the angular momentum components is considered.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17165v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/BF00945688</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Russian Phys.J.,19:3,pp.340-343 (1976) (in Russian)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Sergei P. Efimov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning Orthogonal Random Unitary Channels with Contracted Quantum Approaches and Simplex Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17243</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17243v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Random (mixed) unitary channels describe an important subset of quantum channels, which are commonly used in quantum information, noise modeling, and quantum error mitigation. Despite their usefulness, there is substantial complexity in characterizing or identifying generic random unitary channels. We present a procedure for learning a class of random unitary channels on orthogonal unitary bases on a quantum computer utilizing Pauli learning and a contracted quantum learning procedure. Our approach involves a multi-objective, Pauli- and unitary-based minimization, and allows for learning locally equivalent channels. We demonstrate our approach for varying degrees of noise and investigate the scalability of these approaches, particularly with sparse noise models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17243v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Scott E. Smart, Alexander J\"urgens, Joseph Peetz, Prineha Narang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient compilation of quantum circuits using multi-qubit gates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17246</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17246v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: As quantum processors grow in scale and reliability, the need for efficient quantum gate decomposition of circuits to a set of specific available gates, becomes ever more critical. The decomposition of a particular algorithm into a sequence of these available gates is not unique. Thus, the fidelity of an algorithm's implementation can be increased by choosing an optimized decomposition. This is true both for noisy intermediate-scale quantum platforms as well as for implementation of quantum error correction schemes. Here we present a compilation scheme which implements a general-circuit decomposition to a sequence of Ising-type, long-range, multi-qubit entangling gates, that are separated by layers of single qubit rotations. We use trapped ions as an example in which multi-qubit gates naturally arise, yet any system that has connectivity beyond nearest-neighbors may gain from our approach. We evaluate our methods using the quantum volume test over $N$ qubits. In this context, our method replaces $3N^2/2$ two-qubit gates with $2N+1$ multi-qubit gates. Furthermore, our method minimizes the magnitude of the entanglement phases, which typically enables an improved implementation fidelity, by using weaker driving fields or faster realizations. We numerically test our compilation and show that, compared to conventional realizations with sequential two-qubit gates, our compilations improves the logarithm of quantum volume by $20\%$ to $25\%$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17246v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonathan Nemirovsky, Maya Chuchem, Yotam Shapira</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discrimination of arbitrary unknown quantum channels and measurements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17317</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17317v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work we provide an efficiency analysis of the problem of discrimination of two randomly chosen unknown quantum operations in the single-shot regime. We provide tight bounds for the success probability of such a protocol for arbitrary quantum channels and generalized measurements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17317v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marcin Markiewicz, {\L}ukasz Pawela, Zbigniew Pucha{\l}a</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unorthodox parallelization for Bayesian quantum state estimation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17334</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17334v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum state tomography (QST) allows for the reconstruction of quantum states through measurements and some inference technique under the assumption of repeated state preparations. Bayesian inference provides a promising platform to achieve both efficient QST and accurate uncertainty quantification, yet is generally plagued by the computational limitations associated with long Markov chains. In this work, we present a novel Bayesian QST approach that leverages modern distributed parallel computer architectures to efficiently sample a $D$-dimensional Hilbert space. Using a parallelized preconditioned Crank--Nicholson Metropolis-Hastings algorithm, we demonstrate our approach on simulated data and experimental results from IBM Quantum systems up to four qubits, showing significant speedups through parallelization. Although highly unorthodox in pooling independent Markov chains, our method proves remarkably practical, with validation ex post facto via diagnostics like the intrachain autocorrelation time. We conclude by discussing scalability to higher-dimensional systems, offering a path toward efficient and accurate Bayesian characterization of large quantum systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17334v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hanson H. Nguyen, Kody J. H. Law, Joseph M. Lukens</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Time dispersion in bound states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17407</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17407v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In quantum mechanics time is generally treated as a parameter rather than an observable. For instance wave functions are treated as extending in space, but not in time. But from relativity we expect time and space should be treated on the same basis. What are the effects if time is an observable? Are these effects observable with current technology?
  In earlier work we showed we should see effects in various high energy scattering processes. We here extend that work to include bound states. The critical advantage of working with bound states is that the predictions are significantly more definite, taking the predictions from testable to falsifiable.
  We estimate the time dispersion for hydrogen as $.177$ attoseconds, possibly below the current threshold for detection. But the time dispersion should scale as the $3/2$ power of the principle quantum number $n$. Rydberg atoms can have $n$ of order $100$, implying a boost by a factor of $1000$. This takes the the time dispersion to $177$ attoseconds, well within reach of current technology.
  There are a wide variety of experimental targets: any time-dependent processes should show effects. Falsification will be technically challenging (due to the short time scales) but immediate and unambiguous. Confirmation would have significant implications for attosecond physics, quantum computing and communications, quantum gravity, and the measurement problem. And would suggest practical uses in these areas as well as circuit design, high speed biochemistry, cryptography, fusion research, and any area involving change at attosecond time scales.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17407v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>John Ashmead</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Trade-off in Quantum Metrology: Excessive Precision Compromise Accuracy even with Unlimited Resources</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17427</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17427v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Precision and accuracy, as two crucial criteria for quantum metrology, have previously lacked rigorous definitions and distinctions. In this paper, we provide a unified definition of precision and accuracy from the perspective of distinguishing neighboring quantum states. Using the quantum Cram\'er-Rao bound as a lower bound for precision, we find that the corresponding accuracy will fall short of expectations, because the bias of the parameter estimation cannot be ignored. Given that probability estimation is unbiased, defining precision from the perspective of probability distributions provides a more comprehensive approach. This leads to a correction of the traditional precision lower bound by a factor of 2. The trade-off between precision and accuracy shows that precision can be further improved by sacrificing accuracy, while it should be restricted by inherent precision limit. The inherent precision limit, determined by the number of sampling, can reach the Heisenberg scaling even without entanglement resources, which, however, comes at the cost of significantly reduced accuracy. We show that accuracy may actually decrease with increasing sampling when one pursues excessive precision, which indicates the trade-off should be considered even with unlimited resources.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17427v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cong-Gang Song, Qing-yu Cai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The quantromon: A qubit-resonator system with orthogonal qubit and readout modes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17439</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17439v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The measurement of a superconducting qubit is implemented by coupling it to a resonator. The common choice is transverse coupling, which, in the dispersive approximation, introduces an interaction term which enables the measurement. This cross-Kerr term provides a qubit-state dependent dispersive shift in the resonator frequency with the device parameters chosen carefully to get sufficient signal while minimizing Purcell decay of the qubit. We introduce a two-mode circuit, nicknamed quantromon, with two orthogonal modes implementing a qubit and a resonator. Unlike before, where the coupling term emerges as a perturbative expansion, the quantromon has intrinsic cross-Kerr coupling by design. Our experiments implemented in a hybrid 2D-3D cQED architecture demonstrate some unique features of the quantromon like weak dependence of the dispersive shift on the qubit-resonator detuning and intrinsic Purcell protection. In a tunable qubit-frequency device, we show that the dispersive shift ($2\chi/2\pi$) changes by only $0.8$ MHz while the qubit-resonator detuning ($\Delta/2\pi$) is varied between $0.398$ GHz - $3.288$ GHz. We also demonstrate Purcell protection in a second device where we tune the orthogonality between the two modes. Finally, we demonstrate a single-shot readout fidelity of $98.3\%$ without using a parametric amplifier which is comparable to the state-of-the-art and suggests a potential simplification of the measurement circuitry for scaling up quantum processors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17439v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kishor V. Salunkhe, Suman Kundu, Srijita Das, Jay Deshmukh, Meghan P. Patankar, R. Vijay</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Small Binary Stabilizer Subsystem Codes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17447</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17447v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We establish a database consisting of a representative of every binary quantum stabilizer code under local Clifford permutation equivalence for $n\leq 9$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17447v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrew Cross, Drew Vandeth</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What are the bearers of hidden states? On an important ambiguity in the formulation of Bell's theorem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17521</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17521v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Bell's conclusion from his famous inequality was that any hidden variable theory that satisfies Local Causality is incompatible with the predictions of Quantum Mechanics (QM) for Bell's Experiment. However, Local Causality does not appear in the derivation of Bell's inequality. Instead, two other assumptions are used, namely Factorizability and Settings Independence. Therefore, in order to establish Bell's conclusion, we need to relate these two assumptions to Local Causality. The prospects for doing so turn out to depend on the assumed location of the hidden states that appear in Bell's inequality. In this paper, I consider the following two views on such states: (1) that they are states of the two-particle system at the moment of preparation, and (2) that they are states of thick slices of the past light cones of measurements. I argue that straightforward attempts to establish Bell's conclusion fail in both approaches. Then, I consider three refined attempts, which I also criticise, and I propose a new way of establishing Bell's conclusion that combines intuitions underlying several previous approaches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17521v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joanna Luc</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Study the charging performance of frequency modulated quantum batteries inside a dissipative cavity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17526</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17526v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the charging dynamics of a frequency-modulated quantum battery (QB) placed within a dissipative cavity environment. Our study focuses on the interaction of such a battery under both weak and strong coupling regimes, employing a model in which the quantum battery and charger are represented as frequency-modulated qubits indirectly coupled through a zero-temperature environment. It is demonstrated that both the modulation frequency and amplitude are crucial for optimizing the charging process and the ergotropy of the quantum battery. Specifically, high-amplitude, low-frequency modulation significantly enhances charging performance and work extraction in the strong coupling regime. As an intriguing result, it is deduced that modulation at very low frequencies leads to the emergence of energy storage and work extraction in the weak coupling regime. Such a result can never be achieved without modulation in the weak coupling regime. These results highlight the importance of adjusting modulation parameters to optimize the performance of quantum batteries for real-world applications in quantum technologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17526v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maryam Hadipour, Negar Nikdel Yousefi, Ali Mortezapour, Amir Sharifi Miavaghi, Soroush Haseli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimum Efficiency of an Asymmetric Quantum Harmonic Otto Engine</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17592</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17592v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study a quantum Otto engine operating with a time-dependent harmonic oscillator as its working material. We consider asymmetry between the two adiabatic processes of the Otto cycle, based on which we explore sudden expansion and sudden compression cases. We find the optimal performance of this asymmetric Otto engine under the Omega function, which represents the balance between the utilized energy and the dissipated energy of an engine. We analyze that for sudden compression stroke, the efficiency approaches unity, while it is only one-half for sudden expansion stroke. Additionally, we notice that the efficiency at the maximum Omega function consistently exceeds the maximum work efficiency in both cases. Further, we present a comparative analysis of symmetric and asymmetric Otto engines for the well-known Omega function. Then, we move our study to calculate the fractional loss of work for both the aforementioned cases. Finally, we find results for the ratio of maximum work and work under maximum Omega function. We show that the work at maximum Omega function produces 98.19\% of maximum work for both sudden compression and sudden expansion strokes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17592v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> Monika, Shishram Rebari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exponential advantage in continuous-variable quantum state learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17633</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17633v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider the task of learning quantum states in bosonic continuous-variable (CV) systems. We present a concrete experimentally feasible protocol that utilizes entangled measurements and reflected states to enable efficient learning of the characteristic function of CV quantum states with a sample complexity independent of the number of modes $n$. We then prove that any general adaptive learning scheme without entangled measurements requires a sample complexity that is exponential in $n$ to accomplish the same task, demonstrating an exponential advantage provided by entangled measurements. Remarkably, we also prove that any general adaptive entanglement-assisted scheme also requires an exponential sample complexity if access to reflected states is prohibited. Hence, we establish a rigorous exponential advantage from entangled measurements and access to reflected states in learning CV quantum states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17633v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eugen Coroi, Changhun Oh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entropic witness for quantum memory in open system dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17660</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17660v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The dynamics of open quantum system are often modeled by non-Markovian processes that account for memory effects arising from interactions with the environment. It is well-known that the memory provided by the environment can be classical or quantum in nature. Remarkably, the quantumness of the memory can be witnessed locally by measurements on the open system alone, without requiring access to the environment. However, existing witnesses are computationally challenging for systems beyond qubits. In this work, we present a tractable criterion for quantum memory based on the von Neumann entropy, which is easily computable for systems of any dimension. Using this witness, we investigate the nature of memory in a class of physically motivated finite-dimensional qudit dynamics. Moreover, we demonstrate that this criterion is also suitable for detecting quantum memory in continuous-variable systems. As an illustrative example, we analyze non-Markovian Gaussian dynamics of a damped harmonic oscillator.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17660v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Charlotte B\"acker, Konstantin Beyer, Walter T. Strunz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Machine-Learning-Enhanced Optimization of Noise-Resilient Variational Quantum Eigensolvers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17689</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17689v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Variational Quantum Eigensolvers (VQEs) are a powerful class of hybrid quantum-classical algorithms designed to approximate the ground state of a quantum system described by its Hamiltonian. VQEs hold promise for various applications, including lattice field theory. However, the inherent noise of Noisy Intermediate-Scale Quantum (NISQ) devices poses a significant challenge for running VQEs as these algorithms are particularly susceptible to noise, e.g., measurement shot noise and hardware noise.
  In a recent work, it was proposed to enhance the classical optimization of VQEs with Gaussian Processes (GPs) and Bayesian Optimization, as these machine-learning techniques are well-suited for handling noisy data. In these proceedings, we provide additional insights into this new algorithm and present further numerical experiments. In particular, we examine the impact of hardware noise and error mitigation on the algorithm's performance. We validate the algorithm using classical simulations of quantum hardware, including hardware noise benchmarks, which have not been considered in previous works. Our numerical experiments demonstrate that GP-enhanced algorithms can outperform state-of-the-art baselines, laying the foundation for future research on deploying these techniques to real quantum hardware and lattice field theory setups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17689v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kim A. Nicoli, Luca J. Wagner, Lena Funcke</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fidelity-Enhanced Variational Quantum Optimal Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17692</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17692v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Creating robust quantum operations is a major challenge in the current noisy intermediate-scale quantum computing era. Recently, the importance of noise-resilient control methods has become more pronounced in the field. Ordinarily, noisy quantum systems are described by the Lindblad equation. However, minimizing noise susceptibility using this equation has proven challenging because of its irreversibility. In this study, we propose a new method for creating robust pulses based on the stochastic Schr\"{o}dinger equation. This equation describes individual noise realizations under any colored noise process, contrary to the Lindblad equation, which describes mean system behavior under white noise. Using stochastic optimal control techniques, our method, Fidelity-Enhanced Variational Quantum Optimal Control (F-VQOC), is able to construct higher fidelity paths than its non-stochastic counterpart (VQOC). By accounting for both environmental noise sources as well as noise sources inherent to the control system, highly significant increases in fidelity are noted for both single and multiqubit state preparations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17692v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Robert de Keijzer, Luke Visser, Oliver Tse, Servaas Kokkelmans</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The ultimate bounds to precision of atomic clock frequency measurement techniques</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17693</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17693v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the ultimate quantum limits to the achievable uncertainty in the estimation of the transition frequency between two atomic levels. We focus on Rabi, Ramsey, and coherent population trapping (CPT) techniques, which are widely employed in experiments. We prove that in the Rabi and Ramsey schemes measuring the atomic population allows one to reach the minimum uncertainty, but, for the CPT setup, a measurement involving the coherences between the levels results in a further improvement of the estimation. As a figure of merit, we consider the Fisher information of the population measurement and compare its value to the quantum Fisher information, corresponding to the maximum precision, optimized over all the possible feasible measurements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17693v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stefano Olivares, Salvatore Micalizio, Matteo G. A. Paris</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Winning Rates of $(n,k)$ Quantum Coset Monogamy Games</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17736</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17736v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We formulate the $(n,k)$ Coset Monogamy Game, in which two players must extract complementary information of unequal size ($k$ bits vs. $n-k$ bits) from a random coset state without communicating. The complementary information takes the form of random Pauli-X and Pauli-Z errors on subspace states. Our game generalizes those considered in previous works that deal with the case of equal information size $(k=\frac{n}{2})$. We prove a convex upper bound of the information-theoretic winning rate of the $(n,k)$ Coset Monogamy Game in terms of the subspace rate $R=\frac{k}{n}\in [0,1]$. This bound improves upon previous results for the case of $R=\frac{1}{2}$. We also prove the achievability of an optimal winning probability upper bound for the class of unentangled strategies of the $(n,k)$ Coset Monogamy Game.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17736v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael Schleppy, Emina Soljanin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Readout-induced leakage of the fluxonium qubit</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17807</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17807v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Dispersive readout is widely used to perform high-fidelity measurement of superconducting qubits. Much work has been focused on the qubit readout fidelity, which depends on the achievable signal-to-noise ratio and the qubit relaxation time. As groups have pushed to increase readout fidelity by increasing readout photon number, dispersive readout has been shown to strongly affect the post-measurement qubit state. Such effects hinder the effectiveness of quantum error correction, which requires measurements that both have high readout fidelity and are quantum non-demolition (QND). Here, we experimentally investigate non-QND effects in the fluxonium. We map out the state evolution of fluxonium qubits in the presence of resonator photons and observe that these photons induce transitions in the fluxonium both within and outside the qubit subspace. We numerically model our system and find that coupling the fluxonium-resonator system to an external spurious mode is necessary to explain observed non-QND effects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17807v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aayam Bista, Matthew Thibodeau, Ke Nie, Kaicheung Chow, Bryan K. Clark, Angela Kou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimizing Superconducting Qubit Performance: A Theoretical Framework for Design, Analysis, and Calibration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17825</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17825v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Designing a qubit architecture is one of the most critical challenges in achieving scalable and fault-tolerant quantum computing as the performance of a quantum computer is heavily dependent on the coherence times, connectivity and low noise environments. Superconducting qubits have emerged as a frontrunner among many competing technologies, primarily because of their speed of operations, relatively well-developed and offer a promising path toward scalability. Here, we address the challenges of optimizing superconducting qubit hardware through the development of a comprehensive theoretical framework that spans the entire process - from design to the calibration of hardware through quantum gate execution. We develop this framework in four key steps: circuit design, electromagnetic analysis, spectral analysis, and pulse sequencing with calibration. We first refine the qubit's core components - such as capacitance, Josephson junctions, and resonators - to set the foundation for strong performance. The electromagnetic analysis, using the Lumped Oscillator model, allows us to map out the capacitance matrix, ensuring that we minimize spectral dispersion while maximizing coherence times. Following this, we conduct spectral analysis to fine-tune the qubit's frequency spectrum and coherence properties, ensuring that the qubit parameters are optimized. Finally, we focus on pulse sequencing, including pulse-width optimization, DRAG optimization, and randomized benchmarking, to achieve high gate fidelity. We applied this framework to both Transmon and Fluxonium qubits, obtaining results that closely match those found in experimental studies. This work provides a detailed and practical approach to the design, optimization, and calibration of superconducting qubits, contributing to the broader effort to develop scalable quantum computing technologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17825v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sirshi S Ram, Muralikrishna Molli, Vamshi Mohan Katukuri, Bharadwaj Chowdary Mummaneni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distinguishing Ordered Phases using Machine Learning and Classical Shadows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17837</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17837v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Classifying phase transitions is a fundamental and complex challenge in condensed matter physics. This work proposes a framework for identifying quantum phase transitions by combining classical shadows with unsupervised machine learning. We use the axial next-nearest neighbor Ising model as our benchmark and extend the analysis to the Kitaev-Heisenberg model on a two-leg ladder. Even with few qubits, we can effectively distinguish between the different phases of the Hamiltonian models. Moreover, given that we only rely on two-point correlator functions, the classical shadows protocol enables the cost of the analysis to scale logarithmically with the number of qubits, making our approach a scalable and efficient way to study phase transitions in many-body systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17837v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Leandro Morais, Tiago Pernambuco, Rodrigo G. Pereira, Askery Canabarro, Diogo O. Soares-Pinto, Rafael Chaves</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
