<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>quant-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/quant-ph</link>
    <description>quant-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/quant-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2025 05:00:08 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Frequency conversion in a hydrogen-filled hollow-core fiber: power scaling, background, and bandwidth</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.04049</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.04049v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Large-area quantum networks based on optical fibers allow photons at near-infrared wavelengths to travel with minimal loss. Quantum frequency conversion is a method to alter the wavelength of a single photon while maintaining its quantum state. Most commonly, nonlinear crystals are employed for this conversion process, where near-unity conversion efficiency at high fidelity has been demonstrated. Still, the crystal-based conversion process is plagued by strong background noise, very limited spectral bandwidth, and inhomogeneous temperature profiles at strong pump fields.
  In previous work, we have demonstrated frequency conversion in hydrogen-filled hollow-core fibers and claimed that this conversion process does not compromise performance at strong pump fields, is essentially free of background noise, and intrinsically broadband. Here, we demonstrate that these three claims are justified.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.04049v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anica Hamer, Frank Vewinger, Michael H. Frosz, Simon Stellmer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase space analysis of Bell inequalities for mixed Gaussian states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.04078</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.04078v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a phase space formalism to evaluate Bell inequality violations in continuous variable systems. By doing so we can generalize previous analyses (which have dealt only with pure states) to arbitrary mixed states. We leverage these results to analyze the effect of temperature on violations of Bell inequalities in a two-mode squeezed thermal state, which can become useful in tests of local realism in the presence of thermal noise. We also explore the non-monotonic relationship between the violations of Bell inequalities and the amount of entanglement present in this family of mixed states. Additionally, we discuss the optimal choices of pseudospin operators for states beyond the two-mode squeezed vacuum.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.04078v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gurpahul Singh, Kelly Wurtz, Eduardo Mart\'in-Mart\'inez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Operator Spreading in Random Unitary Circuits with Unitary-invariant Gate Distributions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.04091</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.04091v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Random unitary circuits have become a model system to investigate information scrambling in quantum systems. In the literature, mostly random circuits with Haar-distributed gate operations have been considered. In this work, we investigate operator spreading in random unitary circuits in which the elementary gate operations are drawn from general unitary-invariant ensembles, which include the well-studied Haar-distributed random unitary circuits as a special case. Similar to the Haar-distributed case, the long-time behavior of operator spreading with the more general unitary-invariant gate distribution is governed by drift-diffusion equations characterized by the butterfly velocity $v_{\rm B}$ and a diffusion constant $\mathcal{D}$. Differences with the Haar-random case are (i) that it takes a finite time $\tau_{\rm b}$ until ensemble-averaged Pauli-string weights take a ``binary'' form, in which they depend only on whether Pauli operators inside the support of the Pauli strong are equal to the identity matrix, and (ii) that the operator spreading is characterized by a finite ``domain-wall width'' $n_{\rm DW}$ separating regions with a random-matrix-like Pauli-string distribution. To illustrate these findings, we perform explicit calculations for random unitary circuits distributed according to the Poisson kernel, which interpolates between the trivial and Haar-distributed circuits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.04091v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhiyang Tan, Piet W. Brouwer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Heralded entanglement of on-demand spin-wave solid-state quantum memories for multiplexed quantum network links</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.04131</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.04131v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The ability to distribute heralded entanglement between distant matter nodes is a primitive for the implementation of large-scale quantum networks. Some of the most crucial requirements for future applications include high heralding rates at telecom wavelengths, multiplexed operation and on-demand retrieval of stored excitations for synchronization of separate quantum links. Despite tremendous progress in various physical systems, the demonstration of telecom-heralded entanglement between quantum nodes featuring both multiplexed operation and on-demand retrieval remains elusive. In this work, we combine narrowband parametric photon-pair sources and solid-state quantum memories based on rare-earth doped crystals to demonstrate telecom heralded entanglement between spatially separated spin-wave quantum memories with fully adjustable recall time and temporal multiplexing of 15 modes. In a first experiment, the storage in the spin-state is conditioned on the entanglement heralding. We take advantage of the control over readout pulse phase to achieve feed-forward conditional phase-shifts on the stored photons depending on which heralding detector clicked. We exploit this effect to double the entanglement heralding rate for a given quantum state up to \SI{500}{\cps}, with a measured positive concurrence by up to 6 standard deviations. In a second experiment, we simulate the communication time of a long-distance link by implementing an unconditional storage scheme with a dead-time of \SI{100}{\micro\second}, leading to an entanglement rate of \SI{22}{\cps} per heralding detector, increased by a factor of 15 thanks to temporal multiplexing. These results establish our architecture as a prime candidate for the implementation of scalable high-rate quantum network links.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.04131v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonathan H\"anni, Alberto E. Rodr\'iguez-Moldes, F\'elicien Appas, Soeren Wengerowsky, Dario Lago-Rivera, Markus Teller, Samuele Grandi, Hugues de Riedmatten</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum entanglement as an extremal Kirkwood-Dirac nonreality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.04137</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.04137v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Understanding the relationship between various different forms of nonclassicality and their resource character is of great importance in quantum foundation and quantum information. Here, we discuss a quantitative link between quantum entanglement and the anomalous/nonclassical nonreal values of Kirkwood-Dirac (KD) quasiprobability, in a bipartite setting. We first construct an entanglement monotone for a pure bipartite state based on the nonreality of the KD quasiprobability defined over a pair of orthonormal bases in which one of them is a product, and optimizations over these bases. It admits a closed expression as a Schur-concave function of the state of the subsystem having a form of nonadditive quantum entropy. We then construct a bipartite entanglement monotone for generic quantum states using the convex roof extension. Its normalized value is upper bounded by the concurrence of formation, and for two-qubit systems, they are equal. We also derive lower and upper bounds in terms of different forms of uncertainty in the subsystem quantified respectively by an extremal trace-norm asymmetry and a nonadditive quantum entropy. The entanglement monotone can be expressed as the minimum total state disturbance due to a nonselective local binary measurement. Finally, we discuss its estimation using weak value measurement and classical optimization, and its connection with strange weak value and quantum contextuality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.04137v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Agung Budiyono</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Benchmarking TCL4: Assessing the Usability and Reliability of Fourth-Order Approximations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.04192</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.04192v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The non-Markovian dynamics of an open quantum system can be rigorously derived using the Feynman-Vernon influence functional approach. Although this formalism is exact, practical numerical implementations often require compromises. The time-convolutionless (TCL) master equation offers an exact framework, yet its application typically relies on a perturbative expansion of both the time forward and time backward state propagators. Due to the significant computational effort involved - and the scarcity of analytical solutions for most open quantum systems - the fourth-order perturbative TCL generator (TCL4) has only been benchmarked on a limited range of systems and parameter spaces. Recent advancements, however, have made the computation of TCL4 faster and more accessible. In this paper, we benchmark the TCL4 master equation against numerically exact methods for the biased spin-boson model. We focus on the regime near critical bath coupling where perturbative master equations are expected to become inaccurate. Our findings reveal that the TCL4 approach is most reliable at low temperature and more efficient than the numerical exact methods. This study aims to delineate the conditions under which the TCL4 perturbative master equation enhances the accuracy of the TCL2.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.04192v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiahao Chen, Elyana Crowder, Lian Xiang, Dragomir Davidovic</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neutral Atoms in Optical Tweezers as Messenger Qubits for Scaling up a Trapped Ion Quantum Computer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.04223</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.04223v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose to combine neutral atom and trapped ion qubits in one scalable modular architecture that uses shuttling of individual neutral atoms in optical tweezers to realize atomic interconnects between trapped ion quantum registers. These interconnects are deterministic, and thus may be performed on-demand. The proposed protocol is as follows: a tweezer-trapped neutral atom qubit is brought close to a trapped ion in an ion chain serving as a module of a larger quantum computer, and an entangling gate is performed between the two qubits. Then the neutral atom is quickly moved to another, nearby trapped ion chain in the same modular ion trap and entangled with an ion in that chain, thus entangling the two separate ion chains. The optical dipole potential of the tweezer beam for the neutral atom does not measurably affect the trapped ions, while the RF ion trap does not affect the neutral atom. With realistic tweezer trap parameters, the neutral atom can be moved over millimeter scale distance in a few tens of microseconds, thus enabling a remote entanglement generation rate of over 10^3/s even with very modest assumptions for the atom-ion quantum gate speed, and possibly up to 10^4/s, which is two orders of magnitude higher than the current state-of-the-art with photonic interconnects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.04223v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Svetlana Kotochigova, Subhadeep Gupta, Boris Blinov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Characterizing the Burst Error Correction Ability of Quantum Cyclic Codes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.04310</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.04310v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum burst error correction codes (QBECCs) are of great importance to deal with the memory effect in quantum channels. As the most important family of QBECCs, quantum cyclic codes (QCCs) play a vital role in the correction of burst errors. In this work, we characterize the burst error correction ability of QCCs constructed from the Calderbank-Shor-Steane (CSS) and the Hermitian constructions. We determine the burst error correction limit of QCCs and quantum Reed-Solomon codes with algorithms in polynomial-time complexities. As a result, lots of QBECCs saturating the quantum Reiger bound are obtained. We show that quantum Reed-Solomon codes have better burst error correction abilities than the previous results. At last, we give the quantum error-trapping decoder (QETD) of QCCs for decoding burst errors. The decoder runs in linear time and can decode both degenerate and nondegenerate burst errors. What's more, the numerical results show that QETD can decode much more degenerate burst errors than the nondegenerate ones.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.04310v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jihao Fan, Min-Hsiu Hsieh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An exceptional surface and its topology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.04317</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.04317v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Non-Hermitian (NH) systems can display exceptional topological defects without Hermitian counterparts, exemplified by exceptional rings in NH two-dimensional systems. However, exceptional topological features associated with higher-dimension topological defects remain unexplored yet. We here investigate the topology for the singularities in an NH three-dimensional system. We find that the three-order singularities in the parameter space form an exceptional surface (ES), on which all the three eigenstates and eigenenergies coalesce. Such an ES corresponds to a two-dimensional extension of a point-like synthetic tensor monopole. We quantify its topology with the Dixmier-Douady invariant, which measures the quantized flux associated with the synthetic tensor field. We further propose an experimentally feasible scheme for engineering such an NH model. Our results pave the way for investigations of exceptional topology associated with topological defects with more than one dimension.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.04317v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shou-Bang Yang, Pei-Rong Han, Wen Ning, Fan Wu, Zhen-Biao Yang, Shi-Biao Zheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Machine Learning Enhanced Quantum State Tomography on FPGA</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.04327</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.04327v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Machine learning techniques have opened new avenues for real-time quantum state tomography (QST). In this work, we demonstrate the deployment of machine learning-based QST onto edge devices, specifically utilizing field programmable gate arrays (FPGAs). This implementation is realized using the {\it Vitis AI Integrated Development Environment} provided by AMD\textsuperscript \textregistered~Inc. Compared to the Graphics Processing Unit (GPU)-based machine learning QST, our FPGA-based one reduces the average inference time by an order of magnitude, from 38 ms to 2.94 ms, but only sacrifices the average fidelity about $1\% $ reduction (from 0.99 to 0.98). The FPGA-based QST offers a highly efficient and precise tool for diagnosing quantum states, marking a significant advancement in the practical applications for quantum information processing and quantum sensing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.04327v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hsun-Chung Wu, Hsien-Yi Hsieh, Zhi-Kai Xu, Hua Li Chen, Zi-Hao Shi, Po-Han Wang, Popo Yang, Ole Steuernagel, Chien-Ming Wu, Ray-Kuang Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin Goos-H{\"a}nchen Effect</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.04380</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.04380v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In wave optics, it was proposed that the reflected light wave can have a remarkable shift when the total internal reflection occurs, if a finite-width wave is incident upon a scalar potential barrier. Such a physical effect is well-known as the Goos-H{\"a}nchen (GH) effect, or the GH shift. Later on, the GH effect has been one after another generalized to non-relativistic and relativistic quantum mechanics by adopting the matter waves. In this work, based on Dirac's equation, by considering the notion of "spin" we successfully generalize the GH effect to its spin version -- the spin GH effect. We find that the direction and the magnitude of spin GH shifts for both reflected and transmitted waves depend on the spin direction and the incident angle of the incident wave. This significant physical effect has a potential application to separating Dirac's particles (i.e., the incident waves) with different spin directions. Some discussions related to the interaction between spin and electric field are made in the end.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.04380v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiang-Lin Zhou, Zou-Chen Fu, Choo Hiap Oh, Jing-Ling Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Classically Bound and Quantum Quasi-Bound States of an Electron on a Plane Adjacent to a Magnetic Monopole</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.04406</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.04406v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In three-dimensional space an electron moving in the field of a magnetic monopole has no bound states. In this paper we explore the physics when the electron is restricted to a two-dimensional plane adjacent to a magnetic monopole. We find bound states in the classical version of the problem and quasi-bound states in the quantum one, in addition to a continuum of scattering states. We calculate the lifetimes of the quasi-bound states using several complementary approximate methods, which agree well in the cases where the lifetimes are relatively short. The threshold monopole magnetic charge required to realise a single quasi-bound state is approximately $18Q_D$, where $Q_D$ is the magnetic charge of a Dirac monopole. We examine the feasibility of achieving this magnetic charge in currently available monopole analogues: spin ice, artificial spin ice, and magnetic needles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.04406v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. Martin, A. Baskerville, V. L. Campo, J. Minns, J. Pooley, S. T. Carr, C. A. Hooley, G. M\"oller, J. Quintanilla</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Experimental demonstration of entanglement pumping with bosonic logical qubits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.04460</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.04460v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Entanglement is crucial for quantum networks and computation, yet maintaining high-fidelity entangled quantum states is hindered by decoherence and resource-intensive purification methods. Here, we experimentally demonstrate entanglement pumping, utilizing bosonic quantum error correction (QEC) codes as long-coherence-time storage qubits. By repetitively generating entanglement with short-coherence-time qubits and injecting it into QEC-protected logical qubits, our approach effectively preserves entanglement. Through error detection to discard error states and entanglement pumping to mitigate errors within the code space, we extend the lifespan of entangled logical qubits by nearly 50% compared to the case without entanglement pumping. This work highlights the potential of bosonic logical qubits for scalable quantum networks and introduces a novel paradigm for efficient entanglement management.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.04460v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jie Zhou, Chuanlong Ma, Yifang Xu, Weizhou Cai, Hongwei Huang, Lida Sun, Guangming Xue, Ziyue Hua, Haifeng Yu, Weiting Wang, Chang-Ling Zou, Luyan Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-Markovian noise limits for sustaining entanglement in multiparty quantum states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.04526</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.04526v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The principal resource in several quantum information processing tasks is entanglement. Building practically useful versions of such tasks, one often needs to consider multipartite systems. And in such scenarios, it is impossible to eliminate the effects of environment while distributing the resources. We show how information back-flow from the environment, as a result of non-Markovianity in the system dynamics, affects the resources in multipartite systems, specifically multiparty entanglement. In particular, we find that entanglement of multi-qubit Greenberger-Horne-Zeilinger cat states saturate with time to a non-zero value for a non-Markovian dephasing noise. The multi-qubit W states saturate to a higher value. Such non-zero time-saturated values are washed out if the non-Markovianity in the channel is removed. The multi-qubit W states provide a richer set of features, including a non-zero value for an asymptotic number of qubits and an even-odd dichotomy in entanglement with number of qubits. Moving over to a non-Markovian depolarising channel, we find that both cat and W states exhibit revival of entanglement after collapse.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.04526v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Suchetana Goswami, Ujjwal Sen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Physics-inspired Machine Learning for Quantum Error Mitigation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.04558</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.04558v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Noise is a major obstacle in current quantum computing, and Machine Learning for Quantum Error Mitigation (ML-QEM) promises to address this challenge, enhancing computational accuracy while reducing the sampling overheads of standard QEM methods. Yet, existing models lack physical interpretability and rely heavily on extensive datasets, hindering their scalability in large-scale quantum circuits. To tackle these issues, we introduce the Neural Noise Accumulation Surrogate (NNAS), a physics-inspired neural network for ML-QEM that incorporates the structural characteristics of quantum noise accumulation within multi-layer circuits, endowing the model with physical interpretability. Experimental results demonstrate that NNAS outperforms current methods across a spectrum of metrics, including error mitigation capability, quantum resource consumption, and training dataset size. Notably, for deeper circuits where QEM methods typically struggle, NNAS achieves a remarkable reduction of over half in errors. NNAS also demands substantially fewer training data, reducing dataset reliance by at least an order of magnitude, due to its ability to rapidly capture noise accumulation patterns across circuit layers. This work pioneers the integration of quantum process-derived structural characteristics into neural network architectures, broadly enhancing QEM's performance and applicability, and establishes an integrative paradigm that extends to various quantum-inspired neural network architectures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.04558v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiao-Yue Xu, Xin Xue, Tianyu Chen, Chen Ding, Tian Li, Haoyi Zhou, He-Liang Huang, Wan-Su Bao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hybrid Photon-magnon Systems: Exploring the Purcell Effect</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.04574</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.04574v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a novel approach to observing the Purcell effect in a photon-magnon coupled (PMC) hybrid system consisting of a yttrium iron garnet (YIG) thin film and a hexagonal ring resonator (HRR) arranged in a planar geometry. This hybrid system has been designed and simulated using the commercial electromagnetic full-wave simulator CST Microwave Studio for various values of damping constant (alpha) of the YIG film while keeping the HRR properties constant. Our results reveal that as the magnon damping increases, the anti-crossing behavior between photon and magnon modes in the transmission spectra diminishes, transitioning the coupled modes into the Purcell regime. This transition is attributed to an enhanced spontaneous emission rate of microwave photons when coupled to lossy magnons, driving the PMC system into the Purcell regime. To elucidate this behavior, we developed a comprehensive theoretical framework based on a quantum model, which accurately describes the observed Purcell phenomena and provides estimations of the PMC strength (g/2pi). Notably, by tuning alpha from 1.4 x 10^-5 to 2.8 x 10^-2, we achieved precise control over (g/2pi) ranging from 63 MHz to 127 MHz. This study highlights the Purcell effect's role in enhancing photon decay rates and establishes a clear relationship with PMC strength. Our work offers a comprehensive method for controlling photon resonance dissipation, opening new avenues for exploring the Purcell effect and its applications in on-chip functional devices leveraging magnon-photon interactions for quantum technologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.04574v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sachin Verma, Abhishek Maurya, Fizaan Khan, Kuldeep Kumar Srivastava, Rajeev Singh, Biswanath Bhoi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Realizing Lattice Surgery on Two Distance-Three Repetition Codes with Superconducting Qubits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.04612</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.04612v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum error correction is needed for quantum computers to be capable of fault-tolerantly executing algorithms using hundreds of logical qubits. Recent experiments have demonstrated subthreshold error rates for state preservation of a single logical qubit. In addition, the realization of universal quantum computation requires the implementation of logical entangling gates. Lattice surgery offers a practical approach for implementing such gates, particularly in planar quantum processor layouts. In this work, we demonstrate lattice surgery between two distance-three repetition-code qubits by splitting a single distance-three surface-code qubit. Using a quantum circuit fault-tolerant to bit-flip errors, we achieve an improvement in the value of the decoded $ZZ$ logical two-qubit observable compared to a similar non-encoded circuit. By preparing the surface-code qubit in initial states parametrized by a varying polar angle, we evaluate the performance of the lattice surgery operation for non-cardinal states on the logical Bloch sphere and employ logical two-qubit tomography to reconstruct the Pauli transfer matrix of the operation. In this way, we demonstrate the functional building blocks needed for lattice surgery operations on larger-distance codes based on superconducting circuits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.04612v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ilya Besedin, Michael Kerschbaum, Jonathan Knoll, Ian Hesner, Lukas B\"odeker, Luis Colmenarez, Luca Hofele, Nathan Lacroix, Christoph Hellings, Fran\c{c}ois Swiadek, Alexander Flasby, Mohsen Bahrami Panah, Dante Colao Zanuz, Markus M\"uller, Andreas Wallraff</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
