<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>quant-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/quant-ph</link>
    <description>quant-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/quant-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 05:00:02 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Multiplexed color centers in a silicon photonic cavity array</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17339</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17339v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Entanglement distribution is central to the modular scaling of quantum processors and establishing quantum networks. Color centers with telecom-band transitions and long spin coherence times are suitable candidates for long-distance entanglement distribution. However, high-bandwidth memory-enhanced quantum communication is limited by high-yield, scalable creation of efficient spin-photon interfaces. Here, we develop a silicon photonics platform consisting of arrays of bus-coupled cavities. The coupling to a common bus waveguide enables simultaneous access to individually addressable cavity-enhanced T center arrays. We demonstrate frequency-multiplexed operation of two T centers in separate photonic crystal cavities. In addition, we investigate the cavity enhancement of a T center through hybridized modes formed between physically distant cavities. Our results show that bus-coupled arrays of cavity-enhanced color centers could enable efficient on-chip and long-distance entanglement distribution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17339v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lukasz Komza, Xueyue Zhang, Hanbin Song, Yu-Lung Tang, Xin Wei, Alp Sipahigil</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Transition from non-ergodic to ergodic dynamics in an autonomous discrete time crystal</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17435</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17435v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider an autonomous system of two coupled single-mode cavities, one of which interacts with a multimode resonator. We demonstrate that for small coupling strengths between single-mode cavities, the Loschmidt echo oscillates periodically in time and spontaneous breaking of time translation symmetry takes place. The Loschmidt echo behavior is an indication of the non-ergodic nature of the system when its evolution is time-reversible. In this regime, the system retains a memory of the initial state under the action of small perturbations. This behavior reveals the presence of a time crystalline order in the autonomous system. An increase in the coupling strength leads to a transition from periodic oscillations to an exponential decay in time of the Loschmidt echo. This corresponds to the transition from non-ergodic to ergodic behavior in the system. We demonstrate that the transition from non-ergodic to ergodic system's behavior can also be observed when changing the number of degrees of freedom in the resonator, which is achieved by changing its length.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17435v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>T. T. Sergeev, A. A. Zyablovsky, E. S. Andrianov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fabry-P\'{e}rot etalon walk-off loss in ring cavities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17558</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17558v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Fabry-P\'erot etalons are widely used for laser frequency control. Inserting them in laser cavities imparts unavoidable walk-off loss and reduces the output power. Here, we treat the technology-relevant case of the walk-off loss of an etalon in a unidirectional ring cavity, which is a standard design of single-frequency lasers. We provide the theory background by discussing the analytic limits. The loss can be efficiently minimized by realignment, or by proper matching of the etalon's surface reflectivity with its refractive index. We numerically calculate the loss in the region uncovered by the analytic limits. We discuss practical laser design considerations, and we perform a tilt-tuning experiment in a single-frequency, solid-state laser setup.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17558v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ulrich Eismann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reproducible generation of green-emitting color centers in hBN using oxygen annealing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17562</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17562v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The ability to generate quantum emitters with reproducible properties in solid-state matrices is crucial for quantum technologies. Here, we show that a high density of close-to-identical single-photon emitters can be created in commercial hexagonal boron nitride using annealing under oxygen atmosphere. This simple procedure yields a uniform in-plane distribution of color centers consistently emitting around 539.4 nm, with a wavelength spread smaller than 1 nm. We present an extensive characterization of their photophysical properties, showing that the emitters are bright and stable, and exhibit narrow lines at low temperatures with minimal spectral diffusion. These characteristics make this family of quantum emitters highly appealing for applications to quantum information science.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17562v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Helmi Fartas, Sa\"id Hassani, Jean-Pierre Hermier, Ngoc Diep Lai, St\'ephanie Buil, Aymeric Delteil</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>End-to-end physics-based modeling of laser-activated color centers in silicon</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17240</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17240v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Color centers are among the most promising candidates for quantum information processing. Central requirements for their practical applications include controlled and efficient local activation in nanophotonic devices and identical spectral features. However, producing color centers in a controlled and reliable way is inherently challenging due to the lack of comprehensive theoretical insights into their formation and the difficulty of streamlining the generation process for rapid in-situ optimization. We address these challenges by developing an end-to-end first-principles model that captures the underlying formation process of color centers. Emitters are activated through laser annealing, which allows for in-situ creation and the possibility of model-based control. Notably, our model enables the estimation of the emitters' inhomogeneous broadening down to 16 GHz in bare silicon, which translates into the creation of emitters with highly similar spectral properties. Finally, we address the challenge of in-situ deterministic activation of color centers in nanophotonic devices by going beyond bare silicon and demonstrating successful laser writing in photonic crystal optical cavities. These results lay the foundation for deterministic and large-scale integration of color centers within quantum photonic platforms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17240v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qiushi Gu, Valeria Saggio, Camille Papon, Alessandro Buzzi, Ian Christen, Christopher Panuski, Carlos Errando-Herranz, Dirk Englund</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectral tuning and nanoscale localization of single color centers in silicon via controllable strain</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17290</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17290v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The development of color centers in silicon enables scalable quantum technologies by combining telecom-wavelength emission and compatibility with mature silicon fabrication. However, large-scale integration requires precise control of each emitter's optical transition to generate indistinguishable photons for quantum networking. Here, we demonstrate a foundry-fabricated photonic integrated circuit (PIC) combining suspended silicon waveguides with a microelectromechanical (MEMS) cantilever to apply local strain and spectrally tune individual G-centers. Applying up to 35 V between the cantilever and the substrate induces a reversible wavelength shift of the zero-phonon line exceeding 100 pm, with no loss in brightness. Moreover, by modeling the strain-induced shifts with a `digital twin' physical model, we achieve vertical localization of color centers with sub-3 nm vertical resolution, directly correlating their spatial position, dipole orientation, and spectral behavior. This method enables on-demand, low-power control of emission spectrum and nanoscale localization of color centers, advancing quantum networks on a foundry-compatible platform.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17290v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alessandro Buzzi, Camille Papon, Matteo Pirro, Odiel Hooybergs, Hamza Raniwala, Valeria Saggio, Carlos Errando-Herranz, Dirk Englund</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermal Radiation Force and Torque on Moving Nanostructures with Anisotropic Optical Response</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17791</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17791v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Nanoscale objects moving relative to a thermal radiation bath experience a drag force due to the imbalance in their interaction with the blue- and redshifted components of the electromagnetic field. Here, we show that, in addition to this drag force, moving nanostructures with an anisotropic optical response experience a lateral force and a torque that substantially modify their trajectory. These phenomena emerge from the additional coupling between the electromagnetic field components polarized parallel and perpendicular to the trajectory, enabled by the anisotropic response of the nanostructure. This work unveils the intricate dynamics of anisotropic nanostructures moving in a thermal radiation bath.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17791v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Juan R. Deop-Ruano, Alejandro Manjavacas</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
