<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>quant-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/quant-ph</link>
    <description>quant-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/quant-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 06 Feb 2025 05:00:03 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 06 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum theory of surface lattice resonances</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.02836</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.02836v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The collective interactions of nanoparticles arranged in periodic structures give rise to high-$Q$ in-plane diffractive modes known as surface lattice resonances (SLRs). While these resonances and their broader implications have been extensively studied within the framework of classical electrodynamics and linear response theory, a quantum optical theory capable of describing the dynamics of these structures, especially in the presence of material nonlinearities, beyond the use of \textit{ad hoc} few-mode approximations is largely missing. To this end, we consider here a lattice of metallic nanoparticles coupled to the background electromagnetic field and derive the quantum input-output relations within the electric dipole approximation. As a first application, we discuss coupling of the nanoparticle array to an external array of emitters and illustrate how the formalism can be extended to molecular optomechanics. Specifically, we show how the high $Q$-factors provided by SLRs can facilitate coupling between the nanoparticle array and collective vibrational modes. Finally, we examine a scenario in which the metallic nanoparticles themselves are replaced with saturable excitonic emitters, illustrating how the nonlinearity of the emitters can be used to switch the SLR condition between different electronic transitions. Our work provides a seamless framework to rigorously model SLR phenomena with quantum emitters without resorting to phenomenological treatments of either the electromagnetic environment or the material degrees of freedom.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.02836v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael Reitz, Stephan van den Wildenberg, Arghadip Koner, George C. Schatz, Joel Yuen-Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Polarization entanglement and qubit error rate dependance on the exciton-phonon coupling in self-assembled quantum dots</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.03413</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.03413v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Polarization entangled photons are the key ingredients of various protocols in quantum computation and quantum key distribution. In particular, for key distributions, a near-unity degree of polarization entanglement is one of the requirements for minimizing the qubit error rates. In this work, we theoretically investigate the polarization entangled photon pairs emitted by a quantum-dot radiative cascade embedded in a micropillar cavity. We develop a polaron master equation theory for incorporating the unavoidable exciton-phonon coupling and investigate the role of phonon-mediated processes and phonon-bath temperature on the degree of entanglement. We show that the phonon-coupling introduces the one-photon and two-photon incoherent processes, as well as the cross-coupling between the two exciton states. It is shown that the phonon-mediated coupling along with the ac-Stark shift and multiphoton emission significantly degrade the entanglement at higher temperatures. Finally, we consider a BBM92 quantum key distribution protocol to investigate the qubit error rate for the given degree of entanglement.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.03413v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Urmimala Dewan, Parvendra Kumar, Amarendra K. Sarma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Accurate Modeling of Directional Couplers with Oxide Cladding: Bridging Simulation and Experiment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.02515</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.02515v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Directional couplers are a fundamental building block in integrated photonics, particularly in quantum applications and optimization-based design where precision is critical. Accurate functionality is crucial to ensure reliable operation within classical and quantum circuits. However, discrepancies between simulations and measurements are frequently observed. These inaccuracies can compromise the performance and scalability of integrated photonic systems, underscoring the critical need for advanced, precise simulation methods that bridge the gap between design and implementation. In this work, we show that this discrepancy can be mainly attributed to density changes in the oxide cladding. We conduct a systematic study involving experimental optical measurements, numerical simulations, and direct electron microscopy imaging to investigate this discrepancy in directional couplers. We find that the impact of cladding density variations on performance increases as feature gaps shrink. By incorporating these effects into our simulations using a novel and physically motivated Effective Trench Medium Model (ETMM), we achieve highly accurate reproduction of experimental measurements. We quantify the effects of cladding density variations on the SU(2) symmetry parameters that govern light propagation in directional couplers. This insight is crucial for advancing the precision of compact device fabrication, enabling reliable simulation of photonic integrated devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.02515v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuval Warshavsky, Yehonathan Drori, Jonatan Piasetzky, Amit Rotem, Ofer Shapiro, Yaron Oz, Haim Suchowski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhancing the hyperpolarizability of crystals with quantum geometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.02660</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.02660v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We demonstrate that higher-order electric susceptibilities in crystals can be enhanced and understood through nontrivial topological invariants and quantum geometry, using one-dimensional $\pi$-conjugated chains as representative model systems. First, we show that the crystalline-symmetry-protected topology of these chains imposes a lower bound on their quantum metric and hyperpolarizabilities. Second, we employ numerical simulations to reveal the tunability of non-linear, quantum geometry-driven optical responses in various one-dimensional crystals in which band topology can be externally controlled. Third, we develop a semiclassical picture to deliver an intuitive understanding of these effects. Our findings offer a firm interpretation of otherwise elusive experimental observations of colossal hyperpolarizabilities and establish guidelines for designing topological materials of any dimensionality with enhanced non-linear optical properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.02660v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wojciech J. Jankowski, Robert-Jan Slager, Michele Pizzochero</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cavity engineering of solid-state materials without external driving</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.03172</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.03172v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Confining electromagnetic fields inside an optical cavity can enhance the light-matter coupling between quantum materials embedded inside the cavity and the confined photon fields. When the interaction between the matter and the photon fields is strong enough, even the quantum vacuum field fluctuations of the photons confined in the cavity can alter the properties of the cavity-embedded solid-state materials at equilibrium and room temperature. This approach to engineering materials with light avoids fundamental issues of laser-induced transient matter states. To clearly differentiate this field from phenomena in driven systems, we call this emerging field cavity materials engineering. In this review, we first present theoretical frameworks, especially, ab initio methods, for describing light-matter interactions in solid-state materials embedded inside a realistic optical cavity. Next, we overview a few experimental breakthroughs in this domain, detailing how the ground state properties of materials can be altered within such confined photonic environments. Moreover, we discuss state-of-the-art theoretical proposals for tailoring material properties within cavities. Finally, we outline the key challenges and promising avenues for future research in this exciting field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.03172v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>I-Te Lu, Dongbin Shin, Mark Kamper Svendsen, Simone Latini, Hannes H\"ubener, Michael Ruggenthaler, Angel Rubio</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
