<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>quant-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/quant-ph</link>
    <description>quant-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/quant-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 05:00:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Sensing the vibration of non-reflective surfaces with 10-dB-squeezed-light enhancement</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.06313</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.06313v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Laser light with squeezed quantum uncertainty is a powerful tool for interferometric sensing. A routine application can be found in gravitational wave observatories. A significant quantum advantage is only achievable if a large fraction of the photons are actually measured. For this reason, quantum-enhanced vibrational measurements of strongly absorbing or scattering surfaces have not been considered so far. Here we demonstrate the strongly quantum-enhanced measurement of the frequency characteristics of surface vibrations in air by measuring the air pressure wave instead. Our squeezed laser beam, which simply passes the vibrating surface, delivers a sensitivity that an ultra-stable conventional light beam in the same configuration can only achieve with ten times the power. The pressure amplitude of a ultrasonic wave of just 0.12 mPa/ Hz was clearly visible with a spatial resolution in the millimetre range and a 1 kHz resolution bandwidth. We envision applications in sensor technology where distant, highly absorbing or optically inaccessible surface vibrations in air are to be measured with limited, e.g. eye-safe, light powers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.06313v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1364/OPTICAQ.542186</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Optica Quantum 3, 1-6 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Pascal Gewecke, Jascha Zander, Roman Schnabel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Multiplexed Programmable Quantum Photonic Network</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07272</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07272v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Entanglement distribution in quantum networks will enable next-generation technologies for quantum-secured communications, distributed quantum computing and sensing. Future quantum networks will require dense connectivity, allowing multiple parties to share entangled states in a reconfigurable manner, while long-distance connections are established through the teleportation of entangled states, namely entanglement swapping. However, developing flexible physical platforms that can distribute entanglement through a high-capacity and scalable architecture remains a significant challenge. Here we realise a multiplexed programmable network where entanglement is routed and teleported between four parties through a reconfigurable multi-port circuit operating on the transverse-spatial photonic degree-of-freedom. We harness the natural mode-mixing process inside a multi-mode fibre and place it between two programmable phase planes to implement high-dimensional operations for two independent photons carrying eight transverse-spatial modes. This complex-medium-based circuit allows for the control of a four-party state where high-fidelity entangled states can be simultaneously distributed over multiple channels with different on-demand configurations. Our design allows us to break away from the limited planar geometry and bypass the control and fabrication challenges of conventional integrated platforms. Our demonstration showcases the potential of this architecture for enabling quantum networks with scalable and versatile connectivity that is fully compatible with existing communications infrastructure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07272v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Natalia Herrera Valencia, Annameng Ma, Suraj Goel, Saroch Leedumrongwatthanakun, Francesco Graffitti, Alessandro Fedrizzi, Will McCutcheon, Mehul Malik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-efficiency, high-count-rate 2D superconducting nanowire single-photon detector array</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07357</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07357v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Superconducting nanowire single-photon detectors (SNSPDs) are the current leading technology for the detection of single-photons in the near-infrared (NIR) and short-wave infrared (SWIR) spectral regions, due to record performance in terms of detection efficiency, low dark count rate, minimal timing jitter, and high maximum count rates. The various geometry and design parameters of SNSPDs are often carefully tailored to specific applications, resulting in challenges in optimising each performance characteristic without adversely impacting others. In particular, when scaling to larger array formats, the key challenge is to manage the heat load generated by the many readout cables in the cryogenic cooling system. Here we demonstrate a practical, self-contained 64-pixel SNSPD array system which exhibits high performance of all operational parameters, for use in the strategically important SWIR spectral region. The detector is an 8x8 array of 27.5 x 27.8 {\mu}m pixels on a 30 {\mu}m pitch, which leads to an 80 -- 85% fill factor. At a wavelength of 1550nm, a uniform average per-pixel photon detection efficiency of 77.7% was measured and the observed system detection efficiency (SDE) across the entire array was 65%. A full performance characterisation is presented, including a dark count rate of 20 cps per pixel, full-width-half-maximum (FWHM) jitter of 100 ps per pixel, a 3-dB maximum count rate of 645 Mcps and no evidence of crosstalk at the 0.1% level. This camera system therefore facilitates a variety of picosecond time-resolved measurement-based applications that include biomedical imaging, quantum communications, and long-range single-photon light detection and ranging (LiDAR) and 3D imaging.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07357v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fiona Fleming, Will McCutcheon, Emma E. Wollman, Andrew D. Beyer, Vikas Anant, Boris Korzh, Jason P. Allmaras, Lautaro Narv\'aez, Saroch Leedumrongwatthanakun, Gerald S. Buller, Mehul Malik, Matthew D. Shaw</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
