<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>quant-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/quant-ph</link>
    <description>quant-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/quant-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 05:00:02 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Benchmarking of Fluorescence Lifetime Measurements using Time-Frequency Correlated Photons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08870</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08870v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The investigation of fluorescence lifetime became an important tool in biology and medical science. So far, established methods of fluorescence lifetime measurements require the illumination of the investigated probes with pulsed or amplitude-modulated light. In this paper, we examine the limitations of an innovative method of fluorescence lifetime using time-frequency correlated photons generated by a continuous-wave source. For this purpose, we investigate the lifetime of IR-140 to demonstrate the functional principle and its dependencies on different experimental parameters. We also compare this technique with state-of-the-art FLIM and observed an improved figure-of-merit. Finally, we discuss the potential of a quantum advantage.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08870v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tobias Bernd G\"abler, Nitish Jain, Patrick Then, Christian Eggeling, Markus Gr\"afe, Valerio Flavio Gili</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectral and temporal properties of type-II parametric down-conversion: The impact of losses during state generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08917</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08917v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we theoretically study spectral and temporal properties of pulsed spontaneous parametric down-conversion (SPDC) generated in lossy waveguides. Our theoretical approach is based on the formalism of Gaussian states and the Langevin equation, which is elaborated for weak parametric down-conversion and photon-number-unresolved click detection. Using the example of frequency-degenerate type-II SPDC generated under pump-idler group-velocity-matching condition, we show how the joint-spectral intensity, mode structure, normalized second-order correlation function, and Hong-Ou-Mandel interference pattern depend on internal losses of the SPDC process. In addition, we propose a new method for the experimental determination of internal losses of nonlinear waveguides which is based on the measurement of the normalized second-order correlation functions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08917v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Denis A. Kopylov, Michael Stefszky, Torsten Meier, Christine Silberhorn, Polina R. Sharapova</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Integrated Photonic Programmable Random Matrix Generator with Minimal Active Components</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08953</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08953v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Random matrices are fundamental in photonic computing because of their ability to model and enhance complex light interactions and signal processing capabilities. In manipulating classical light, random operations are utilized for random projections and dimensionality reduction, which are important for analog signal processing, computing, and imaging. In quantum information processing, random unitary operations are essential to boson sampling algorithms for multiphoton states in linear photonic circuits. In photonic circuits, random operations are realized through disordered structures resulting in fixed unitary operations or through large meshes of interferometers and reconfigurable phase shifters, which require a large number of phase shifters. In this article, we introduce a compact photonic circuit for generating random matrices by utilizing programmable phase modulation layers interlaced with a fixed mixing operator. We show that using only two random phase layers is sufficient for producing output optical signals with a white-noise profile, even for highly sparse input optical signals. We experimentally demonstrate these results using a silicon photonics circuit with tunable thermal phase shifters and utilize waveguide lattices as mixing layers. The proposed circuit offers a practical method for generating random matrices for photonic information processing and for applications in data encryption.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08953v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kevin Zelaya, Mostafa Honari-Latifpour, Mohammad-Ali Miri</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
