<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>quant-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/quant-ph</link>
    <description>quant-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/quant-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 05:00:02 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Frequency auto-homogenization using group-velocity-matched downconversion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.02466</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.02466v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: With the stability of integrated photonics at network nodes and the advantages of photons as flying qubits, photonic quantum information processing (PQIP) makes quantum networks increasingly scalable. However, scaling up PQIP requires the preparation of many identical single photons which is limited by the spectral distinguishability of integrated single-photon sources due to variations in fabrication or local environment. To address this, we introduce frequency auto-homogenization via group-velocity-matched downconversion to remove spectral distinguishability in varying quantum emitters. We present our theory using $\chi^{(2)}$ quantum frequency conversion and show proof-of-principle data in a free-space optical setup.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.02466v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dylan Heberle, Christopher C. Tison, James Schneeloch, A. Matthew Smith, Paul M. Alsing, Jeffrey Moses, Michael L. Fanto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhanced quantum magnetometry with a laser-written integrated photonic diamond chip</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.02478</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.02478v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: An ensemble of negatively charged nitrogen-vacancy centers in diamond can act as a precise quantum sensor even under ambient conditions. In particular, to optimize thier sensitivity, it is crucial to increase the number of spins sampled and maximize their coupling to the detection system, without degrading their spin properties. In this paper, we demonstrate enhanced quantum magnetometry via a high-quality buried laser-written waveguide in diamond with a 4.5 ppm density of nitrogen-vacancy centers. We show that the waveguide-coupled nitrogen-vacancy centers exhibit comparable spin coherence properties as that of nitrogen-vacancy centers in pristine diamond using time-domain optically detected magnetic resonance spectroscopy. Waveguide-enhanced magnetic field sensing is demonstrated in a fiber-coupled integrated photonic chip, where probing an increased volume of high-density spins results in 63 pT.Hz$^{-1/2}$ of DC-magnetic field sensitivity and 20 pT.Hz$^{-1/2}$ of AC magnetic field sensitivity. This on-chip sensor realizes at least an order of magnitude improvement in sensitivity compared to the conventional confocal detection setup, paving the way for microscale sensing with nitrogen-vacancy ensembles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.02478v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yanzhao Guo, Giulio Coccia, Vinaya Kumar Kavatamane, Argyro N. Giakoumaki, Anton N. Vetlugin, Roberta Ramponi, Cesare Soci, Paul E. Barclay, John P. Hadden, Anthony J. Bennett, Shane M. Eaton</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
